<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?> <eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>QE00269</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCQD</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Queensland</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Event</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2011-10-28">2011-10-28</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Cate O'Neill</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-03-18">2016-03-18</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00269b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>event</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="Also known as"><part>Forde Inquiry</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1998-01-01">1998</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1999-12-31">1999</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<biogHist>
<abstract>In August 1998 in Queensland, the Minister for Families, Youth and Community Care established a Commission of Inquiry to examine whether there had been any abuse, mistreatment or neglect of children in Queensland institutions. This Inquiry is widely known as the Forde Inquiry, in reference to the Chairperson, Leneen Forde. In May 1999, the Committee presented its report. It found numerous incidents of unsafe, improper and illegal treatment of children in Queensland institutions, including cases of sexual, physical, emotional and systems abuse. The Queensland government made its response to the recommendations of the Inquiry in August 1999. The government, in collaboration with religious authorities, issued a joint formal statement of apology in 1999.</abstract>
<p>The Queensland Government commissioned the Forde Inquiry to investigate the treatment of children in licensed government and non-government institutions in Queensland. The inquiry covered 159 institutions from 1911 to 1999, excluding foster care and institutions providing care for children with disabilities or those suffering from acute or chronic health problems.</p>
<p>The inquiry gathered evidence in a number of ways. Research was commissioned into a broad range of areas relevant to the inquiry. It received 151 written submissions from former residents and staff of children's institutions, as well as evidence from professional and academic experts. The commission held public hearings about allegations of handcuffing of juvenile offenders at John Oxley Youth Detention Centre in 1989.</p>
<p>Commissioners and staff visited facilities in current use and also inspected institutions that were no longer operating (including Silky Oaks Haven for Children, Nazareth House, St Joseph's Home, Neerkol and Kalimna Vocational Centre for Girls), so that the inquiry staff had 'the opportunity to interpret evidence in a more meaningful way'.</p>
<p>The inquiry found abuse had occurred and its report made 42 recommendations relating to contemporary child protection practices, youth justice and redress of past abuse.</p>
<p>The Report stated the commission of inquiry was concerned largely with the period between 1930 and 1980, and that most of its evidence was drawn from the following institutions:</p>
<p>Alkira, Salvation Army Home for Boys in Indooroopilly; W.R. Black Home in Chelmer; Blackheath Home, in Oxley; BoysTown, in Beaudesert; Carramar Children's Home and Carramar Receiving and Assessment Centre, in Townsville; Enoggera Boys' Home; Horton House in Toowoomba; Good Shepherd Home for Girls (later known as the Mt Maria Re-education Centre) in Mitchelton; Holy Cross Home in Wooloowin; John Oxley Youth Detention Centre in Wacol; Margaret Marr Memorial Home for Boys in Wynnum; Nazareth House in Wynnum North; Riverview Training Farm; Silky Oaks Haven for Children in Manly West, St Vincent's Home, Nudgee; St Joseph's Home, Neerkol; Tufnell Home in Nundah; Warilda Children's Home (previously the Diamantina Receiving Home) in Wooloowin; Westbrook Farm School and Training Centre; and the Wilson Youth Hospital in Windsor.</p>
<p>Following the release of the report, the Queensland government and representatives of six major churches made the Apology to those harmed in Queensland institutions during their childhood.</p>
<p>From 2007 to 2010, there was a Redress Scheme in Queensland, in response to recommendations in the commission's report.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00003b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
BoysTown (1961 - 2001)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>BoysTown was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00160b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Silky Oaks Haven for Children (1940 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Commission of inquiry into abuse of children in Queensland institutions visited the site of Silky Oaks Haven for Children.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00131b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Nazareth House (1926 - 1982)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Commission of inquiry into abuse of children in Queensland institutions visited the site of Nazareth House.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00622b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Training Farm for Boys (1966 - 1969)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Training Farm for Boys was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00101b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Kalimna Vocational Centre for Girls (1962 - 1977)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Commission of inquiry into abuse of children in Queensland institutions visited the site of Kalimna Vocational Centre for Girls.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00504b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Allan Allaway interviewed by Rob Willis in the Forgotten Australians and Former Child Migrants oral history project (2010)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Allan Allaway discusses the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Childen in Queensland Institutions in his oral history interview.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00450b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Commission for Children, Young People and Child Guardian (2000 - 2014)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The creation of the Commission for Children, Young People and Child Guardian was in response to recommendations made by the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00533b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Farm Home for Boys, Westbrook (1919 - 1966)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Farm Home for Boys, Westbrook was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00466b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Redress Scheme, Queensland (2007 - 2010)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Redress Scheme, Queensland was established in response to recommendations of the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00155b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
St Vincent's Home for Children (1935 - 1971)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>St Vincent's Home for Children was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00117b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Margaret Marr Memorial Home for Boys (1924 - 1973)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Margaret Marr Memorial Home for Boys was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00611b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Boys Home, Indooroopilly (1946 - 1968)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Boys Home, Indooroopilly was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00049b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Alkira, Salvation Army Home for Boys (1969 - 1983)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Alkira, Salvation Army Home for Boys was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00039b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
John Oxley Youth Detention Centre (1987 - 2001)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Commission of inquiry into abuse of children in Queensland institutions held public hearings relating to the treatment of juvenile offenders at John Oxley Youth Detention Centre in 1989.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00058b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Blackheath Home, Oxley (c. 1924 - 1963)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Blackheath Home, Oxley was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00533b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Farm Home for Boys, Westbrook (1919 - 1966)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Farm Home for Boys, Westbrook was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00198b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Carramar Children's Home (1964 - 1967)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Carramar Children's Home was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00036b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Carramar Receiving and Assessment Centre (1967 - 1995)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Carramar Receiving and Assessment Centre was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00088b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Horton House (1963 - 1976)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Horton House was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00195b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Warilda Children's Home and Warilda Infants' Home (1964 - 1967)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Warilda Children's Home and Warilda Infants' Home were institutions mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00193b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Diamantina Receiving Depot and Infants' Home (1910 - 1962)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Diamantina Receiving Depot and Infants' Home was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00047b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Wilson Youth Hospital (1961 - 1983)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Wilson Youth Hospital was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00536b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Westbrook Youth Detention Centre (1993 - 1994)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Westbrook Youth Detention Centre was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00082b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Holy Cross Home (1965 - 1973)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Holy Cross Home was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00126b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Mt Maria Re-Education Centre, Mitchelton (1966 - 1973)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Mt Maria Re-Education Centre was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00040b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Karrala House (1963 - 1971)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Karrala House was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00172b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Tufnell Home (1901 - 1993)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Tufnell Home was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00069b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Enoggera Boys' Home (1906 - 1978)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Enoggera Boys' Home was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00574b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Good Shepherd Home for Girls (1930 - 1966)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Good Shepherd Home for Girls was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00057b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
W. R. Black Home (1928 - 1965)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>W.R. Black Home was an institution mentioned by a number of witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Queensland</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Queensland</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/biogs/QE00269b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/bib/QP0000656.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Queensland Government response to recommendations of the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions - Progress Report</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Queensland Government response to recommendations of the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions - Progress Report</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Queensland government</publisher>
<date>2001</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://fordefoundation.org.au/u/lib/cms/forde-govt-resp-progress.pdf"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/bib/QP0000609.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Support for Forgotten Australians</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Support for Forgotten Australians</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Queensland Government</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Queensland Government home</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.qld.gov.au/community/getting-support-health-social-issue/support-for-forgotten-australians/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/bib/QP0000084.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Report of the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions</name>
<title render="italic">Report of the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions</title>
<imprint>
<place>Brisbane</place>
<publisher>Queensland. Department of Families, Youth and Community Care</publisher>
<date>1999</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/bib/QP0000222.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Lives of Uncommon Children: Reflections of Forgotten Australians</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Lives of Uncommon Children: Reflections of Forgotten Australians</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Micah Projects Inc.</publisher>
<date>2009</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.micahprojects.org.au/resource_files/micah/IR_84_Lives-of-Uncommon-Children-Reflections-of-Forgotten-Australians.pdf"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/bib/QP0000200.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Queensland Government Response to Recommendations of the Commission of Inquiry into the Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Queensland Government Response to Recommendations of the Commission of Inquiry into the Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Queensland Government</publisher>
<date>1999</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://fordefoundation.org.au/u/lib/cms/forde-govt-response.pdf"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/bib/QP0000159.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Apology to those harmed in Queensland institutions during their childhood signed by the Government in collaboration with churches</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Queensland Government</name>
<title render="quoted">Apology to those harmed in Queensland institutions during their childhood signed by the Government in collaboration with churches</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Queensland Government</publisher>
<date>1999</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href=""></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/bib/QP0000158.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Report of the Commission of Inquiry into Child Abuse in Queensland institutions</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Report of the Commission of Inquiry into Child Abuse in Queensland institutions</title>
<imprint>
<place>Brisbane</place>
<publisher>Queensland Government</publisher>
<date>1999</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.qld.gov.au/community/documents/getting-support-health-social-issue/forde-comminquiry.pdf"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/objects/QD0000286.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Apology to those harmed in Queensland institutions during their childhood</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Apology to those harmed in Queensland institutions during their childhood</unittitle>
<unitdate>1999</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a copy of the Apology to those harmed in Queensland institutions during their childhood from 1999, with signatures of representatives of the Queensland government and six churches.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Queensland government</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/objects/QD0000284.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Forde Inquiry staff</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Forde Inquiry staff</unittitle>
<unitdate>1998?</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a copy of a photograph that was published on p.4 of the report of the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse of Children in Queensland Institutions. It shows commissioners and staff visiting the former site of a children's institution.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Queensland government</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/qld/objects/QD0000283.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Institutions mentioned by witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse in Queensland Institutions</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Institutions mentioned by witnesses to the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse in Queensland Institutions</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1998</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a figure that was published on p.8 of the report of the Commission of Inquiry into Abuse in Queensland Institutions, to represent the extent to which institutions were mentioned in evidence during the Inquiry.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Queensland government</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>