<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>E000316</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCVC</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Organisation</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2009-06-04">2009-06-04</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Cate O'Neill</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-04-26">2016-04-26</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000316b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Brookside Private Reformatory for Protestant Girls</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Brookside Reformatory</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1887-01-01">1887</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1900-12-31">c. 1900</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Reformatory</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Non-denominational</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Home</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Brookside Private Reformatory for Protestant Girls was established in 1887 by Mrs W. T. Rowe. It was located in the town of Cape Clear, near Scarsdale. Many girls ended up in Brookside after unsuccessful boarding out or foster care placements. It closed in 1900.</abstract>
<p>Private reformatories such as Brookside were made possible by the Juvenile Offenders Act 1887.</p>
<p>The Brookside Private Reformatory for Protestant Girls was established in December 1887 by Mrs W. T. Rowe. It was located in the town of Cape Clear, near Scarsdale. Mrs Rowe was the daughter of Archbishop Stretch of Melbourne.</p>
<p>In a visit to Brookside in 1890 reported on in the <span style="font-style:italic">Age</span>, the author 'Mem' describes Mrs Rowe as 'a lady who has made it her life work to assist in the rescue of young girls whose surroundings have, almost inevitably in most cases, brought them into trouble'.</p>
<p>Brookside was a private, or 'assisted', reformatory, made possible by the Juvenile Offenders Act 1887, where the government paid 5 shillings a week towards the maintenance of girls in the reformatory. (The government also ran a reformatory for girls in Coburg, and one for boys in Ballarat.) A government report from 1890 stated that Mrs Rowe and the Good Shepherd Sisters (who ran reformatories at Abbotsford and Oakleigh) 'have the same entire control and guardianship over their wards as that enjoyed by the Superintendent of the Boys' Reformatory, a Government institution'.</p>
<p>The 1872 Report of the Royal Commission on Reformatory and Industrial Schools had commended the reformatory work of the Good Shepherd Sisters with Catholic girls, and stated the 'extreme desirability' of work with Protestant girls being in private, rather than government, hands.</p>
<p>The Secretary urged the same in the Departmental Report of 1886, leading to the establishment of Brookside.</p>
<p>The Department saw Brookside's rural location as ideal for such an institution, being 'away from large towns, gold-fields and factories, and surrounded within moderate distances by the residences of suitable employers'. Another plus, according to the Secretary of the Department, was the 'absolute separation from disreputable friends and relatives'.</p>
<p>Brookside's remote situation also meant that absconding was 'practically unknown'. This was also mentioned by 'Mem' in the <span style="font-style:italic">Age</span> report:</p>
<p>'There is no lock and key supervision here, but liberty to scamper among the fields, full and free trust when the cows have to be brought home, hay has to be made in the paddock beyond the Creek, or the wood cart has to be loaded in the forest land still further away … Green fields, I'm sure most people will agree, are a very much more wholesome restraint than iron bolts and bars.'</p>
<p>Older and younger girls were housed separately at Brookside, Mem noted with approval, so that young girls were protected from 'contamination' by the older and more worldly girls.</p>
<p>Mem reported that one duty the Brookside girls performed was looking after 'the baby', who turned out to be a two-year-old Aboriginal boy, 'a protégé of one of Mrs Rowe's daughters, who is for the time being having a holiday stay at Brookside'.</p>
<p>Many girls ended up in Brookside after unsuccessful boarding out or foster care placements.</p>
<p>Punishment at Brookside was described by Mem as 'neither severe nor frequently inflicted'. Girls being punished had to perform their usual duties for three days without companionship, that is, not in solitary confinement, but not allowed to talk to the others.</p>
<p>Girls usually went from Brookside to a 'service home'. Mem wrote that demand for the girls' services from local squatters and farmers were 'more numerous than could be granted'. Ladies from Brookside continued contact with girls once they were placed in service, and records were kept of all correspondence with each girl and of their 'career' post-reformatory.</p>
<p>In 1890, there were an average of 20 girls at Brookside Reformatory. When it began some two years earlier, it had room for six. The government contributed 5 shillings per week for each girl.</p>
<p>Mem reflected that the barracks system operating at the Boys' Reformatory at Ballarat would not be suitable for girls, as training in domestic service cannot be provided in such conditions.</p>
<p>In 1899, newspaper articles criticised the conditions at Brookside Reformatory. This coverage resulted from the claims of a group of girls who had absconded from the Reformatory, about their harsh treatment at Brookside. The girls told police about punishments including floggings, having their hair cut, being confined to bed, and bread-and-water diets. However, an article in the <span style="font-style:italic">Argus</span> reported that all the girls unanimously exonerated Mrs Rowe.</p>
<p>Staff from the Department of Industrial Schools held a subsequent inquiry into the girls' claims.</p>
<p>A newspaper article from August 1899 stated that Mrs Rowe was superintendent of Brookside, but that she lived at Glenfine, eight miles away. Miss King and Miss Hamilton managed the girls at Brookside, nine were living in one cottage, and four girls in another cottage. The article stated that a 'branch reformatory' had opened in Heywood, receiving about half of the 40 or so girls living at Brookside.</p>
<p>The journalist discussed Miss King's qualifications as a matron at Brookside. Despite having the 'best of motives', he doubted that Miss King's past experiences as a machinist in Ballarat, and working as a biblewoman with the Wesleyan mission qualified her to 'venture into a field like this'.</p>
<p>Miss Hamilton, although also untrained, was described as 'in every way a better stamp of woman', being more intelligent and kindly than Miss King.</p>
<p>Of the girls and young woman at Brookside, the article declared that they were probably some of the Department's 'hardest cases', almost all of them 'grossly immoral'.</p>
<p>The 'Special Reporter' concluded that:</p>
<p>'the authorities at Brookside are untrained and unsuitable for their difficult task; that the system pursued is antiquated and non-reformatory in its effects; and that the inspection is so inefficient and casual as to be practically a negligible quantity.'</p>
<p>An editorial in the <span style="font-style:italic">Argus</span> on 4 August 1899 declared, 'It is a growing scandal in Australia that the vast state contributions to charitable institutions are unaccompanied by adequate state supervision'.</p>
<p>On 10 August 1899 in the Legislative Assembly, the Under-Secretary made his rejoinder to claims published in <span style="font-style:italic">The Argus</span> about Brookside and private reformatories in general, defending the Department's management and oversight of the institution.</p>
<p>In August 1900, the matron, Miss King, purchased the Brookside Estate upon which the Reformatory was situated.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1887-01-01">1887</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1887-12-31">1887</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Scarsdale</placeEntry>
<event>Location - Mrs Rowe's private reformatory, Brookside, was located at Cape Clear, near Scarsdale</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000818b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Reformatories, Youth Training Centres, Juvenile Justice Centres and Youth Justice Centres: the government response to juvenile correction (1887 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000179b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
The Juvenile Offenders' Act 1887 (1888 - 1890)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Brookside Private Reformatory was established under the provisions of the Juvenile Offenders' Act 1887.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000219b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Reformatory (1864 - c. 1954)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>'Brookside' was a private reformatory established under the terms of the Juvenile Offenders Act 1887.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000315b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Government Reformatory for Protestant Girls (1864? - 1893)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Brookside Private Reformatory for Protestant Girls', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Brookside Private Reformatory for Protestant Girls</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000316b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/bib/P00000226.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Orphanages in Ballarat – brief historical notes (draft)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Golding, Frank</name>
<title render="italic">Orphanages in Ballarat – brief historical notes (draft)</title>
<imprint>
<date>2009</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/bib/P00000103.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: The Development and Working of the Reformatory and Preventive Systems in the Colony of Victoria, Australia, 1864-1890</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Guillaume, George; Connor, Edward C.</name>
<title render="italic">The Development and Working of the Reformatory and Preventive Systems in the Colony of Victoria, Australia, 1864-1890</title>
<imprint>
<place>Melbourne</place>
<publisher>Government Printer</publisher>
<date>1891</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/bib/P00000104.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Farm Life for Reformatory Girls: being an account of a visit to 'Brookside' Private Reformatory with editorial comments</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Mem</name>
<title render="italic">Farm Life for Reformatory Girls: being an account of a visit to 'Brookside' Private Reformatory with editorial comments</title>
<imprint>
<place>Melbourne</place>
<publisher>Melville, Mullen &amp; Slade and M.L. Hutchison</publisher>
<date>1890</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>