<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>E000347</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCVC</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Event</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2009-06-18">2009-06-18</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Cate O'Neill</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2015-02-25">2015-02-25</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000347b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>event</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Care of Children Committee</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Curtis Committee</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1946-01-01">1946</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1946-12-31">1946</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Start Place</placeRole>
<placeEntry>United Kingdom</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<functions>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>In 1946, the Care of Children Committee, chaired by Dame Myra Curtis, presented its report to the House of Commons. The Report of the Care of Children Committee (Training in Child Care) was a landmark report, indicating a major shift in child welfare theory, which was later to influence child welfare policy in Victoria.</abstract>
<p>The Curtis Report, as it is commonly known, led to the passing of the Children's Act 1948 in the United Kingdom. The Report of the Committee expresses members' shock and dismay at what they describe as 'the remote and impersonal relations' existing within children's homes. The predominant concerns of the Committee were not with physical and material conditions in the homes, but with the care and attention children needed to receive.</p>
<p>In the mid twentieth century, there was a growing awareness of the needs, and indeed the rights, of every child to stability, affection and emotional security. The United Nations' Department of Social Affairs published the report, <span style="font-style:italic">Children deprived of a normal life</span> in 1951. An important figure in this shift in understanding is Dr Edward John Mostyn Bowlby, the founder of attachment theory. Bowlby published the landmark book, <span style="font-style:italic">Children and the growth of love</span> in 1953.</p>
<p>Key recommendations of the Curtis report were:</p>
<list><item>to encourage the development of the family group home system (family groups were not to exceed 12 children, and a mix of ages and sexes was preferable in each home)</item>
<item>to keep siblings together in placements wherever possible</item>
<item>to educate children in care in local schools</item></list>
<p>The report also contained specific instructions for the good management of institutions. The Committee stated that the main requirements for a child's substitute home were:</p>
<list><item>Affection and personal interest; understanding of his defects; care for his future; respect for his personality and regard for his self esteem</item>
<item>Stability</item>
<item>Opportunity of making the best of his ability and aptitudes</item>
<item>A share in the common life of a small group of people in a homely environment</item></list>
<p>The Committee reported that, however well children's material needs were met in Homes,</p>
<p>'on the human and emotional side, they continually feel the lack of affection and personal interest. The longing for caresses from strangers, so common among little children in Homes, is in striking and painful contrast to the behaviour of the normal child of the same age in his parents' home. The lack of the mother's fondling cannot of course be entirely made good, but something must be provided which gives the child the feeling that there is a secure and affectionate personal relation in his life.'</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000350b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Family Group Home
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Care of Children Committee', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Care of Children Committee</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000347b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/bib/P00000129.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Report of the Care of Children Committee (Training in Child Care) - paper number cmd. 6922</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Report of the Care of Children Committee (Training in Child Care) - paper number cmd. 6922</title>
<imprint>
<date>1946</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">House of Commons Parliamentary Papers</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://parlipapers.chadwyck.co.uk.ezproxy.slv.vic.gov.au/home.do"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>