<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>E000886</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCVC</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Archival Collection</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-06-27">2013-06-27</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Cate O'Neill</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-07-27">2016-07-27</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000886b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>concept</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Records held by Connections UnitingCare</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1910-01-01">c. 1910</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The collection held by Connections UnitingCare's Adoption Information Service dates from around 1910. It includes records of the Methodist Babies' Home, Presbyterian Babies Home', Presbyterian Sisterhood, Fairfield Girls' Memorial Home, Canterbury Family Centre, Copelen Street and Connections UnitingCare. The types of records include admission books, adoption registers, client files, medical cards, and photographs.</abstract>
<h4>Access Conditions</h4>
<p>Connections UnitingCare's Adoption Information Service enables adopted persons, adoptive parents, parents who have relinquished their child and other family members to obtain information about an adoption. It also provides access to records to former Wards of State and Forgotten Australians who spent time in children's Homes run by its predecessor organisations.</p>
<p>Please note that the Adoption Information Service does not have records from Kildonan or any Kildonan services.</p>
<h4>Records</h4>
<p>More specifically, the collection includes:</p>
<h4>Methodist Babies' Home</h4>
<list><item>Admission books 1929-1971<br />
Contains: child's original name, date of birth, hospital where born, admission date, birthparent's names, ages and addresses where available, adoptive parents' names and addresses, placement date, date of adoption order.</item>
<item>Adoption books 1929-1971<br />
A-Z Directory of adoptive parents. Contains: Adoptive parent's names and address; child's original name, date of birth, placement date, date of adoption order.</item>
<item>Register of adoptions and admissions 1929-1966<br />
Contains: Child's original name, date of birth, admission date, discharge date, adoptive parents' surname, date of adoption order.</item>
<item>Masterbook 1952-1971<br />
Monthly listing of admissions, discharges, placements and adoption orders granted. Contains: Child's original name, admission date, placement date, adoptive parents' names and addresses.</item>
<item>Admission slips 1959-1968<br />
Birth mother admission slips. Contains: Child's original name, date of birth, hospital where born, birth mother's name, birth father's name, birthmother's parents' names, birthparents' religion, qualitative remarks about the birthparents and appearance of the child.</item>
<item>Children's birth details 1931-1940, 1965-1966<br />
Contains: child's original name, child's date of birth, child's birth details including weight and length.</item>
<item>Summary of admissions 1929-1974<br />
Contains: child's original name, date of birth, place of birth, admission date, baby's condition on entry including weight, birth mother's religion.</item>
<item>Child medical cards 1929-1974<br />
Medical information on the birth of all babies admitted to the Methodist Babies Home 1929-1972. Contains: child's alias used by the nurses at the Methodist Babies Home, child's date of birth, limited medical information on birth parents.</item>
<item>Photographs c.1930s</item></list>
<h4>Presbyterian Babies' Home</h4>
<list><item>Record of admissions 1928-1972<br />
Contains: child's original name, age when admitted, birthplace, birthparents' names, birthparents' address, admission date, discharge date, child's destination upon leaving Presbyterian Babies Home (e.g. If returned to birthparents or adopted).</item>
<item>Particulars of new babies 1955-1976<br />
Contains: child's original name, date of birth, time of birth, hospital where born, weight at birth, birth mother's full name, discharge date, some dates of adoption order and surnames of adoptive parents.</item>
<item>Intake registers 1965-1979<br />
Contains: date of admission, birth mother's name, birth mother's marital status, birth mother's town of residence, who referred by.</item>
<item>Adoption book 1961-1971<br />
Contains: adoptive parent's names, town of residence, religion, occupations, age of adoptive parents, reason for requesting a child, adoptee's name, date of placement.</item>
<item>Admission book 1953-1976<br />
Contains: birth mother's name, birth fathers name, child's original name, child's date of birth and birth place, admission date, birth mothers address, reason for admission.</item>
<item>Case book 1961-1971<br />
Contains: adoptive parent's names, town of residence, religion, occupations, age of adoptive parents, reason for requesting a child, adoptee's name, date of placement.</item>
<item>Foster care and adoption applicant register 1948-1971<br />
Contains: birth mother's name, birth fathers name, child's original name, child's date of birth and birth place, admission date, birth mothers address, reason for admission.</item>
<item>Record of State Wards 1957-1976<br />
Contains: child's ward number, child's name and gender, child's date of birth, admission and discharge date, some birth parents' names and addresses, where discharged to</item>
<item>Record of infants admitted 1966-1976<br />
Contains: Child's original name, Child's date of birth, date of admission, adoptive parents' surname, date of adoption order.</item>
<item>Record of adoptions 1971-1974<br />
Contains: Child's original name, child's date of birth, hospital where born, admission date, discharge date, monthly list of adoptions.</item>
<item>Discharge documents 1961-1969<br />
Alphabetised birth mother patient records. Contains: birth mother's medical information including blood type, birth mother's date of birth, child's date of birth, birth mother's date of discharge, child's destination upon leaving Presbyterian Babies Home (e.g. If returned to birthparents or adopted.</item>
<item>Visitors book 1928-1969<br />
Contains: names and addresses of visitors</item>
<item>List of nurses 1928-1952<br />
Contains: Full name of nurse, address, age, religion, educational attainment, commenced and finished dates, status of examinations, who they reports to, certificate and badge.</item>
<item>Ledger of payments 1956-1973<br />
Contains: date of payment, batch number assigned, surname of payer, date paid to, amount paid.</item>
<item>Photo album 1974-1975<br />
A former mothercraft nurse who trained at the Presbyterian Babies' Home has deposited copies of images from her private photo album at Connections UnitingCare. There are pictures of children, staff and buildings - some of the children are identified.</item></list>
<h4>Presbyterian Sisterhood Home</h4>
<list><item>Admission books 1910-1975<br />
Contains: birth mother's name, age and admission date. Child's original name and date of birth.</item>
<item>Register of girls and babies in residence 1933-1976<br />
Contains: yearly and monthly list of mothers in residence and babies born, birth mother's name and admission date, child's original name and date of birth, duration of stay in the Sisterhood, destination of birth mother after leaving Sisterhood, destination of child after leaving Sisterhood, date of adoption order.</item>
<item>Record of mothers and babies 1953-1967<br />
Contains: child's original name, child's time and date of birth, place of birth, birth mother's name and age, child's birth weight, delivering doctor, date of discharge, days in hospital, destination of child after leaving Sisterhood (e.g. Returned to birthmother, to adoptive parents, made ward of the state), destination of birth mother after leaving Sisterhood, adoptive parents' names, placement date.</item>
<item>Mary Dickens Wing case books 1953-1970<br />
Contains: birth mother's details, labour details, baby's gender and date of birth, medication administered.</item></list>
<h4>Fairfield Girls Memorial Home</h4>
<list><item>Admission forms 1952 - Contains: birth mother's name, address, date of admission, date of birth, place of birth, marital status, religion.</item></list>
<h4>Canterbury Family Centre</h4>
<list><item>Client files 1979-2000</item></list>
<h4>Copelen Street</h4>
<list><item>Client files 1979-1995</item></list>
<h4>Connections UnitingCare</h4>
<list><item>Adoption and Permanent Care client files 2000-present</item></list>
<h4>Finding Aids</h4>
<p>Connections UnitingCare's Adoption Information Service has an in-house developed database which can be searched using a number of parameters including names, date of birth, and admission/discharge dates. Scanned images of the records in the collection are stored on the organisation's server and attached to the relevant case files directly within the database.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000223b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Connections UnitingCare (2000 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000887b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Contact Details">
Adoption Information Service, Connections UnitingCare - Contact Details
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000066b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Methodist Babies' Home (1929 - c. 1974)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000569b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Presbyterian Sisterhood Home (1909 - c. 1978)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000224b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Presbyterian Babies' Home (1928 - 1977)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000232b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Methodist Church (c. 1851 - 1977)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000066b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Methodist Babies' Home (1929 - c. 1974)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000226b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Copelen Street Family Centre (1974 - 1991)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000588b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Copelen Child and Family Services (1991 - 1998)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000589b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Copelen (1998 - 2000)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000225b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Canterbury Family Centre (1977 - 2000)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Records held by Connections UnitingCare', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Records held by Connections UnitingCare</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000886b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/bib/P00001158.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: The importance of photos</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">O'Neill, Cate</name>
<title render="quoted">The importance of photos</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>eScholarship Research Centre, the University of Melbourne</publisher>
<date>2015</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect web resource blog</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnectwrblog.info/2015/06/the-importance-of-photos/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>