<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>E001049</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCVC</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Archival Collection</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2017-03-22">2017-03-22</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Nicola Laurent</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2017-10-31">2017-10-31</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E001049b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>concept</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Records from Tally Ho</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1903-01-01">1903</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1989-12-31">1989</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Records from Tally Ho is a collection of records dating from 1903 to 1989 about Tally Ho Boys' Training Farm and Tally Ho Youth Services. Uniting (Victoria and Tasmania) Limited holds minimal records from Tally Ho prior to the 1980s and has, for some time, been actively searching for personal records and other documents to assist past residents seeking information about their time at Tally Ho. Uniting deeply regrets it does not hold complete records from Tally Ho.</abstract>
<h4>Access Conditions</h4>
<p>Former residents (and their families) should contact the Uniting Heritage Service to find information, and access personal files. The Uniting Heritage Service is a free service that helps individuals access information about them or family members, as well as access appropriate support should they choose. Heritage Service staff prefer to release records to past residents or their family members in person, where possible, in order to give greater meaning and context to the information.</p>
<h4>Records</h4>
<p>In 2017, Wesley Mission Victoria (now part of Uniting (Victoria and Tasmania) Limited) was the recipient of a Records Access Documentation Grant to investigate the contents of 3,480 boxes in its archives. From March to June 2017, researchers carefully reviewed the contents of these boxes, which mainly contained administrative files. The research and documentation of these administrative records has led to the discovery of new information about past residents. No client files or personal records of Tally Ho residents were found. However, over 7,000 brief entries or mentions of past residents were identified in administrative records from the 1920s to the 1980s.</p>
<p>Since April 2003, Uniting Wesley has maintained a register of people who have made requests for Tally Ho records. Heritage Service staff will make every effort to get back in touch with people on the register to let them know that new information is available.</p>
<p>The records Uniting holds about Tally Ho and its residents contain different information depending on the time period. Here is a brief description of the types of records in the collection:</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho Farm, c.1920-1939 &amp; 1991</span><br />
The documents that relate to children who were at Tally Ho in the 1920s and 1930s are generally in the form of administrative lists or registers, and do not contain much detail. The documents usually contain the child's full name but only occasionally include family background, admission and departure dates and reason for admission. Sometimes information about where a child was discharged to is available.</p>
<p>Other documents include reports, newspaper articles, and letters between management and the Children's Welfare Department. In 1991, a care leaver described his experience at the farm in the 1930s, and names some of the children he lived with.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho Farm, 1940-1959</span><br />
There are less records available that relate to children who were at Tally Ho in the 1940s and 1950s, but there is a reasonable amount of correspondence between staff, management, and government departments. These records often include an admission date, sometimes mention birthdates, and regularly provide parents and siblings names. Many children named in this series were wards of the state, and some were from families who had been affected by war.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho Special School, 1964-1971</span><br />
These records relate to the Tally Ho Special School in Glen Waverley. The documents that name children include: admission register; attendees lists, receipt books and sport and library requisites. They contain information such as: birthdates; dates of admission and departure; activities; where the child had attended previously; and where they were discharged to.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho, c.1965-1979</span><br />
The documents that relate to children who were at Tally Ho from 1965 to 1979 include: letters; memorandums; newspaper articles; and meeting minutes written by staff and management. They contain information such as: admission dates; daily activities; family background; where the children had come from; and where they may go after leaving.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho Farm - Client and incident specific, 1980-1986</span><br />
These records contain documents created and kept for individual children and incidents at the farm between 1980 and 1986. They include two client files, diaries, incident reports, reports and notes staff had written about residents.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho Farm - Administrative lists and registers, 1980s</span><br />
These documents contain brief, statistical information about children who lived at Tally Ho in the 1980s and were kept by staff for administrative purposes. These records are generally lists and record the children's activities, income and expenditure. They sometimes include children's birthdates, admission dates, discharge dates and where they stayed, and details about the family's background.</p>
<p>Because Tally Ho transitioned from the farm to residential units half way through 1986, most records in this series are of children at the farm, but there may be mentions of children in residential houses.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho Farm - Minutes and reports, 1980s</span><br />
This series contains documents which were generally about the farm, but made mention of children occasionally. They include meeting minutes of staff and the placement panel, reports to management, casework summaries, and plans for the transition from Tally Ho Farm to Tally Ho Youth Services. The records often include admission dates and where the child lived but other details are scare.</p>
<p>Some reports discuss suitability for the program, and therefore some children named may not have actually been admitted to Tally Ho. Because Tally Ho transitioned from the farm to residential units half way through 1986, most records in this series are of children at the farm, but there may be mentions of children in residential houses.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho Farm - Dailies Books, 1986-1987</span><br />
The dailies books are books that residential carers maintained where they would write what had happened during the day including behaviours, incidents, property information, and notes to other staff members. The location of the residential unit was often obtainable, as were the dates that children were present. In some instances parents and siblings of the children are named.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho Youth Services - Documents specific to children and incidents, 1987-1989</span><br />
These records were kept about individual children in the residential unit and include agreements between residents and Tally Ho and client files. They contain information such as: admission and departure dates; placement location, birthdate and sometimes background and the names of family members.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho Youth Services - Dailies, Minutes and Reports, 1987-1989</span><br />
The records include details of incidents, daily activities and operations at residential units and often mention where children are residing. The documents includes: incident reports; meeting minutes; daily reports; dailies books and files notes written by staff.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho Youth Services - Administrative Records, 1987-1989</span><br />
The records include lists of admissions, income and expenditure and resident statistics. They sometimes include important dates and where the child stayed.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Tally Ho Youth Services - Community Friends Program, 1987-1989</span><br />
The records include documents about the Community Friends Program - where participants were paired with an adult volunteer for the purpose of gaining friendship and guidance. The documents include: meeting minutes; reports; statistics; monthly assessments and one client file. Information includes the length of a child's participation in the program and who they were paired with.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">Other Records</span><br />
The Heritage Service has established a protocol and working relationship with the Victorian Government Department of Education and Training in relation to the records from the school at Tally Ho, so there is a streamlined process for people requesting Tally Ho records.</p>
<p>Heritage Service staff are in ongoing discussion with the Victorian Department of Health and Human Services about any Tally Ho records they may hold.</p>
<h4>Fires at Tally Ho</h4>
<p>It had been thought that a fire or fires may have been the reason why the records are incomplete. In 2014, Uniting Wesley conducted an investigation to explore the evidence for this belief. The researcher examined the records from Tally Ho held by Uniting Wesley, in which various documents made reference to fires in 1958, 1964 and 1965.</p>
<p>The 1958 fire occurred in the drying room of one of eight cottages. The report's findings stated "There is insufficient evidence to draw a conclusion on whether records were lost…however any loss is presumed to be limited to records relating to the clients residing in the particular cottage at the time."</p>
<p>In relation to the 1964 and 1965 fires, the report found that "records were unlikely to have been lost" due to the locations of the fires and that records were not listed amongst items destroyed.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E001036b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Uniting (Victoria and Tasmania) Limited (2016 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000121b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Tally Ho Youth Services (1986 - 1989)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E001048b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Uniting Heritage Service (2016 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000698b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Wesley Mission Victoria Records (1902 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Records from Tally Ho were previously described within the Wesley Mission Victoria Records entry.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E001035b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Contact Details">
Uniting Heritage Service - Contact Details
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E000119b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Tally Ho Boys' Training Farm (1903 - 1986)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Records from Tally Ho', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Records from Tally Ho</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Victoria</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/biogs/E001049b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/bib/P00001224.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Records from Tally Ho (1903 - 1986)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Records from Tally Ho (1903 - 1986)</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Wesley Mission Victoria</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="https://www.wesley.org.au/care-leavers/records-from-tally-ho-1903-1986/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/vic/objects/D00000447.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Report on fire at Tally Ho Boys' Village</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Report on fire at Tally Ho Boys' Village</unittitle>
<unitdate>1964</unitdate>
<abstract>Albert Godbehere, superintendent of the Tally Ho Boys' Village, wrote the report on the fire, which occurred on Tuesday 21 January 1964.</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>