<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>SE00126</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCSA</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - South Australia</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Organisation</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2011-02-14">2011-02-14</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Gary George and Karen George</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2017-08-31">2017-08-31</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00126b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Barton Vale Girls' Home</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="Also known as"><part>Barton Vale School</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="Also known as"><part>Barton Vale Girls Reformatory</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1922-01-01">1922</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1947-12-31">1947</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Reformatory</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Salvation Army</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Home</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Barton Vale Girls' Home was established at Harewood Avenue, Enfield by the Salvation Army in 1922. It took over the role of the government-run Redruth Girls' Reformatory which closed in the same year. As a reformatory it accommodated girls who were convicted for offences or for other reasons were deemed to be in need of strong discipline. In 1947 the Government took control of Barton Vale and renamed it Vaughan House.</abstract>
<p>In 1922 the South Australian State Government, upon the recommendation of the State Children's Council, decided to close the reformatory for girls at Redruth in Burra. The Government requested that The Salvation Army open a similar institution to replace Redruth and assisted the Army in its purchase of a 21 acre (8.5 hectares) estate on Harewood Avenue, Enfield, known as Barton Vale. According to a July 1922 newspaper article similar arrangements between the Victorian State Government and The Salvation Army had led to the creation of three Salvation Army homes for girls in that State. These included Riddells Creek Girls' Home, the William Booth Girls' Home at East Camberwell and the Catherine Booth Girls' Home at East Kew. Adjutant Ryder, who had worked for some years at both Riddells Creek and East Kew Girls' Homes, was to become the first matron of Barton Vale.</p>
<p>The Barton Vale property included an early Victorian, Gothic-style mansion with a high tower, originally built by pastoralist Edmund Bowman. The extensive grounds were said in newspaper reports to include; "a fine orange orchard, lawns and flower garden." At the death of the last member of the Bowman family the contents of the home were auctioned and the building was purchased by the Salvation Army for £2600. Alterations were made to the building to provide accommodation for up to 45 girls. In August of 1922 Barton Vale was declared 'a reformatory school' under the State Children's Act. The last 10 girls still resident at Burra were transferred to the Enfield premises and the Redruth Reformatory was closed.</p>
<p>As a reformatory Barton Vale accommodated girls who were convicted for offences or for other reasons were deemed to be in need of strong discipline.</p>
<p>Mr JG Bice, the Chief Secretary, stated that the Government would contribute to the maintenance of the Home. He was quoted in a newspaper of the time as saying:</p>
<p>'It will be a real home for the girls…and not a prison. This is the step I have had in view since the first time I saw the reformatory at Redruth.'</p>
<p>Responding to a large deputation seeking prison reform Mr Bice said that he had been ashamed of the Redruth Reformatory. He stated that 'the Gladstone Gaol was a palace compared with the Redruth Reformatory' and he was glad to have been able to act on the State Children's Council recommendation and move the girls to Barton Vale.</p>
<p>In December 1923 it was reported that the girls at Barton Vale had much more freedom than had been possible at Burra and that so far the new situation was encouraging.</p>
<p>From as early as 1925, however, reports of disturbances at the Home and girls absconding began to appear in the newspapers. The instances of girls escaping increased over the next few years. A brief article in 1929 mentioned the escape of four girls, the recapture of two, and that four or five girls were 'missing at present'.</p>
<p>By 1930, increasing 'troubles' and abscondings from Barton Vale were causing concern. In February of that year a Judge questioned whether it was right for him to be committing girls to the Home, but said he had no other choice. The Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board held a meeting to discuss conditions at the Home.</p>
<p>In July 1930 a riot at the Home led to 10 girls being removed by the police to spend time at the Children's Welfare Department. One girl was arrested. Two girls escaped during the riot. After this dramatic event an unnamed 'Social Welfare Authority' was quoted in the newspaper in an article titled 'What's Wrong with Barton Vale?' saying that the system there was out of date.</p>
<p>' To send 40 girls to bed at 8 o'clock every night is asking for mischief. Some of them are 20 years old! The girls need organised games and recreation. … Their records are all hymns. The girls would like a little jazz occasionally and it would do them no harm: Why not an occasional picture show?'</p>
<p>The person quoted then went on to say that the girls needed occupation - 'Let them do the washing for the Hospital, or something equally useful. After a few hours at the washtub they won't feel so much like screaming.' It was questioned at this time whether the Government should once again take over the running of the institution.</p>
<p>The mixing of girls of different religious denominations was also seen as a problem. In 1930 it was decided that girls of the Roman Catholic faith should be separated from the Protestant girls. After a new Roman Catholic Girls' Home at Parkside was established, with help from the government, 10 girls from Barton Vale were moved there and placed under the care of the Sisters of St Joseph. Later, Catholic girls were sent to The Convent of the Good Shepherd, 'The Pines'.</p>
<p>The abscondings, however, did not end there. Later in the same year three girls attempted escape by jumping from the high balcony of the tower. One was badly injured and could not escape. Two were later recaptured with injuries to their feet and ankles.</p>
<p>Girls continued to be committed to Barton Vale throughout the 1930s and into the 1940s. While in 1940 it was reported that only 11 girls were at Barton Vale, by September 1943, 35 girls were resident there. In March 1947 a newspaper reported that only 7 'delinquent girls' remained at Barton Vale.</p>
<p>The Salvation Army ran the Barton Vale home until 1947 when the Government resumed responsibility for the reformatory. Despite opposition to the change from the local council Barton Vale was renamed Vaughan House.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1922-01-01">1922</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1947-12-31">1947</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Enfield</placeEntry>
<event>Location - Barton Vale Girls Home was situated at Harewood Avenue, Enfield</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-earlier" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00079b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Redruth Girls' Reformatory (1897 - 1922)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1922-01-01">1922</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1922-12-31">1922</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00127b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
The Salvation Army (1829 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Barton Vale Girls' Home was run by the Salvation Army, under the control of the State Children's Council and its successor the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00437b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Register of New Committals (1931 - 1968)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. This thick register contains general admission information relating to Homes under the control of the government and includes admissions for Barton Vale Girls Home.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00453b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Correspondence files ('CW &amp; PRD' and 'SW' files) -Children's Welfare and Public Relief Department and successors (1927 - c. 1979)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These correspondence files are comprised of letters and other documents filed chronologically. They include some correspondence related to homes run by the Salvation Army under the control of the Department.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00438b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Minutes - State Children's Council, later the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board (1886 - 1965)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These two large volumes of minutes include some entries related to Barton Vale Girls Home. Information about state wards admitted to the home is often given including names and some details.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00515b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Mandates committing children to the custody of the Department, Social Welfare Department and Predecessors (1880 - 1930)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These mandates are legal documents committing 'neglected', 'destitute' or 'delinquent' children to a reformatory. They may include committals to Barton Vale.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00512b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
State Ward Index Cards, State Children's Department and successors (1900 - 1992)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. State Ward Index Cards were small cards created when a child came under the control of the Department. They contain various amounts of information. Some may relate to children who were resident at Barton Vale.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00605b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Social files, Barton Vale Girls' Home (1922? - 1947?)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Salvation Army Australia Southern Territory Territorial Archives and Museum. These Social files are made up of a folder of general histroical information relating to Barton Vale.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00442b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Annual Reports of the State Children's Council and the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Department (1887 - 1960)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These yearly reports provide updates on developments at homes under the control of the Department, including Barton Vale.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00606b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Barton Vale, South Australia [Photographs], Barton Vale Girls' Home (1922? - 1947?)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Salvation Army Australia Southern Territory Territorial Archives and Museum. This series includes a limited number of photographs of buildings, girls and staff at Barton Vale Girls Home.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01080b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Reformatory (1866 - 1967)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00021b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Catholic Girls' Home Parkside (1930 - 1943)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Girls of the Catholic faith at Barton Vale Girls' Home were moved to the Catholic Girls' Home, Parkside, when it opened in 1930.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00757b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Records of Barton Vale Girls' Home (1922? - 1947?)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00607b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Index to the War Cry [Periodical], Salvation Army Magazine (1883 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Salvation Army Territorial Archives and Museum. This electronic index can be searched for information and articles relating to this Home appearing in the Salvation Army Magazine 'War Cry'.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00787b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Absconding
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01362b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Stolen Generations
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00726b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Records of the Social Welfare Department and predecessors (1849 - c. 1987)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00540b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Photographs of Departmental institutions, Social Welfare Department and Predecessors (1945 - 1970)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. This file of photographs of institutions under the control of the Department of Social Welfare and its predecessors, inculde photos of Barton Vale after it became known as Vaughan House.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00028b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
State Children's Council (1886 - 1927)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1922-01-01">1922</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1927-12-31">1927</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Barton Vale Girls' Home was run by the Salvation Army, under the control of the State Children's Council and its successor the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00023b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board (1927 - 1966)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1927-01-01">1927</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1947-12-31">1947</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Barton Vale Girls' Home was run by the Salvation Army, under the control of the State Children's Council and its successor the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-later" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00084b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Vaughan House (1947 - 1979)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Barton Vale Girls' Home', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - South Australia</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Barton Vale Girls' Home</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - South Australia</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00126b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000231.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: THE REFORMATORIES</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">THE REFORMATORIES</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1923</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Advertiser</title>
<num type="pages">12</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article36610108"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000022.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Social Salvation, Early development of the Social Wing of The Salvation Army</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Steer, Hedley</name>
<title render="italic">Social Salvation, Early development of the Social Wing of The Salvation Army</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide</place>
<publisher>The Salvation Army</publisher>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000042.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Finding your own way</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">George, Karen</name>
<title render="italic">Finding your own way</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Nunkuwarrin Yunti of South Australia Inc.</publisher>
<date>2005</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nunku.org.au/resources/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000207.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Journal: War Cry: The Salvation Army Magazine</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">War Cry: The Salvation Army Magazine</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>The Salvation Army Australia</publisher>
<date>1883 -</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000225.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Agency Details: GA2377 Vaughan House</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">State Records of South Australia</name>
<title render="quoted">Agency Details: GA2377 Vaughan House</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">State Records of South Australia, ArchivesSearch</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://archives.sa.gov.au"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000226.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: NEW HOME FOR REFORMATORY GIRLS</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">NEW HOME FOR REFORMATORY GIRLS</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1922</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Advertiser</title>
<num type="pages">6</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article49105180"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000227.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: CLOSING THE REDRUTH REFORMATORY</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">CLOSING THE REDRUTH REFORMATORY</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1922</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Register</title>
<num type="pages">6</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article63926526"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000228.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: THE GIRLS' REFORMATORY</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">THE GIRLS' REFORMATORY</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1922</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Advertiser</title>
<num type="pages">12</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article49109438"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000021.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Southern Soup-Soap-Salvation, a compendium of Salvation Army Social Services in the Australian Southern Territory</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Kirkham, Lt-Col John C</name>
<title render="italic">Southern Soup-Soap-Salvation, a compendium of Salvation Army Social Services in the Australian Southern Territory</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>The Salvation Army Australia Southern Territory Territorial Archives and Museum</publisher>
<date>2003</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000230.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: PRISON REFORM</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">PRISON REFORM</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1922</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Advertiser</title>
<num type="pages">12</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article49133413"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000240.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: TREATMENT OF PRISONERS</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">TREATMENT OF PRISONERS</title>
<imprint>
<place>Port Pirie, SA</place>
<date>1922</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Recorder</title>
<num type="pages">1</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article102730677"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000232.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Girls Escape From Barton Vale</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Girls Escape From Barton Vale</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1929</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Register News-Pictorial</title>
<num type="pages">3</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article53474723"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000233.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: BARTON VALE ESCAPES DISTURB S.M.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">BARTON VALE ESCAPES DISTURB S.M.</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1930</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Register News-Pictorial</title>
<num type="pages">4</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article54163604"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000234.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: REFORMATORY GIRL SENT TO ASYLUM</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">REFORMATORY GIRL SENT TO ASYLUM</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1930</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Register News-Pictorial</title>
<num type="pages">3</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article54157283"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000235.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: BARTON VALE RIOT</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">BARTON VALE RIOT</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1930</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Advertiser</title>
<num type="pages">15</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article30495178"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000236.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: BRIEF LIBERTY</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">BRIEF LIBERTY</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1930</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Advertiser</title>
<num type="pages">7</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article29856828"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000237.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: What's Wrong With Barton Vale? Welfare Authority's Opinions</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">What's Wrong With Barton Vale? Welfare Authority's Opinions</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1930</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Register News-Pictorial</title>
<num type="pages">4</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article53804115"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000238.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Salvation Army Street Appeal Tomorrow</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Salvation Army Street Appeal Tomorrow</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1943</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Advertiser</title>
<num type="pages">3</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article48768182"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000239.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Change Of Name Of Barton Vale Home</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Change Of Name Of Barton Vale Home</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, SA</place>
<date>1947</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Advertiser</title>
<num type="pages">4</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article43742366"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000229.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: INDUSTRIAL HOME FOR GIRLS</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">INDUSTRIAL HOME FOR GIRLS</title>
<imprint>
<place>Port Pirie, SA</place>
<date>1922</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Recorder</title>
<num type="pages">4</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article102725393"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000106.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Barton Vale Girls Home 01</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Barton Vale Girls Home 01</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1900</unitdate>
<abstract>Barton Vale - Residence of the Bowman family at Enfield</abstract>
<note label="rights">No known copyright restrictions</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000024.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Barton Vale Girls Home</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Finding Your Own Way (2005)</repository>
<unittitle>Barton Vale Girls Home</unittitle>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>