<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>SE00049</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCSA</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - South Australia</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Organisation</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2011-02-07">2011-02-07</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Karen George and Gary George</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2017-08-31">2017-08-31</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00049b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>St Vincent de Paul Orphanage</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="Also known as"><part>Goodwood Orphanage</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1866-01-01">1866</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1975-12-31">1975</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Catholic</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Orphanage</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Industrial School</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Home</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Receiving Home</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>St Vincent de Paul Orphanage was established by the Catholic Church in 1866 in Gilberton. In 1867 it took in Catholic children from the Grace Darling Hotel. The Orphanage moved to Adelaide in 1868, to Mitcham in 1872, Burnside in 1875 and Millswood in 1888. The Orphanage was run by the Orphanage Board from 1866 to 1872, The Sisters of St Joseph, 1872 to 1889 and the Sisters of Mercy, 1889 to 1975. Between 1949 and 1957, 54 migrant girls were brought to the Orphanage from England and Malta. The St Vincent de Paul Orphanage closed in 1975 and was replaced by a number of cottage homes known as the St Vincent Group Homes.</abstract>
<p>The St Vincent de Paul Orphanage was first established by the Catholic Church in 1866. In the mid 1800s some members of the Catholic Church became concerned that orphans of the faith under government care were often placed with non-Catholic families. They believed that these children's spiritual welfare needed to be protected through the establishment of a Catholic orphanage. The orphanage was funded via a statewide appeal and a large house in Gilberton, known as Oberlin House, was secured for the purpose. Situated on the corner of Walkerville and Park Terraces, directly opposite the Buckingham Arms Hotel, the house had a large dining hall, two downstairs rooms for dormitories, two upstairs bedrooms and a large kitchen. There was also a paddock adjacent to the building, approximately one acre in size.</p>
<p>The Orphanage officially opened on 16 August 1866 and was managed by a board which included Catholic priests and laymen. A lay matron took charge of the first children sent to the Orphanage. A newspaper of the time reported the rules for the management of the Institution as follows:</p>
<p>'1. Children to rise from bed at 7o'clock a.m.; 2. Breakfast at 8 o'clock, an hour being allowed for washing, dressing, and prayer; 3. School to commence with prayer at 9.30 a.m., and to close also with prayer at 3 p.m. ; Dinner at 12 o'clock, the previous half-hour being allowed for play; 5. Supper to be served at 5 o'clock p.m. - young children allowed food when necessary; 6. Bed-hour (after prayer) for children of four years and over at 9 o'clock and 8 o'clock for those under that age; 7. Girls to be instructed in needlework, cookery, and other necessary domestic employment; 8. Boys to be employed at useful work, and to be carefully educated as to fit them for trades and other employment; 9. The matron shall neither receive nor allow any children to be taken out of the Orphanage unless by a written order from the Board signed by the Secretary; 10. Domestic servants and all others residing in the Orphanage to be strictly obedient to the command of the matron. '</p>
<p>In 1867 the government approached the Catholic Church and pressured them to give shelter to Catholic children from the badly overcrowded state orphanage situated at that time in the Grace Darling Hotel at Brighton. In May of that year the St Vincent de Paul Orphanage was gazetted as an industrial school so that the government could pay a subsidy for each child admitted. In the first half of 1867 thirty-eight children moved from Brighton to Walkerville. As the government sent more children to the Walkerville home, it was soon found to be too small for the demand. A building known as Boston Cottages on King William Street South was leased and opened as a branch orphanage for the girls. Children accommodated there, although under the direct care of a lay matron, were supervised by of the Sisters of St Joseph. In June 1868 the girls moved again to a row of cottages on the corner of Franklin and Grey Streets in the City. At this time a number of the Sisters moved in to care for them. The boys were also moved to these premises in August 1868.</p>
<p>During this period government sponsorship became intermittent and in 1872 ceased completely. However, the orphanage continued to run supported entirely by the church. In 1872 the children were moved from the City to a house in Mitcham, recently vacated by St Joseph's Refuge, which provided grounds as well as a building.</p>
<p>In November of 1872 the Orphanage Board ceased operating and the running of the Orphanage fell to the Sisters of St Joseph. Three years later, when the ownership of the Mitcham property changed hands, a larger premises known as Knightsbridge House was secured in Burnside and the children moved once again. In 1883 the Board was reconstituted as the Orphanage Committee, and they began the search for a more suitable property. This was found in 1888 and the children made their final move to a 12-13 acre (5 hectares) property secured by the Adelaide Archbishop on the corner of Mitchell Street and Goodwood Road, Millswood. The residence was renovated and new buildings added. One year later, by the order of Archbishop Reynolds, the Sisters of Mercy took over the running of the orphanage from the Sisters of St Joseph.</p>
<p>During the early 1900s further additions were made so that the home could accommodate up to 120 children. Another new wing was opened in 1924.</p>
<p>In 1947 the Archbishop of Adelaide, Archbishop Beovich, requested that 50 Catholic migrant English girls be brought to Adelaide to be accommodated at the St Vincent De Paul Orphanage. Renovations and improvements were made to the Orphanage buildings in order to accept the girls. The United Kingdom and Commonwealth Governments recognized St Vincent De Paul Orphanage, Goodwood, as an 'approved organisation' for the introduction of child migrants under the free and assisted passage schemes in August 1948. On 17 December 1948 twenty-eight girls between the ages of 6 and 14 years left England on the 'Ormonda'. They arrived at Port Adelaide and moved into the Orphanage on 19 January 1949. In May a further 14 girls arrived on the 'Mooltan', and in June 1950 four more on the Otranto. Although this fulfilled only 46 of the originally 50 girls that were to make up 'Group Nomination S.G. 10' it was later agreed that the nomination had been fulfilled.</p>
<p>In September 1950 Archbishop Beovich began negotiations for 12 Maltese girls to come to St Vincent De Paul Orphanage, Goodwood. It was not until April 1954, however, that the first 3 girls arrived from Malta aboard the 'Surriento'. In October of that year 3 more girls arrived aboard the 'Fairsea'. Only two more girls were sent from Malta, 1 arriving on the 'Arosa Star' in January 1955 and the last on the 'Castel Felice' in February 1955.</p>
<p>By 1960 ninety-nine children were resident in the orphanage. This number dropped to 52 in 1970 and at its closure in 1975, only 20 children were in residence. The role of St Vincent de Paul Orphanage was replaced by a number of suburban cottage homes know as the St Vincent Group Homes.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1866-01-01">1866</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1868-12-31">1868</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Gilberton</placeEntry>
<event>Location - St Vincent De Paul Orphanage was situated at Walkerville Terrace, Gilberton</event>
</chronItem>
<chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1867-01-01">1867</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1868-12-31">1868</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Adelaide</placeEntry>
<event>Address - St Vincent De Paul Orphanage was situated at Boston Cottages, King William Street South, Adelaide</event>
</chronItem>
<chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1868-01-01">1868</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1872-12-31">1872</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Adelaide</placeEntry>
<event>Location - St Vincent De Paul Orphanage was situated at Franklin Street, Adelaide</event>
</chronItem>
<chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1872-01-01">1872</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1875-12-31">1875</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Mitcham</placeEntry>
<event>Location - St Vincent De Paul Orphanage was situated at former premises of the St Joseph's Refuge, Mitcham</event>
</chronItem>
<chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1875-01-01">1875</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1888-12-31">1888</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Burnside</placeEntry>
<event>Location - St Vincent De Paul Orphanage was situated at Knightsbridge House, Burnside</event>
</chronItem>
<chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1888-01-01">1888</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1975-12-31">1975</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Millswood</placeEntry>
<event>Address - St Vincent De Paul Orphanage was situated at 181 Goodwood Road, on the corner of Mitchell Street, Millswood</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00022b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Sisters of St Joseph (1866 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1868-01-01">1868</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1889-12-31">1889</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00050b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Sisters of Mercy, Adelaide Congregation (1880 - 2011)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1890-01-01">1890</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1975-12-31">1975</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00068b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Brighton Industrial School (1867 - 1869)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Due to overcrowding at the Brighton Industrial School, a number of children were sent to the Catholic St Vincent de Paul's Orphanage and the Church of England's Orphan Home, also known as Farr House.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00498b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Children forwarded to the Roman Catholic Orphanage 1867-1869 (index) [Admission Register] (1867 - 1869)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of South Australia. This three page list names children sent from the Destitute Asylum to St Vincent de Paul Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00494b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
St Vincent de Paul Orphanage, Burnside [Admission Register] (1872 - 1889)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Professional Standards Office Records Service of the Catholic Church. This quarto sized hardcover notebook contains general admission information for children entering the Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00493b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Discharge Book, St Vincent de Paul Orphanage (1866 - 1920)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Professional Standards Office Records Service of the Catholic Church. This small hardback lined notebook contains information regarding the discharge of children from the Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00492b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
St Vincent de Paul Admission Register, Book 3 (labelled 3B) (1875 - 1975)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Professional Standards Office Records Service of the Catholic Church. This large ledger contains general admission information for children entering the Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00491b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
St Vincent de Paul Admission Register, Book 2 (1920 - 1949)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Professional Standards Office Records Service of the Catholic Church. This large handwritten and typed ledger contains general admission information for children entering the Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00490b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
St Vincent de Paul Admission Register, Book 1 (1875 - 1929)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Professional Standards Office Records Service of the Catholic Church. This large handwritten ledger contains general admission information for children entering the Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00496b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Admission forms, St Vincent de Paul Orphanage (1893 - 1895)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Professional Standards Office Records Service of the Catholic Church. This manilla folder contains some original admission forms and several handwritten agreements.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00502b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Records of St Vincent de Paul Orphanage (1866? - 1975?)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00497b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Admission list, St Vincent de Paul Orphanage (26 May 1941)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Professional Standards Office Records Service of the Catholic Church. This manilla folder contains a letter with an attached list of children in the Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00062b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Destitute Asylum (1851 - c. 1917)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Following the Destitute Persons Relief Act 1867, some children were moved from the Destitute Asylum to St Vincent de Paul Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01216b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
St Joseph's Junior Boys' Home (1960s - 1969)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>While St Joseph's Junior Boys Home at Largs Bay took in boys between the ages of 3 and 12 all girls were sent to St Vincent de Paul Orphanage, Goodwood.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00036b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
St John the Baptist Home for Boys (1898 - 1941)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>In 1941 St John the Baptist Home for Boys took boys aged 12 years of age or older, while younger boys were sent to the St Joseph's Orphanage at Largs Bay or to the St Vincent de Paul Orphanage at Goodwood.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01189b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Former Residents' Folders (1900s - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Former residents' folders, held by the Professional Standards Office, may contain information relating to St Vincent de Paul Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00505b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Photographs, St Vincent De Paul Orphanage (1866? - 1975?)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Adelaide Catholic Archdiocesan Archives. These photographs include a number of the Orphanage building.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00740b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
JD Somerville Oral History Collection (1904 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01362b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Stolen Generations
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01397b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Inquiry into Children in Institutional Care (2003 - 2004)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00042b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
St Joseph's Refuge (1868 - c. 2001)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>St Vincent De Paul Orphanage was situated at former premises of the St Joseph's Refuge, Mitcham</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00743b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Records created by the Destitute Board (c. 1845 - 1927)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00741b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Records of St Vincent De Paul Orphanage (1866? - 1975?)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00738b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Records of St Vincent de Paul Orphanage (1866 - 1975)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01376b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Records held by the Sisters of St Joseph Archives (1866? - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00495b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
St Vincent de Paul Orphanage, Burnside [Admission Register] (1872 - 1883)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Professional Standards Office Records Service of the Catholic Church. This foolscap sized hardcover folder contains general admission information for children entering the Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00211b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Waverley Hostel (1972 - 1988)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Some girls from the St Vincent de Paul Orphanage were accommodated at Waverley Hostel after they left school and were seeking employment.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01149b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Children in State Care Commission of Inquiry, State of South Australia (2004 - 2008)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00363b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Child and Youth Migration to South Australia (1850s - c. 1981)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01162b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Child Migration - St Vincents de Paul Orphanage - Goodward, SA - Catholic (1947 - 1960)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the National Archives of Australia and available online. This file contains correspondence between St Vincent de Paul Orphanage, the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board and the Commonwealth Department of Immigration regarding Child Migration.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01159b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Child Migration - Methodist Children's Home - Magill SA (1948 - 1955)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the National Archives of Australia and available online. This file contains correspondence between the Methodist Children's Home, the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board and the Commonwealth Department of Immigration regarding Child Migration.It also contains references to St Vincent de Paul Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00503b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Goodwood Orphanage Oral History (1993 - 1994)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the State Library of South Australia as part of the JD Somerville Collection. This oral history is made up of seventeen interviews commissioned by the Libraries Board of SA concerning the experiences of children, nuns and priests living and working at St Vincent de Paul Orphanage, also known as Goodwood Orphanage. Please note this Oral History also includes an associated series of 72 photographs.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00500b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Miscellaneous records, St Vincent de Paul Orphanage (1890s - 1970s)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by The Adelaide Catholic Archdiocesan Archives. These miscellaneous records include correspondence, news clippings, early reports and other documents containing general and historical information related to the Orphanage.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00499b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Minutes, St Vincent de Paul Orphanage (1887 - 1890)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by the Professional Standards Office Records Service of the Catholic Church. This small hardback notebook contains minutes of meetings and includes some names of children and information about admissions.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00040b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
St Joseph's Orphanage Largs Bay (1907? - 1960s)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1941-01-01">1941</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1969-12-31">1969</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>From 1941 all girls at St Joseph's Orphanage, Largs Bay, were sent to St Vincent de Paul Orphanage at Goodwood.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-later" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00201b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Orana Cottage Home, St Vincent de Paul Group Homes (1975 - 1980)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-later" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00197b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Bon Agor House, St Vincent de Paul Group Homes (1975 - 1989s)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-later" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00212b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Yoorana Cottage, St Vincent de Paul Group Homes (1975 - 1989)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'St Vincent de Paul Orphanage', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - South Australia</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">St Vincent de Paul Orphanage</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - South Australia</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00049b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000462.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Responding to the film 'Once my mother'</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">O'Neill, Cate</name>
<title render="quoted">Responding to the film 'Once my mother'</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>eScholarship Research Centre, the University of Melbourne</publisher>
<date>2015</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect web resource blog</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnectwrblog.info/2015/07/responding-to-the-film-once-my-mother/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000365.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Report on the St Vincent de Paul Cottage Homes</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Booth, Robyn</name>
<title render="italic">Report on the St Vincent de Paul Cottage Homes</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Unpublished typescript</publisher>
<date>1979</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000142.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: The Orphanage of St Vincent De Paul</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">The Orphanage of St Vincent De Paul</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, South Australia</place>
<date>1866</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The South Australian Register</title>
<num type="pages">2</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article41025377"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000042.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Finding your own way</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">George, Karen</name>
<title render="italic">Finding your own way</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Nunkuwarrin Yunti of South Australia Inc.</publisher>
<date>2005</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nunku.org.au/resources/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000008.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Journal Article: Orphaned in South Australia: Oral histories about growing up at Goodwood Orphanage</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Robertson, Beth M.</name>
<title render="quoted">Orphaned in South Australia: Oral histories about growing up at Goodwood Orphanage</title>
<imprint>
<date>1995</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Oral History Association of Australia Journal</title>
<num type="issue">17</num>
<num type="pages">86-97</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000007.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Women on the Move: Mercy's triple spiral: a history of the Adelaide Sisters of Mercy, Ireland to Argentina 1856-1880 to South Australia 1880</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">McLay, Anne</name>
<title render="italic">Women on the Move: Mercy's triple spiral: a history of the Adelaide Sisters of Mercy, Ireland to Argentina 1856-1880 to South Australia 1880</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide</place>
<publisher>Sisters of Mercy</publisher>
<date>1996</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000005.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Think of the Ravens: The Sisters of St Joseph in Social Welfare</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Foale, Marie Therese</name>
<title render="italic">Think of the Ravens: The Sisters of St Joseph in Social Welfare</title>
<imprint>
<place>Kent Town</place>
<publisher>Sisters of St Joseph of the Sacred Heart Inc</publisher>
<date>2001</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000192.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">St Vincent de Paul Orphanage, Goodwood 03</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>St Vincent de Paul Orphanage, Goodwood 03</unittitle>
<unitdate>1922</unitdate>
<abstract>Children in the grounds of the Orphanage at Goodwood, South Australia</abstract>
<note label="rights">No known copyright restrictions</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000098.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">St Vincent de Paul Orphanage, Goodwood 02</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>St Vincent de Paul Orphanage, Goodwood 02</unittitle>
<unitdate>1972</unitdate>
<abstract>Goodwood Orphanage 1972. Part of the Millswood Collection.</abstract>
<note label="rights">No known copyright restrictions</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000097.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">St Vincent de Paul Orphanage, Goodwood 01</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>St Vincent de Paul Orphanage, Goodwood 01</unittitle>
<unitdate>1972</unitdate>
<abstract>Goodwood Orphanage 1972. Part of the Millswood Collection.</abstract>
<note label="rights">No known copyright restrictions</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000096.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">St Vincent de Paul Orphanage Goodwood, Old Building</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>St Vincent de Paul Orphanage Goodwood, Old Building</unittitle>
<unitdate>1888</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Used with permission of the Trustees of the Sisters of St. Joseph. Not to be reproduced without permission of the Trustees.</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000013.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Children waiting for a ride on a merry-go-round.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Children waiting for a ride on a merry-go-round.</unittitle>
<unitdate>1923</unitdate>
<abstract>Children with adults waiting for a ride on a merry-go-round during a fete held at Goodwood Orphanage.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the State Library of South Australia</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000012.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">A group of men and boys at the Orphanage, Goodwood</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>A group of men and boys at the Orphanage, Goodwood</unittitle>
<unitdate>1920</unitdate>
<abstract>A large group of men and orphaned boys at the St. Vincent de Paul's Orphanage, Goodwood Road, Goodwood, South Australia</abstract>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the State Library of South Australia</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000011.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Spectators listening to an address at Goodwood Orphanage.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Spectators listening to an address at Goodwood Orphanage.</unittitle>
<unitdate>1923</unitdate>
<abstract>A crowd of spectators listening to an address delivered by a clergyman from the entrance to St. Vincent de Paul's Orphanage at Goodwood, South Australia, possibly during a fete held in the grounds of that Institution.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the State Library of South Australia</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000010.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Children outside the Goodwood Orphanage</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Children outside the Goodwood Orphanage</unittitle>
<unitdate>1920</unitdate>
<abstract>Children of the St.Vincent de Paul's Orphanage (Sisters of Mercy) and their priest photographed at the entrance to the orphanage building on Goodwood Road, Goodwood, South Australia.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the State Library of South Australia.</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>