<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>SE00064</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCSA</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - South Australia</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Organisation</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2011-02-09">2011-02-09</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Karen George and Gary George</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2017-03-01">2017-03-01</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00064b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Edwardstown Industrial School</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1898-01-01">1898</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1949-12-31">1949</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Government-run</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Industrial School</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Home</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Edwardstown Industrial School opened in 1898 on the site of the former Girls' Reformatory at Edwardstown. It replaced the Magill Industrial School as a government receiving home for State children. From 1928 it took only boys over six years. Girls and younger boys went to Seaforth Convalescent Home. From the 1930s Edwardstown was also a remand Home for children awaiting court appearances. In 1950 it was renamed Glandore Industrial School.</abstract>
<p>The Edwardstown Industrial School opened in 1898 on the site of the former Girls Reformatory. That year all of the girls were moved out of the reformatory and transferred to Catholic and Protestant Homes in country areas. After the transfer was completed, the Magill Industrial School closed and all the children in residence were relocated to the Edwardstown Industrial School.</p>
<p>Like the Magill Industrial School, the Edwardstown Industrial School was a receiving home for children placed into State care. The children at Edwardstown came from varying circumstances. Many had suffered the loss or desertion of one or both parents. Others had been removed from parents because they were defined as 'neglected'. Some children with physical and/or intellectual disabilities were also placed at the School. Children remained at the institution for varying lengths of time. Many remained only briefly prior being boarded out or sent to other institutions.</p>
<p>Although the Industrial School was not a school or training institution, it did have a school section which was run by the Education Department, with children being taught from the regular curriculum.</p>
<p>During 1910-1911, the State Children's Council became aware of a number of deaths of very young children placed at the Industrial School. As part of their investigation of the causes, the Council asked for input from the Matron. In January 1911 she reported to the Council that the institution was overcrowded and that one of the main reasons for the increase in deaths was the placing of very young, often frail and unwell children in the School. She suggested that the increase in the number of these children meant that:</p>
<p>'The Industrial School has so far been the Infants Hospital and we cannot possibly hope to save all the children at the same time.'</p>
<p>The Trained Nurse who worked alongside the Matron in the position of Sub-matron also responded describing the circumstances of a number of the children who had died. She emphasized that she and the Matron worked day and night caring for children who were ill and they took all possible precautions to prevent infections from spreading.</p>
<p>The Council asked the Matron for suggestions for reducing the number of deaths. As a result of the investigation, new rules came into force. Any child who showed signs of serious illness was sent directly to hospital. As a preventative measure, feeding regulations were displayed more prominently at the Industrial School, children were weighed regularly and the results recorded on a weighing card.</p>
<p>Life in the Industrial School during the early part of the twentieth century was harsh. Discipline was strict, food unvaried, activities limited and work hours long and hard. Staff numbers were small for the number of children in the institution. During the late 1920s the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board (which replaced the State Children's Council) became concerned about the mingling of girls and boys at the institution. As a solution, the Board resolved that girls of all ages and boys under the age of six would be moved to Seaforth Home. From 1928, the Industrial school became a home for boys aged six to 18.</p>
<p>From the 1930s the Edwardstown Industrial School was also used as a Remand Home for children awaiting appearance before the courts for committing offences. Children continued to be moved on from the Industrial School to other institutions, were placed out into foster care or service or were adopted.</p>
<p>In 1938 the Advertiser newspaper reported on the alleged flogging of a nine year old boy at the Industrial School. This incident moved forward the government's plans for an inquiry into the treatment of children described at the time as 'delinquent'. The 1939 Inquiry into 'Delinquent and other children in the care of the state', found that boys who had committed offences were also being placed at the Industrial School even though it was only meant to accommodate boys deemed to be destitute or neglected. The Inquiry also found that the School provided insufficient overall supervision of boys and no supervision of older boys at night. The only trained staff members on site in that era were the Matron and an Education Department teacher.</p>
<p>The report described the School as having a 'general depressing atmosphere', increased by the 'unnecessarily high galvanised iron fence' and the presence of 'two cells, with locks and bars' standing prominently in what passed for a garden.</p>
<p>By the early 1940s over 140 boys resided at Edwardstown. The Industrial School remained overcrowded and understaffed. In 1944 and 1945 members of the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board visited the Industrial School and reported that it had 'an appearance of general neglect' and that there was a real need for creating 'more home-like conditions'. The Board suggested that these conditions and the shortage of staff had contributed to an increased number boys absconding from the institution.</p>
<p>In 1947, the Board expressed concern at sexual misconduct between boys at the school. A year later, a male attendant at the school was charged with indecent assault of two teenage boys. During the later 1940s a number of boys were transferred to the Boys Reformatory at Magill for sexual misconduct.</p>
<p>In 1948, the Board again reported its concern about 'the obvious lack of supervision over the boys' and suggested that</p>
<p>'consideration should be given to introducing proper night lighting, supervision through doors, and better records from staff on evening and night duty'</p>
<p>Records show that the Industrial School remained overcrowded to the end of the decade although numbers of staff were increased.</p>
<p>During the 2004-2008 Children in State Care Commission of Inquiry, a number of Forgotten Australians came forward to report abuse that had occurred at the Industrial School during the 1940s.</p>
<p>In 1950 the Edwardstown Industrial School changed its name to the Glandore Industrial School.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1898-01-01">1898</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1949-12-31">1949</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Edwardstown</placeEntry>
<event>Location - Edwardstown Industrial School was situated at Naldera Street, Edwardstown</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-earlier" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00077b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Magill Industrial School (1869 - 1898)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00028b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
State Children's Council (1886 - 1927)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1898-01-01">1898</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1927-12-31">1927</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00023b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board (1927 - 1966)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1927-01-01">1927</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1950-12-31">1950</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00080b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Seaforth Convalescent Home (1921 - 1946)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>From 1928 boys over the age of six went to Edwardstown Industrial School and girls and younger boys were sent to Seaforth Convalescent Home.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00552b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Register of admissions - Industrial School, Magill and Edwardstown (1886 - 1929)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These six volumes of registers deal with admissions to the Edwardstown Industrial School and its predecessor, the Magill Industrial School.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00437b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Register of New Committals (1931 - 1968)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. This Register contains brief admission information relating to Homes under the control of the Department. It includes Edwardstown Industrial School.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00444b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Correspondence files ('SCD' files) - State Children's Department (1887 - 1927)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These correspondence files cover all aspects of the business of the State Children's Department and include information relating to Homes under the Department's control.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00453b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Correspondence files ('CW &amp; PRD' and 'SW' files) -Children's Welfare and Public Relief Department and successors (1927 - c. 1979)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These correspondence files cover all aspects of the business of the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Department. They include information relating to Homes under the Department's control.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00438b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Minutes - State Children's Council, later the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board (1886 - 1965)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These minutes of the State Children's Council, and its successor the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board, include entires on admissions and discharges, transfers, cases of particular children and comments regarding the general running of the Edwardstown Industrial School.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00539b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Minutes - Gentlemen's Committee, State Children's Council (1903 - 1911)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These brief minutes relate to all aspects of the business of the Gentlemen's committee. Many relate to the cases of individual children under the care of the Department, including those at the Edwardstown Industrial School.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00546b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Minutes - Ladies' Committee, State Children's Council (1911 - 1916)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These brief minutes relate to all aspects of the business of the Ladie's committee. Many relate to the cases of individual children under the care of the Department, including those at the Edwardstown Industrial School.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00554b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Rough register of children in the care of the Department, State Children's Department (1920 - 1921)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. This register contains brief information relating to the movement of children in Departmental institutions. It includes references to the Edwardstown Industrial School.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00555b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Returns of children in the care of the Department, Social Welfare Department and Predecessors (1927 - 1928)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. This register tracks the movement of, and decisions relating to, children under departmental care.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00556b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Daily returns of children in the Industrial Schools, Edwardstown Industrial School (1921 - 1939)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These records provide the names of all children admitted and discharged from the Edwardstown Industrial School and the total number of boys and girls for each entry date.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01225b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Girls' Probationary School (1901 - 1945)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Some girls from Edwardstown Industrial School were sent to the Girls' Probationary School</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00065b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Girls' Reformatory, Edwardstown (1891 - 1898)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Edwardstown Industrial School opened in the site of the former Girls' Reformatory, Edwardstown.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01148b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Inquiry into Delinquent and other children in the care of the State, State of South Australia (1938 - 1939)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00083b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Struan Farm School, Naracoorte (1947 - 1969)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>A group of eight boys from the Edwardstown Industrial School and the Boys' Reformatory, Magill, were the first boys to be sent to Struan Farm School, Naracoorte</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00557b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Education - Register of Prosecutions, Education Department (1928 - 1959)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. This register of prosecutions of parents for the non-attendance at school of children of school age. Remarks include notes on committing of children to the Edwardstown Industrial School.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00787b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Absconding
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE01362b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Stolen Generations
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00864b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Industrial School (c. 1866 - 1958)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00553b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Register of Admissions - Industrial School, Edwardstown (1903 - 1908)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00442b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Annual Reports of the State Children's Council and the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Department (1887 - 1960)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Held by State Records of SA. These reports contain a regular entry relating to the Edwardstown Industrial School providing numbers of children admitted and discharged, and information about the general running of the School.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00354b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Seaforth Home (1946 - 1975)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1946-01-01">1946</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1949-12-31">1949</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Since 1928 only boys were admitted to Edwardstown Industrial School, all girls were sent to the Seaforth Home.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-later" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00067b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Glandore Industrial School (1949 - 1958)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1950-01-01">1950</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1958-12-31">1958</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Glandore Industrial School continued the work of the Edwardstown Industrial School from 1950.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Edwardstown Industrial School', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - South Australia</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Edwardstown Industrial School</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - South Australia</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/biogs/SE00064b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000042.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Finding your own way</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">George, Karen</name>
<title render="italic">Finding your own way</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Nunkuwarrin Yunti of South Australia Inc.</publisher>
<date>2005</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nunku.org.au/resources/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000117.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Alleged Flogging of Boy</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Alleged Flogging of Boy</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, South Australia</place>
<date>1938</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Advertiser</title>
<num type="pages">7</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://trove.nla.gov.au/ndp/del/article/35584657"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000115.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Report of the Committee appointed by the Government to inquire into Delinquent and other children in the care of the State</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Report of the Committee appointed by the Government to inquire into Delinquent and other children in the care of the State</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, South Australia</place>
<publisher>State of South Australia</publisher>
<date>1939</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">South Australian Parliamentary Papers 1939, Issue 75</title>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/bib/SP0000114.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Children in State Care Commission of Inquiry: Allegations of sexual abuse and death from criminal conduct, presented to the South Australian Parliament by the Hon. E.P. Mullighan QC, Commisioner</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Mullighan, the Hon E.P.</name>
<title render="italic">Children in State Care Commission of Inquiry: Allegations of sexual abuse and death from criminal conduct, presented to the South Australian Parliament by the Hon. E.P. Mullighan QC, Commisioner</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide, South Australia</place>
<publisher>Children in State Care Commission of Enquiry</publisher>
<date>2008</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="https://www.decd.sa.gov.au/doc/children-state-care-commission-inquiry-report-complete"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000343.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Edwardstown Industrial School - manual arts room</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Edwardstown Industrial School - manual arts room</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1946</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a copy of an image that was published in the Annual Report of the Children's Welfare and Public Relief Board 1946.</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000409.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Glandore Community Centre - plaque</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Glandore Community Centre - plaque</unittitle>
<unitdate>2013</unitdate>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000408.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Glandore Community Centre - memorial stone</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Glandore Community Centre - memorial stone</unittitle>
<unitdate>2013</unitdate>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000220.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Glandore Industrial School 01</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Records of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Glandore Industrial School 01</unittitle>
<unitid>GRG29/136 - picture 76</unitid>
<unitdate>1950s</unitdate>
<abstract>Glandore Industrial School, previously Edwardstown Industrial School.

Original caption: 'The front of the Industrial School at Naldera Street, Glandore, a home for neglected wards of the State.'</abstract>
<physdesc>Copy of photo from Album volume 1 of the Archival Series Photographs of Departmental Institutions<geogname></geogname>
</physdesc>
<note label="rights">Department of Education and Child Development, SA Government</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/sa/objects/SD0000073.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Glandore Industrial Home/Children's Home</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>'Homes and Orphanages', Care Leavers of Australia Network website</repository>
<unittitle>Glandore Industrial Home/Children's Home</unittitle>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>