<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>WE00890</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCWA</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Archival Item</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-01-31">2013-01-31</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Debra Rosser</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2017-08-31">2017-08-31</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00890b.htm</entityId>
<entityId localType="State Records Office of Western Australia Reference code">AU WA S1099- cons6645 INCE0084</entityId>
<entityType>concept</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>"Care for Children - Committees (Boarding Out Committee (Perth and District)) - Agendas, Minutes and Working Papers - JULY 1908 to MAY 1935"</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1908-08-25">25 August 1908</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1936-05-19">19 May 1936</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<biogHist>
<abstract>"Care for Children - Committees (Boarding Out Committee (Perth and District)) - Agendas, Minutes and Working Papers - JULY 1908 to MAY 1935" contains a file called Minutes of the Perth and District Boarding Out Committee. The records in the file are arranged in chronological order, beginning in 1908. Entries contain information such as who attended meetings of the Boarding Out Committee, the number of applications for boarding out received or the number of children boarded out, and arrangements for visiting homes prior to boarding out and inspections afterwards. Children are often named, particularly in relation to certain incidents or practices. Later entries in the file include detailed information about arrangements for annual Boarded Out Children's Christmas parties (including entertainment items by children), donors and sponsors and correspondence from the Child Welfare Department.</abstract>
<p>This file is an old, bound volume with a paper cover and titled 'Minutes of the Perth and District Boarding Out Committee'. The file is in poor condition but the entries are legible. It is arranged in chronological order, with many pages either blank or glued together. The early entries are handwritten, mostly in ink. The first entry refers to a meeting on 7 July 1908.</p>
<p>Entries generally note who was present or absent, the number of applications for boarding out received or the number of children boarded out, and arrangements for visiting homes prior to boarding out and inspections afterwards. The Committee also noted the 'Lady Inspector/s' of the State Children's Department reports. Comments on, and suggested 'rules' for service children are included in the Minutes.</p>
<p>Children are often named, particularly in relation to certain incidents or practices. Comments about visits to Children's Homes are included, and efforts to obtain toys and other 'comforts' for children is an ongoing theme.</p>
<p>Later entries in the file include detailed information about arrangements for annual Boarded Out Children's Christmas parties (including entertainment items by children), donors and sponsors and correspondence from the Child Welfare Department.</p>
<p>An example of the type of 'cases' referred to in the Minutes of the Boarding Out Committee is the following (names of the child and her foster mother have been removed):</p>
<p>'A discussion took place in regard to the ward AW, boarded out with Miss H [address given]. Reports from Mrs. Finch and Mrs. Bolton were read. Mrs. Kent said she thought as the child was so happy in this home she should remain there. Mrs. Sparks' reports were also read. It was noted that Miss H had not carried out the Inspector's instructions in relation to taking AW to the Children's Hospital. Mrs. Bolton stated that the child was very sick and she should have had the necessary treatment. The Vice-President thought we should have had a report from the Chief Clerk [of the Child Welfare Department] who was present when the Committee met at Miss H's house. Mrs. Kent suggested Miss H should receive some help from the Department. She was aware that there should be sufficient income in a home where a ward was placed, but there was an exception to every rule. She understood the Department was helping people from a fund received from the Lotteries Commission and she thought Miss H could be given some necessities for her home as well as these people. (Minutes of the Boarding Out Committee, 30 April 1934)'</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00839b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Files - Community Welfare ("A" Series), State Records Office of Western Australia (1908 - 1990)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01156b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Contact Details">
State Records Office of Western Australia - Contact Details
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00483b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Boarding Out Committee
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00440b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Boarding Out (1897 - 1976)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'"Care for Children - Committees (Boarding Out Committee (Perth and District)) - Agendas, Minutes and Working Papers - JULY 1908 to MAY 1935"', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">"Care for Children - Committees (Boarding Out Committee (Perth and District)) - Agendas, Minutes and Working Papers - JULY 1908 to MAY 1935"</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00890b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/objects/WD0000252.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Children's Christmas Party [Minutes Boarding Out Committee 1923]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Records Office Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Children's Christmas Party [Minutes Boarding Out Committee 1923]</unittitle>
<unitdate>28 November 1923 - 13 December 1923</unitdate>
<abstract>This is part of a larger file that has Minutes of the Perth and District Boarding Out Committee. This excerpt gives a glimpse of the arrangements leading up to and after the 1923 'Boarded Out Children's Christmas Party' that was held, as usual, in the grounds of Government House.</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/objects/WD0000251.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Care for Children - Committees (Boarding Out Committee (Perth and District)) - Agendas, Minutes and Working Papers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Records Office Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Care for Children - Committees (Boarding Out Committee (Perth and District)) - Agendas, Minutes and Working Papers</unittitle>
<unitdate>25 August 1908 - 19 May 1936</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a digital version of a file held by the State Records Office.</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>

<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>