<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>WE00159</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCWA</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Organisation</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2011-03-15">2011-03-15</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Debra Rosser</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-06-24">2016-06-24</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00159b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="also known as"><part>Alexandra Home for Mothers and Babies</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="also known as"><part>Ngala Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc.</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="also known as"><part>Ngala</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1956-01-01">1956</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1989-12-31">1989</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Maternity Home</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Care Provider</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Babies' Home</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Home</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Adoption Agency</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Disability Institution</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc (Ngala) was the new name given in 1956 to The Alexandra Home for Mothers and Babies (Inc) and Mothercraft Training School, in Highgate. In 1959 Ngala moved to Kensington. Ngala had three functions: a maternity home for mothers and babies; from 1959, the 'reception centre' for all infants admitted to State 'care'; and a training school for mothercraft and infant health nurses. Many babies were adopted from Ngala until 1980 when adoptions ceased. In 1989, Ngala became a family support service called Ngal-a Family Resource Centre and no longer provided institutionalised out of home care. However, it continued as a subsidised facility under child welfare legislation.</abstract>
<p>When Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc (Ngala) began in 1956, it was both a maternity home and a training facility for mothercraft nurses. It was located in Lincoln Street, Highgate, in the premises that had originally been acquired for the House of Mercy in 1901, and which had continued from 1916 as the Alexandra Home for Women and from 1950 as The Alexandra Home for Mothers and Babies (Inc) and Mothercraft Training School.</p>
<p>'Ngal-a' is a Bibbulmun word meaning 'we two' or 'mother and child'.</p>
<p>In August 1959, Ngala moved fromLincoln Street, Highgate, to purpose-built premises on the corner of George Street and Jarrah Road in Kensington.</p>
<p>From September 1959, all infants who were admitted into State 'care' were sent to Ngala instead of being admitted to the Child Welfare Reception Home. These 'infants' were children aged from birth to 5 years and in some government reports were known as 'lone' or 'sole' infants, to distinguish them from babies who were admitted with their mothers. Writing its history in <span style="font-style:italic">The Open Door</span> (1980), Jean Lang reported (p.68) that not all sole children were admitted to Ngala because of child protection issues. Often, the mother was physically ill, or one or both of the child's parents were in a mental health institution. By the mid-1970s, according to Lang (p.85), there were an increasing number of 'multi-social problems', including a 'larger number of Aboriginal children…now being admitted from various tent villages'.</p>
<p>Young children with intellectual, and sometimes physical, disabilities could also be admitted to Ngala from 1959. There was a special wing for children with intellectual disabilities.</p>
<p>Single, pregnant women could be admitted privately to Ngala, or be referred by government agencies prior to the birth of their child. Until 1959, babies whose mothers were resident at Ngala were born at King Edward Memorial Hospital. After Ngala moved to Kensington in 1959, babies were also born at the South Perth Community Centre Hospital. Mothers and babies returned to Ngala after the birth. They were accommodated in the 'Alexandra Wing' at Ngala.</p>
<p>From 2 November 1959, Ngala also trained Infant Health Nurses.</p>
<p>In the first four months after its relocation to Kensington, Ngala admitted 230 pregnant women, mothers, babies and young children. In the year ending June 1961, 46 children were adopted from Ngala. Ngala also accepted babies who were awaiting adoption and whose mothers had not been admitted to Ngala before their confinement.</p>
<p>Lang (1980) writes that Ngala was involved in three aspects of the birth of children to single mothers: accommodation and support for young women who were determined to keep their child; accommodation and/or foster placement of babies while an adoption placement was sought for them; and the preparation of adopting mothers.</p>
<p>While the consent of both parents was legally required before a baby could be adopted from Ngala, State and Commonwealth inquiries have found that many young parents did not make an informed choice to allow their baby to be adopted. Following the Parliamentary apology to people involved in adoption in Western Australia in 2010, Ngala issued a statement of support and expressed regret for the trauma that past maternity and adoption practices caused to mothers 'and their children'. Submissions to the Commonwealth Contribution to Former Forced Adoption Policies and Practices in 2012 showed that the impact of this trauma was long-lasting.</p>
<p>During the 1960s, children and young people referred to Ngala by child welfare authorities were recorded in the annual reports of the Child Welfare Department (<span style="font-style:italic">Signposts</span>, 2004 pp.372-373). A year-end census of children who were wards of the state and those who were classed as 'private children' under 6 years of age at year end was also reported. In 1961, there were 137 admissions (representing 51 individual children), with 20 children who were 'wards' and 6 under-sixes who were 'private children' at year end. In 1965, there were 95 admissions (representing 56 individual children), with 25 children who were 'wards' and 31 under-sixes who were 'private children' at year end. In 1968, the last year that statistics were presented in this way, there were 94 admissions (representing 57 individual children), with 2 children who were 'wards' and 16 under-sixes who were 'private children' at year end. From 1966 to 1968, the number of children who were classed as 'native wards' were also identified in admission statistics. There were six children admitted as 'native wards' in 1966, 9 in 1967 and 14 in 1968.</p>
<p>In 1975 (<span style="font-style:italic">Signposts</span>, 2004 p.373) Ngala was described by the Department for Community Welfare as providing short term care for up to 89 infants and boys and girls aged 0-5 years, with the average length of stay being 'around 1 year'. Sibling groups were admitted together and 'foster placements were actively sought for the children'. School-age and pre-school children walked to the local school. There was a range of play equipment including: 'garden, play area, 2 swimming pools, swings and slides, tennis court, cubby house, bikes, 2 sandpits, a boat, 2 adventure playgrounds and educational toys that could be used outdoors…TV, piano, radio or radiogram, library, toys and a fish tank'. Visits outside Ngala were said to be 'many and varied and included going to town, the zoo, on the ferry'. Ngala's approach to accommodating 'unmarried mothers' was also described: it provided for 'confinement' and assisted in 'rehabilitation'. This section of Ngala was known as the Alexandra Wing. At this time, aaccording to Lang (p.83), all but one of the pregnant women in the Alexandra Wing were 'schoolgirls' who were provided with a tutor while at Ngala.</p>
<p>In 1989, Ngala became a family support service called Ngal-a Family Resource Centre and no longer provided institutionalised out of home care. However, it continued as a subsidised facility under child welfare legislation.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1956-01-01">1956</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1959-12-31">1959</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Highgate</placeEntry>
<event>Location - The Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc was located in Lincoln Street, Highgate</event>
</chronItem>
<chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1959-01-01">1959</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1989-12-31">1989</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Kensington</placeEntry>
<event>Address - The Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc operated from purpose-built premises on the corner of George Street and Jarrah Road, Kensington</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-earlier" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01415b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
The Alexandra Home for Mothers and Babies (Inc) and Mothercraft Training School (1950 - 1956)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00907b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Interview with Beryl Grant, nurse, State Library of Western Australia (1977)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01493b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Picture South Perth Photograph Collection (1870s - 2000s)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00623b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Ngala Adoption Records (1958 - 1980)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00469b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Unmarried Mothers
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00455b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Mothercraft Nurse (1940s - 1970s)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00438b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Adoption (1896 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00646b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Private Child (1870s - 1970s)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00906b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Interview with Helen Jean Duncan, State Library of Western Australia (1977)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01418b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
South Perth Hospital Maternity Records (1959 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00910b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Interview with Beryl Grant, Matron of Ngala, 1959-1980
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00944b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Interview with Beryl Grant, nurse, State Library of Western Australia (1989)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00481b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Department for Child Protection and Family Support [and its predecessors] Records (1894 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00365b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Department for Community Welfare, State of Western Australia (1972 - 1985)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Department for Community Welfare placed young children under the age of six years at Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc (Ngala) and, until 1980 when Ngala ceased its involvement in adoption, may also have placed young expectant mothers there.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00990b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Intellectual Disability
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00764b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Beryl Grant interviewed by Christine Choo in the Forgotten Australians and Former Child Migrants oral history project (2011)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00364b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Child Welfare Department, State of Western Australia (1927 - 1972)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1956-01-01">1956?</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1972-12-31">1972</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Child Welfare Department placed all children under the age of six years at Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc (Ngala) from 1 September 1959 (and possibly earlier) instead of the Child Welfare Reception Home.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01082b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
King Edward Memorial Hospital (1916 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1956-01-01">1956</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1989-12-31">1989</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc. (Ngala) sent all resident expectant mothers to King Edward Memorial Hospital (KEMH) for the birth of their babies in the years between 1956 and 1959. From 1959 to 1980 some women still had their babies at KEMH. Mothers and babies generally returned to Ngala after the birth, but from September 1959, babies could be sent from KEMH to Ngala without their mothers.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01416b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
South Perth Community Centre Hospital Inc, South Perth Community Hospital (1956 - 2003)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1959-01-01">1959</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1980-12-31">1980</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc sent some expectant mothers to the South Perth Community Centre Hospital Inc for the birth of their babies.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00369b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Department for Community Services, State of Western Australia (1985 - 1992)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1985-01-01">1985</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1989-12-31">1989</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Department for Community Services placed young children under the age of six years at Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00159b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0001384.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: South Perth Hospital - Our History</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">South Perth Hospital - Our History</title>
<imprint>
<place>Perth, Western Australia</place>
<publisher>South Perth Hospital</publisher>
<date>1989</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.sph.org.au/our-history"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0001017.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Submission No. 150 Commonwealth Contribution to Former Forced Adoption Policies and Practices</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Submission No. 150 Commonwealth Contribution to Former Forced Adoption Policies and Practices</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Commonwealth of Australia</publisher>
<date>2012</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Submissions received by the Committee</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.aph.gov.au/Parliamentary_Business/Committees/Senate/Community_Affairs/Completed_inquiries/2010-13/commcontribformerforcedadoption/submissions"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0001009.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Submission No. 48 Commonwealth Contribution to Former Forced Adoption Policies and Practices</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Submission No. 48 Commonwealth Contribution to Former Forced Adoption Policies and Practices</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Commonwealth of Australia</publisher>
<date>2012</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Submissions received by the Committee</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.aph.gov.au/Parliamentary_Business/Committees/Senate/Community_Affairs/Completed_inquiries/2010-13/commcontribformerforcedadoption/submissions"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000775.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Statement of Support for Adoption Apology [Ngala]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Ngala</name>
<title render="quoted">Statement of Support for Adoption Apology [Ngala]</title>
<imprint>
<date>2009</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.ngala.com.au/About-Ngala/History/Statement-of-Support-for-Adoption-Apology"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000774.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: History</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Ngala</name>
<title render="italic">History</title>
<imprint>
<date>2009</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.ngala.com.au/About-Ngala/History"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000645.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book Section: Ngala</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Grant, Beryl</name>
<title render="quoted">Ngala</title>
<imprint>
<place>Crawley, W.A.</place>
<publisher>University of Western Australia Press</publisher>
<date>2009</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Historical Encyclopedia of Western Australia</title>
<name type="author">Gregory, Jenny and Jan Gothard [editors]</name>
<num type="pages">635-636</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000500.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Submission No. 55 Inquiry into Children in Institutional Care: Submissions</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Department for Community Development, State of Western Australia</name>
<title render="quoted">Submission No. 55 Inquiry into Children in Institutional Care: Submissions</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Commonwealth of Australia</publisher>
<date>2003</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Inquiry into Children in Institutional Care - Submissions received by the committee as at 17/3/05</title>
<name type="author">Senate Community Affairs Committee</name>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.aph.gov.au/Parliamentary_Business/Committees/Senate/Community_Affairs/Completed_inquiries/2004-07/inst_care/submissions/sublist"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000324.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Western Australian Government Gazette Online Archive</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Western Australian Government Gazette Online Archive</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>State Law Publisher of Western Australia</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">State Law Publisher: Official Publisher of Western Australian Legislation and Statutory Information</title>
<name type="author">Western Australia</name>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.slp.wa.gov.au/gazette/gazette.nsf"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000006.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: The Open Door: a History of Loving Care for Families, House of Mercy-Alexandra Home-Ngala, 1890-1980</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Lang, Jean</name>
<title render="italic">The Open Door: a History of Loving Care for Families, House of Mercy-Alexandra Home-Ngala, 1890-1980</title>
<imprint>
<place>Perth</place>
<publisher>Ngala Mothercraft Home &amp; Training Centre Inc.</publisher>
<date>1980</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000001.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Signposts: A Guide for Children and Young People in Care in WA from 1920</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Information Services, Department for Community Development</name>
<title render="italic">Signposts: A Guide for Children and Young People in Care in WA from 1920</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Government of Western Australia</publisher>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://signposts.cpfs.wa.gov.au/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/objects/WD0001020.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">The entrance of Ngala, 1961</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>City of South Perth Local History Collection</repository>
<unittitle>The entrance of Ngala, 1961</unittitle>
<unitid>City of South Perth Local History Collection COSP_PH_2224/</unitid>
<unitdate>1961</unitdate>
<abstract>This digitised image is part of the Picture South Perth Photograph Collection. Matron Beryl Grant is pictured with some children at the front entrance of the Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by City of South Perth</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/objects/WD0000285.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Sister Janet Chin, from Malaya [Ngala]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>PhotoSearch, National Archives of Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Sister Janet Chin, from Malaya [Ngala]</unittitle>
<unitid>PhotoSearch Image no. A1501, A4281/3 Barcode 8925298</unitid>
<unitdate>1963</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a digital version of an image held by the 'PhotoSearch' site of the National Archives of Australia.The full title is 'Sister Janet Chin, from Malaya [Malaysia], a triple certificated nurse has spent 18 months in Australia as a private student, specialising in maternal and infant care and obtaining a diploma in child care at Ngala, a mothercraft and infant welfare centre in South Perth - Sister Chin with five month old baby Diane [photographic image] / photographer, W Hartley. 1 photographic negative: b&amp;w, acetate'.</abstract>
<note label="rights">National Archives of Australia</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>