<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>WE00077</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCWA</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Organisation</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2011-03-15">2011-03-15</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Debra Rosser</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-04-21">2016-04-21</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00077b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Forrest River Mission</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="also known as"><part>Oombulgurri</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="also known as"><part>Umbulgara</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1913-01-01">1913</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1968-12-31">1968</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Mission</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Anglican</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Home</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Protestant</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Forrest River Mission was established by the Anglican church in 1913, on the upper reaches of the Forrest River, near Wyndham. Around 40 Aboriginal boys and girls lived at the mission and were separated from their parents and lived in dormitories. Their lives were closely regulated until the 1950s. The head of the government departments responsible for Aboriginal welfare was the guardian of children at the mission, which closed in 1968.</abstract>
<p>According to Neville Green, who has written (2011) a comprehensive history of Forrest River Mission, it was run at first by the Perth Diocesan Board of Missions (p.8) and in the 1920s (p.43) by the Australian Board of Missions who, from the 1920s received a government subsidy for housing children. Children were sent from the Fitzroy Crossing district and east to the Northern Territory border. On 1 June 1955 (p.147), the Australian Board of Missions transferred responsibility to the Anglican Diocese of Perth, which set up a Forrest River Committee. In 1965 an advisory committee was set up in the Kimberley.</p>
<p>Forrest River Mission was established by an Anglican missionary, Rev. Gribble, in 1913. A boys' dormitory was built in 1914 and a girls' dormitory in 1915. (Green, 2011 p.39). There was a school at the mission from the outset. Children went to school in the morning and worked around the mission in the afternoons. The school was closed during harvest time. Green reports (p.42) that the dormitories were padlocked, preventing children interacting with family and others at the mission.</p>
<p>Forrest River Mission (Green, p.13) was run with strict rules and institutional conventions that included defined hours of 'rising, eating, working, praying and sleeping' and clothing issued by the mission. Children were separated from their parents and boys and girls were kept apart. These practices continued 'well beyond the Second World War' according to Green who observed that children brought up on the mission were 'often ill-prepared for mainstream society'. Green's research (p.83) found that it was only on Christmas Day that boys were allowed to sit with their parents and spend the day with them. Girls were allowed to leave their dormitories, too, but unlike the boys they had to ask permission from staff to leave the dormitory and talk to family and others.</p>
<p>Reflecting on the loss of traditional culture, Green (p.19) writes that children were regularly baptised and in the early days they could keep their Aboriginal name as a second name but by 1948, only one name (a European name) was allowed. Until 1928, girls were married to boys chosen by Rev. Gribble when a girl reached puberty. This horrified an observer in 1928 (p.24) as the young couple had no real knowledge of each other or choice in the marriage, which were often contrary to traditional marriage rules, and certainly disregarded them. When the couple had a baby, it was removed to the dormitory.</p>
<p>Discipline was harsh, according to Green (p.25): children could be 'strapped, have their hair cropped or made to stand on a box in a public place while balancing a watermelon on their heads'. These disciplines were originally undertaken by Rev Gribble, but were later enforced by schoolteachers and dormitory matrons.</p>
<p>Gribble was transferred from Forrest River by the Australian Board of Missions in November 1928 (Green, pp.25, 58). A number of Anglican ministers were appointed as superintendents of Forrest River in the years following Gribble's retirement (p.57).</p>
<p>In 1930, (Green,p.65) staff at the mission were accused by the superintendent of sodomising 'mission boys'; a female staff member was accused of 'taking lewd photographs of the girls in her care' and selling those photographs in Wyndham. The staff accused the superintendent of using 'the chain as a punishment'. The superintendent resigned, the male abuser committed suicide and the female was dismissed without criminal charges being laid.</p>
<p>In 1936, a new girls' dormitory was built (Green, p.92).</p>
<p>In February 1942, after Darwin was bombed, Green (p.98) records that the dormitory children were evacuated to temporary camps near waterholes around the mission. When they returned to the mission, it was to face food shortages during the war years. While this no doubt caused hardship, Green (p.103) reports that it also enabled children to be allowed to search for bush tucker and to join the Forrest River adults in monthly corroborees to share the gathered food. During the war years, the children were also allowed to have regular, organised 'games evenings' which Green says (p.108) helped to break down the gender barrier between the girls and boys in the dormitories. Decisions were taken about clothing the children would wear during the war, when funds were even lower than usual and Aboriginal people were not entitled to clothing coupons. Green writes (pp.116-117) that 'children under five years would not wear clothes; boys between the ages of five and eleven years would wear short pants and the girls of that age would wear only waist skirts'. The older boys would wear shorts and a sleeveless shirt and older girls would have one dress. There was no mention of underwear. Sugar bags could be made into dresses for little girls on special occasions. Weekly washing was done at the river by women and girls in the traditional way.</p>
<p>School continued for the children throughout World War II and Anglican schools were asked (Green, p.107) to support 'nominated children'. Until 1947, schooling at Forrest River was held in the open air (p.114). According to Green (pp.124, 127, 132) the Bateman Survey in 1947 criticised the lack of proper education opportunities for children at the Forrest River Mission and authorities felt that the isolated position of the mission would not assist the assimilation policies that were gaining currency. In 1953, Forrest River accepted the offer of a government teacher and very minimal funding for school supplies.</p>
<p>Green (p.132) writes that even during the 1950s children had a poor diet, with fresh meat only once a week and damper and tinned meat thereafter.</p>
<p>In 1956, after months of planning and considerable bureaucratic juggling, eight children from the mission went to a holiday camp at Point Peron, south of Perth (Green, p.134). In the late 1950s, children were also being given the opportunity to go on school trips to Wyndham (p.134). In 1961, a two-classroom government school was built at the mission (pp.136-137) and in 1963, staff took the children up to Kununurra to see the Queen.</p>
<p>In 1968, with mounting debts and large expenses, Green reports (pp.153, 157) that Forrest River Mission was closed by Anglican authorities. Children joined their families and were 'scattered across several Wyndham reserves.</p>
<p>On 4 October 1970, Green records (p.162), a group of former Forrest River Mission residents formed the Oombulgurri Committee and decided to return to the land which would thereafter be known as the self-governing community of Oombulgurri.</p>
<h4>The Forrest River Massacre</h4>
<p>Western Australian historian Neville Green (2009 pp.559-560) reports that in 1926, there was a massacre of Aboriginal people from the Forrest River Mission. In January 1927, Magistrate GT Wood held a Royal Commission into the incident and found that 11 people were murdered and their bodies burned to hide the evidence. Two police officers were charged with one murder, but at the committal hearings Magistrate Kitson determined there was not enough evidence to proceed. Historians and anthropologists have since confirmed the massacre did occur as the superintendent of the mission alleged.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1913-01-01">1913</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1968-12-31">1968</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Forrest River</placeEntry>
<event>Location - Forrest River Mission was located at Forrest River, near Wyndham in the Kimberley</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00010b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Anglican Diocese of Perth (1856 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1913-01-01">1913</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1968-12-31">1968</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Direct responsibility for Forrest River Mission was given by the Anglican Diocese of Perth to subsidiary Anglican organisations from the 1920s, and handed back to the Diocese in 1955.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00553b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Concept">
Commissioner for Native Affairs (1936 - 1954)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Commissioner of Native Affairs was the legal guardian of children at Forrest River Mission.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00499b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Concept">
Chief Protector of Aborigines (1898 - 1936)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Chief Protector of Aborigines was the legal guardian of children at Forrest River Mission.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00481b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Department for Child Protection and Family Support [and its predecessors] Records (1894 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00593b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Anglican Diocese of Perth, Western Australia, Records (1880s - 2010)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00752b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Neville Green interviewed by John Bannister in the Bringing them home oral history project (1999)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01388b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Photographs of Forrest River Mission [picture], State Library of Western Australia (1914 - 1967)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00571b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Mission (1829? - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00467b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Stolen Generations (c. 1981 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00637b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
State Archives Collection of Western Australia (1829 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01120b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Department of Aboriginal Affairs [predecessors], Records, Department of Aboriginal Affairs (1886 - 2004)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00554b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Concept">
Commissioner of Native Welfare (1954 - 1972)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1954-01-01">1954</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1972-12-31">1972</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Commissioner of Native Welfare was the legal guardian of children at Forrest River Mission until 1963 when could regulate the 'care' of Aboriginal children.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Forrest River Mission', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Forrest River Mission</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00077b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000204.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Guide to Institutions Attended by Aboriginal People in Western Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">State Solicitor's Office of Western Australia</name>
<title render="italic">Guide to Institutions Attended by Aboriginal People in Western Australia</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Government of Western Australia</publisher>
<date>2005</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://web.archive.org/web/20140126131607/http://www.dpc.wa.gov.au/lantu/MediaPublications/Documents/Guide-to-Institutions-attended-by-Aboriginal-people-in-WA-2005.pdf"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000041.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Historical Encyclopedia of Western Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Gregory, Jenny and Jan Gothard [editors]</name>
<title render="italic">Historical Encyclopedia of Western Australia</title>
<imprint>
<place>Crawley, W.A.</place>
<publisher>University of Western Australia Press</publisher>
<date>2009</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0001341.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Forrest River Mission Private Archives Collection Listing</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Forrest River Mission Private Archives Collection Listing</title>
<imprint>
<date>2006</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">State Library of Western Australia website</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.slwa.wa.gov.au/pdf/mn/mn501_1000/mn0545.pdf"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0001340.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Triumphs and tragedies : Oombulgurri : an Australian aboriginal community</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Green, Neville</name>
<title render="italic">Triumphs and tragedies : Oombulgurri : an Australian aboriginal community</title>
<imprint>
<place>Carlisle, Western Australia</place>
<publisher>Hesperian Press</publisher>
<date>2011</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000025.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: To Remove and Protect: Aboriginal Lives Under Control [website]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">AIATSIS</name>
<title render="italic">To Remove and Protect: Aboriginal Lives Under Control [website]</title>
<imprint>
<date>2010</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://aiatsis.gov.au/archive_digitised_collections/remove/index.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000717.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Was it worthwhile?</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Longworth, Alison</name>
<title render="italic">Was it worthwhile?</title>
<imprint>
<place>Murdoch, Western Australia</place>
<publisher>Murdoch University</publisher>
<date>2005</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">An historical analysis of five women missionaries and their encounters with the Nyungar people of south-west Australia</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://researchrepository.murdoch.edu.au/163/2/02Whole.pdf"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000005.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Looking West: A Guide to Aboriginal Sources in Western Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">State Records Taskforce, Government of Western Australia</name>
<title render="italic">Looking West: A Guide to Aboriginal Sources in Western Australia</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Government of Western Australia</publisher>
<date>2004</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://pandora.nla.gov.au/pan/42687/20040616-0000/www.lookingwest.communitydevelopment.wa.gov.au/menu.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000011.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies [website]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies (AIATSIS)</name>
<title render="italic">Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies [website]</title>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://aiatsis.gov.au/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000025.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: To Remove and Protect: Aboriginal Lives Under Control [website]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">AIATSIS</name>
<title render="italic">To Remove and Protect: Aboriginal Lives Under Control [website]</title>
<imprint>
<date>2010</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://aiatsis.gov.au/archive_digitised_collections/remove/index.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000001.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Signposts: A Guide for Children and Young People in Care in WA from 1920</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Information Services, Department for Community Development</name>
<title render="italic">Signposts: A Guide for Children and Young People in Care in WA from 1920</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Government of Western Australia</publisher>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://signposts.cpfs.wa.gov.au/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/objects/WD0000995.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Aerial photograph of Forest River Mission [picture]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Aerial photograph of Forest River Mission [picture]</unittitle>
<unitid>State Library of Western Australia Richard Woldendorp collection of photographs; BA1611/1635</unitid>
<unitdate>1993</unitdate>
<abstract>'Aerial photograph of Forest River Mission [picture]' is an image from the Richard Woldendorp collection of photographs, held by the State Library of Western Australia. Although taken decades after Forrest River Mission closed, it gives a sense of the remoteness of the mission and its overall location.</abstract>
<note label="rights">State Library of Western Australia</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/objects/WD0000116.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Sunday Island Mission evidence to Roth royal commission</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Sunday Island Mission evidence to Roth royal commission</unittitle>
<unitdate>25 February 1905</unitdate>
<abstract>This digital copy of an article from <span style="font-style:italic">The Western Mail </span> in February 1905 gives an account of testimony by Montague Sydney Hadley, who was in charge of the Sunday Island Mission.</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>