<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>WE01313</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCWA</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Archival Item</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-12-16">2013-12-16</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Debra Rosser</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2015-07-30">2015-07-30</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01313b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>concept</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Cottesloe Girls Closed Social Work</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1898-01-01">1898</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1998-12-31">1998</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Cottesloe Girls Closed Social Work is a file held in the Children's Homes Files series at the Salvation Army Heritage Museum WA. It has material dated between 1898 and 1998, principally related to the Salvation Army Girls' Home, Cottesloe but also to other Homes run by the Salvation Army. It does not include any personal records, but does have photographs of children and staff.</abstract>
<h4>Access Conditions</h4>
<p>Access to most items in the file is open, but it is essential to make an appointment to view.</p>
<h4>Records</h4>
<p>The Cottesloe Girls Closed Social Work file is one of the three files at the Heritage Museum relating to the Salvation Army Girls' Home, Cottesloe. The file also has information relevant to many other Homes run by the Salvation Army, and Salvation Army activities generally.</p>
<p>There is historical information in the file about the Collie Boys' Home; Crossroads west; Graceville; Hillcrest; the Hollywood Children's Village; the Salvation Army Boys' Home (Nedlands, West Subiaco); the Salvation Army Industrial School for Boys, Collie; the Salvation Army Industrial School for Girls, Collie; the Seaforth Salvation Army Boys' Home, Gosnells; and Withnell House.</p>
<p>There are no personal records included in this file, but there are photographs of children and staff.</p>
<p>Some documents from the file are briefly described below:</p>
<h4>Brief History of Cottesloe Home for Girls, 1918-1970</h4>
<p>This is a short history written by Phyl Crompton, Archivist of The Salvation Army Historical Society WA. From information in the item, it can be dated to 1996.</p>
<h4>Wartime Evacuation from The Salvation Army Girls' Home Cottesloe Western Australia</h4>
<p>This is a short history written by Leslie Rusher, Commissioner. From information in the item, it can be dated to 1996. The item reports that the Home returned to Cottesloe in 1945 but in fact it was 1944.</p>
<h4>Cottesloe Girls Home</h4>
<p>This is an undated short history. It includes an account of the evacuation to Kellerberrin during World War II and reports that girls and staff transferred to Withnell House in Mt Lawley in 1969 and from there to Hollywood Children's Village.</p>
<h4>Historical Record [Salvation Army Girls' Home, Cottesloe] </h4>
<p>This item has two parts: there is a three-page photocopied excerpt (1918-1950) and an 18-page printed document that is 'an exact copy retyped' of the 'Historical Records of The Children's Home Institution 15 Broome Street Cottesloe Beach Western Australia' (1918-1957). It includes many notable events, such as the impact of World War II, outings and entertainments and a description of an officer's fall from the roof in 1941.</p>
<h4>The Salvation Army - Nedlands</h4>
<p>This is a short history written by Phyl Crompton, Archivist of The Salvation Army Historical Society WA. It has information about the Salvation Army's activities and institutions in Nedlands (West Subiaco), the Nedlands Boys' Home, the Hollywood Children's Village, Withnell House (Maylands) and aged care facilities on the Hollywood (Nedlands) site.</p>
<h4>Crossroads west: WA youth program in strong demand during its first year [excerpt]</h4>
<p>This item is a photocopied excerpt from an article in <span style="font-style:italic">The War Cry</span> dated 27 June 1992 (p.3) celebrating the Salvation Army's youth programs. There are photographs of young people and Salvation Army officers. The remainder of the article, which is continued on page 7, is not included in the excerpt.</p>
<h4>The General's Representative Leaves Australia</h4>
<p>This is a photocopied excerpt (p.5) from <span style="font-style:italic">The War Cry</span> dated 27 September 1919. It has information about the Salvation Army Girls' Home, Cottesloe; the the Salvation Army Boys' Home, (West Subiaco, Nedlands); the Salvation Army Boys' Home, Collie; the Salvation Army Industrial School for Girls, Collie; and the Salvation Army Industrial School for Boys, Collie.</p>
<h4>Inspection Report - West Australia</h4>
<p>This is a photocopy of a report signed by MC Watson, stamped 20 November 1959. There is information about Hillcrest; the Salvation Army Girls' Home, Cottesloe; and Graceville.</p>
<h4>Salvation Warfare in the Wide Open West</h4>
<p>This is a photocopied excerpt from <span style="font-style:italic">The War Cry</span> with a handwritten date, 8 August 1959. It has impressions of the Hillcrest maternity hospital, Graceville, and the Salvation Army Girls' Home, Cottesloe.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01303b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Children's Homes Files (1897 - 2012)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01300b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Contact Details">
Salvation Army Heritage Museum WA - Contact Details
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Cottesloe Girls Closed Social Work', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Cottesloe Girls Closed Social Work</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01313b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/objects/WD0000753.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Regulations Historical Record</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Salvation Army Heritage Museum WA</repository>
<unittitle>Regulations Historical Record</unittitle>
<unitdate>1918? - 1969?</unitdate>
<abstract>'Regulations Historical Record' is a digital copy of an item held in the <span style="font-style:italic">Cottesloe Girls closed social work</span> lever-arch file at the Salvation Army Heritage Museum WA. The item is an undated photocopy of the front page of the Cottesloe Girls' Home historical record. It shows the types of 'events or incidents' that Managers were required to record in all the 'social institutions'.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Salvation Army Heritage Museum WA</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>