<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>WE01489</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCWA</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Glossary Term</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2014-11-25">2014-11-25</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Debra Rosser</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2017-08-08">2017-08-08</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01489b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>concept</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Subsidised Institution</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="also known as"><part>Scheduled Institution</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1874-01-01">1874</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Subsidised institution (or scheduled institution) is a term that has been used in Western Australia to describe an institution which received a government inmate subsidy for eligible children accommodated there. At various times, a list of these subsidised institutions would be attached as a schedule to child welfare legislation.</abstract>
<p>Western Australia did not and does not have provision for licensing institutions which had the care of children over the age of three (and, from 1919, six years). The names of institutions which would receive a subsidy from the government (subsidised or scheduled institutions) were listed in child welfare legislation (usually in the Second Schedule), but the names were descriptive rather than legal/formal (except sometimes where the Institution/Home was an incorporated body). The names in the schedules are frequently not identical to the name used in the annual reports of the department responsible for child welfare. The Second Schedule (and institution names) were sometimes updated when there were other amendments to the Act. However, the fact that an amendment to an Act was made without updating the names in the Second Schedule should not be confirmation that an institution did not change its name during the break between Second Schedule updates. Regardless of the name used, the institutions were subsidised by the State and subject to the protections and responsibilities of the Act. The latest legislation to follow this practice was the Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1976 (No 2).</p>
<p>To 1970, the only government Home that was named in Second Schedules was the main Reception Home at Mt Lawley. The Reception Home at Bridgewater was not added to the schedule after it opened in 1969. Possibly, as they ran their own Homes, the government didn't have to subsidise them as the appropriations came from the departmental budget.</p>
<h4>Second Schedules 1907-1976</h4>
<h4> State Children Act 1907</h4>
<p>Section 15 of the State Children Act 1907: '(1) The Government Industrial School at Subiaco, established before the commencement of this Act, is hereby declared to be a Government institution within the meaning and for the purposes of this Act. (2.) The orphanages and industrial and reformatory schools established before the commencement of this Act, specified in the Second Schedule, are hereby declared to be subsidised institutions within the meaning and for the purposes of this Act.' 'Section 15. SECOND SCHEDULE. The St. Joseph's Roman Catholic Orphanage, Subiaco ; the Church of England Girls' Orphanage, Adelaide Terrace, Perth ; the Swan Boys' Orphanage, near Midland Junction ; the Clontarf Roman Catholic Orphanage, near Victoria Park ; the St. Kevin's Roman Catholic Industrial School, near Leederville ; the Red Hill Industrial School, near Midland Junction ; the Salvation Army Industrial Schools for Boys and Girls, near Collie.'</p>
<h4> State Children Act Amendment Act 1927</h4>
<p>In the State Children Act Amendment Act 1927, s.15 of the State Children Act 1907 was repealed as follows: 's.15. The second schedule to the principal Act is repealed and a schedule is inserted in place thereof, as follows:- SECOND SCHEDULE. St. Joseph's Roman Catholic Orphanage for Girls, Subiaco. The Anglican Girls' Orphanage, Adelaide Terrace, Perth. The Salvation Army Girls' Home, Cottesloe Beach. The Salvation Army Girls' Industrial School, Gosnells. The Home of the Good Shepherd Industrial School for Girls, Leederville. The Swan Boys' Anglican Orphanage, near Midland Junction. The Clontarf Roman Catholic Boys' Orphanage, near Victoria Park. The Salvation Army Boys' Home, West Subiaco. The Seaforth Salvation Army Boys' Home, Gosnells. The Seaforth Salvation Army Backward Boys' Home, Gosnells. The Seaforth Salvation Army Boys' Industrial School, Gosnells. The Methodist Children's Home, Victoria Park. The St. Vincent's Roman Catholic Foundling Home, Subiaco. The Children's Home, Parkerville. The Government Receiving Depot. Walcott Street, Mount Lawley.'</p>
<h4>Child Welfare Act 1947</h4>
<p>Section 15 used the language of the State Children Act 1907 to enable 'orphanages and industrial schools' in the Child Welfare Act 1947 Second Schedule to be 'subsidised institutions'. 'SECOND SCHEDULE St. Joseph's Roman Catholic Orphanage for Girls, Subiaco. The Salvation Army Girls' Home, Cottesloe Beach. The Home of the Good Shepherd Roman Catholic Industrial School for Girls, Leederville. The Swan Boys' Anglican Orphanage, near Midland Junction. The Clontarf Roman Catholic Boys' Orphanage, near Victoria Park. The Salvation Army Boys' Home, West Subiaco. The Seaforth Salvation Army Backward Boys' Home, Gosnells. The Seaforth Salvation Army Boys' Industrial School, Gosnells. The Methodist Children's Home, Victoria Park. The St. Vincent's Roman Catholic Foundling Home, Subiaco. The Children's Home, Parkerville. The Government Receiving Home, Walcott Street, Mount Lawley. The Tom Allan Memorial Home (Methodist) for Boys, Werribee. The Castledare Roman Catholic Junior Orphanage, Queen's Park. The Presbyterian Children's Home, Byford. St. Joseph's Roman Catholic Farm School, Bindoon. Nazareth House (Roman Catholic), Geraldton. Benmore Presbyterian Boys' Home, Caversham. Padbury Boys' (Anglican) Farm School, Stoneville. Anglican Children's Home, Coogee Beach. Swan Girls' Home (Anglican), Middle Swan.'</p>
<h4>Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1962</h4>
<p>In the Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1962, the second schedule was amended: '15. The Second Schedule to the principal Act is amended (a) by substituting for the words, "Anglican Farm School" in line two, the words, "Hillston, Anglican Farm School"; (b) by substituting for the words, "Swan Homes for Children" in line seven, the word, "Swanleigh"; © by deleting the passage, "Burnbrae Children's Home (Girls), Byford." in the third last line; and (d) by substituting for the passage, "Alexandra Home for Babies (Boys and Girls), Highgate." in the last line the following passages- Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre, Inc. (Boys and Girls), South Perth. Sister Kate's Children's Home, Inc. (Boys and Girls), Queen's Park.'</p>
<h4>Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1967</h4>
<p>In the Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1967, the second schedule is amended: 'The Second Schedule to the principal Act is amended by deleting (a) the item, "Tom Allan Memorial Home for Boys, Werribee.", under the subheading, "Methodist:"; and (b) the subheading, "Presbyterian:" and the item, "Benmore Boys' Home, Caversham.", under that subheading.'</p>
<h4>Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1970</h4>
<p>In the Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1970, the second schedule (s.15) is amended: 's. 6 SECOND SCHEDULE. Church of England: Swanleigh (Boys and Girls), Middle Swan. Parkerville Children's Home Inc. (Boys and Girls), Parkerville. Roman Catholic: Catherine McAuley Centre. St Vincent's (Boys and Girls), Wembley. St. Joseph's (Girls), Wembley. Castledare Boys' Home, Cannington, Clontarf Boys' Town, Victoria Park. St. Mary's Agricultural School (Boys), Tardun. Nazareth House (Girls), Geraldton. Neuville Training &amp; Assessment Centre (Girls), Leederville. Salvation Army: Salvation Army Hollywood Children's Village (Boys and Girls), Hollywood. Methodist: Methodist Homes for Children, Victoria Park. Allandale Home (Boys). Werribee Hostel (Girls). Mofflyn Home (Girls and Boys). Undenominational: Ngal-a Mothercraft Home and Training Centre Inc. (Boys and Girls), South Perth. Sister Kate's Children's Homes Inc. (Boys and Girls), Queen's Park. Wanslea Hostel (Boys and Girls), Cottesloe.'</p>
<h4>Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1976 (No 2)</h4>
<p>In 1976, the Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1976 (No 2) repealed (s.14) the previous Second Schedules as follows: '14. "Section 15 of the principal Act is repealed and re-enacted with amendments as follows- 15. Subject to the provisions of subsection (2) of section fourteen of this Act the centres and facilities specified in the Second Schedule to this Act are declared to be subsidised centres or facilities."' These were listed in the new Second Schedule as follows '(s.137): SECOND SCHEDULE. SUBSIDISED CENTRES OR FACILITIES. CATHOLIC: Catherine McAuley Centre, St. Vincents's, St. Joseph's, "Salvado", Castledare, Christian Community Inc., Clontarf, Good Shepherd Teen Centre, Pallotine Centre Rossmoyne, Catherine House Inc., Balgo Mission, Beagle Bay Mission, Benedictine Mission Kalumburu, La Grange Mission, Lombardina Mission, Nazareth House Geraldton, Pallotine Boys Hostel Albany, Pallotine Mission, Tardun, St. Francis Xavier's Native Mission, St. Joseph's Hostel Derby, Yaandina Babies &amp; Childrens Centre Inc. ANGLICAN: Parkerville Children's Homes (Inc.) Swanleigh BAPTIST: Katukutu Hostel, Marribank Mission CHRISTIAN BRETHREN ABSEMBIES: Kurrawang Aboriginal Christian Centre Inc. CHURCHES OF CHRIST: "Bamburra" Hostel, Churches of Christ Ingada Village-Carnarvon, Churches of Christ Aborigines Mission-Norseman, Churches of Christ Roelands Village, "Fairhaven" Training Hostel Esperance METHODIST: Homes for Children: "Mofflyn" "Allandale" "Werribee" "Bourkedale" "Cooinda" "Meribah" "Warminda", Mogumber Training Centre Applecross Cottage, Ardross Hostel, Greenmount Hostel (Innaminka), Mt. Yokine Hostel, Nollamara Cottage PRESBYTERIAN: Sister Kate's Children's Homes (Inc.), Collins House SALVATION ARMY: Hollywood Children's Village, "Cottesloe House" UNDENOMINATIONAL: Fairbridge, Ngal-a Mothercraft Home &amp; Training Centre (Inc.), Wanslea Hostel'.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00425b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
Child Welfare Amendment Act (No 2) 1976 (1976 - 2006)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Subsidised institutions were named in the Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1976 (No 2).</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00422b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1962 (1962 - 2004)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Subsidised institutions were named in the Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1962.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00417b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
Child Welfare Act 1947 (1948 - 2006)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Subsidised institutions were named in the Child Welfare Act 1947.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00410b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
State Children Act Amendment Act 1927 (1927 - 1948)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Subsidised institutions were named in the State Children Act Amendment Act 1927.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00407b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
State Children Act 1907 (1907 - 1948)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Subsidised institutions were named in the State Children Act 1907.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01282b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Inmate Subsidy
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Subsidised institutions were those institutions that were paid an 'inmate subsidy' or 'capitation grant' for eligible children accommodated there.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Subsidised Institution', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Subsidised Institution</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01489b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000093.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Child Welfare Amendment Act (No 2) 1976 (WA)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Child Welfare Amendment Act (No 2) 1976 (WA)</title>
<imprint>
<date>1976</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.slp.wa.gov.au/legislation/statutes.nsf/main_mrtitle_5034_homepage.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000090.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1962 (WA)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Child Welfare Act Amendment Act 1962 (WA)</title>
<imprint>
<date>1962</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.slp.wa.gov.au/legislation/statutes.nsf/main_mrtitle_6448_homepage.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000085.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Child Welfare Act 1947 (WA)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Child Welfare Act 1947 (WA)</title>
<imprint>
<date>1947</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.slp.wa.gov.au/legislation/statutes.nsf/main_mrtitle_7632_homepage.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000081.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: State Children Act Amendment Act 1927 (WA)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">State Children Act Amendment Act 1927 (WA)</title>
<imprint>
<date>1927</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.slp.wa.gov.au/legislation/statutes.nsf/main_mrtitle_8638_homepage.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000078.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: State Children Act 1907 (WA)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">State Children Act 1907 (WA)</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>State Law Publisher of Western Australia</publisher>
<date>1907</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.slp.wa.gov.au/legislation/statutes.nsf/main_mrtitle_9527_homepage.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>