<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>WE01029</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCWA</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Glossary Term</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-04-24">2013-04-24</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Debra Rosser</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-04-06">2016-04-06</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01029b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>concept</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Eugenics</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1910-01-01">1910s</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1950-12-31">1950s</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Social Movement</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Eugenics was a pseudo-scientific social movement based on distorted beliefs about 'fit' and 'unfit' people. In Western Australia, eugenics influenced policies and practices towards people with disabilities, particularly intellectual disabilities. Eugenicists believed that they could breed out mental deficiency by segregating and sterilising the 'unfit'. Although their direct intervention waned from the 1930s, the legacy of the eugenicists was the segregation of people with intellectual disabilities from the community in WA. This did not really change until the 1970s.</abstract>
<p>Eugenicists had two main concerns: increasingly visible poverty, illness and crime that was a consequence of industrialisation and urbanisation; and a falling birthrate among the middle classes offset by rising birthrates among the poor of all nations but especially 'non-white' races.</p>
<p>Eugenicists held three beliefs that influenced their practices and the policies they tried to implement in WA:</p>
<list><item>Poverty, crime and 'mental deficiency' were linked</item>
<item>Healthy living and the encouragement of good breeding could restore the social balance</item>
<item>The 'unfit' should be stopped from breeding through 'locating, then registering, and finally segregating or sterilising them' (Gillgren, p.65).</item></list>
<p>From 1910, children with intellectual disabilities who lived at home were given remedial education at the public Perth Infants' School but this approach lapsed as the eugenics movement took hold. In 1911, Dr WP Birmingham who was a senior member of the Board of Visitors of the Claremont Hospital for the Insane, reported on his review of facilities for people with intellectual disabilities in England, Germany and the United States of America. Birmingham began his report by defining and classifying 'mental deficiency' as congenital or acquired. Congenital defectives had three sub-groups: idiot, imbecile and feeble-minded. Birmingham stated that mental deficiency was incurable and had a genetic basis.</p>
<p>Consistent with eugenicist beliefs, Birmingham reported that mental defectives were susceptible to heightened sexuality and promiscuity (particularly females), to crime, and were generally a threat to white, civilised society. These people could, however, be productively put to work if they were kept in a controlled and segregated environment. Birmingham has been considered quite moderate is his eugenicist views because he opposed sterilisation.</p>
<p>Birmingham's report had no immediate impact on practices in WA, possibly because he also advocated for government investment in cottage homes, industrial training and workshops. The Inspector of Public Charities' report in 1913 confirmed that children with intellectual disabilities were indeed languishing in homes for the aged and insane. The Inspector found it regrettable but wrote that these children were 'unfitted for unrestricted liberty' and there was a need to avoid their multiplication. After World War One, though, the 'stagnant pool of Western Australian lunacy reform' was stirred (Gillgren, p.67). The 1919 Angwin Select Committee on the Claremont Hospital for the Insane recommended establishing a separate institution and Board of Commissioners for mental defectives. In November 1920, <span style="font-style:italic">The West Australian</span> newspaper urged the protection and segregation of mentally defective children before they, too, grew to neglected adulthood and 'spread the disease' through uncontrolled breeding.</p>
<p>The Royal Commission in Lunacy in 1922 also concentrated on segregation for 'the safety of the public and the well-being of the race' (Gillgren, p.68). The eugenicists in Perth had their best chance of success with the Mental Deficiency Bill in 1929. This sought to statutorily segregate people with intellectual disabilities into custodial institutions. A Select Committee was set up to review the Bill, which lapsed due to a lack of support for sterilisation and the cost of the proposed facilities and programs. However, the legacy of the Bill was a widespread belief in the value of segregating children with intellectual disabilities from the community, even if it was too costly to try and segregate them from the insane.</p>
<p>Pockets of eugenicists survived World War II. In September 1950, <span style="font-style:italic">The West Australian</span> newspaper asked Perth religious and civic leaders to respond to the Anglican Bishop of Birmingham Dr Barne's claim that 'degenerate human stock was increasing too rapidly'. Speaking to the British Society for the Advancement of Science, Bishop Barnes advocated 'mercy killing' of 'children born horribly defective or deformed' and the sterilisation of mental defects, saying that while sterilisation was only partially effective in preventing further births, 'half a loaf was better than no bread'. Bishop Barnes' views were not widely supported by those of Perth's religious and social welfare leaders who were asked to comment by <span style="font-style:italic">The West Australian</span>. The Anglican Archbishop of Perth Dr Moline said that the 'unfortunate accident by which Dr. Barnes is a bishop does not give any authority to his views' which did not represent the views of the Anglican Church. A spokesman for the Roman Catholic Archbishop Dr Prendiville said the methods advocated by the Bishop were 'condemned by the divine and natural law'. Congregational Church minister Rev. Bryant was not prepared to make a 'snap judgement' on the issue of sterilisation. The president of the Women's Service Guild, Mrs D Bulford, didn't wish to generalize, saying that each case 'must be considered on its individual merits and be a matter for individual responsibility and conscience'. The president of the National Council of Women, Mrs JB Carmody, said that 'no Christian could accept' views on sterilisation which coincided 'with those of the late lamented Hitler…the application of these practices would send us back to a state of barbarism'. Finally, the newspaper reported that the president of the WA branch of the British Medical Association, Dr AB Wilson, 'said that he felt the subject was one requiring individual interpretation according to man's outlook on divinity, but he declined to comment further'.</p>
<p><span style="font-style:italic">The Daily News</span> also published responses to Bishop Barnes' statements. Under the heading 'Four out of five Perth people agree with Bishop Barnes', the article aired the views of five Perth citizens. As a small snapshot of the attitudes towards intellectual disability in Perth in the 1950s, it would seem that eugenicist principles lived on in some people's hearts and minds. It was certainly the case that children with disabilities in Western Australia continued to be hidden away from the public gaze in the same institutions that had been identified as inadequate before World War One.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01038b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Royal Commission in Lunacy, State of Western Australia (1921 - 1922)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01036b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Select Committee to inquire into the management of the Claremont Hospital for the Insane (1919)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01034b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Moral Defective (1920s - 1950s)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01030b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Select Committee of the Legislative Assembly on the Mental Deficiency Bill (1929)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00999b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Claremont Mental Hospital (1903 - 1972)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00990b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Intellectual Disability
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE00453b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Mentally Deficient
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Eugenics', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Eugenics</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Western Australia</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/biogs/WE01029b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000984.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Four out of five Perth people agree with Bishop Barnes</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Four out of five Perth people agree with Bishop Barnes</title>
<imprint>
<date>1950</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Daily News</title>
<num type="pages">9</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article84483891"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000937.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Menace of tainted human stock</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Menace of tainted human stock</title>
<imprint>
<date>1950</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The West Australian</title>
<num type="pages">3</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article47884536"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000851.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Eloquent Testimony : the Story of the Mental Health Services in Western Australia, 1830-1975</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Ellis, A.S.</name>
<title render="italic">Eloquent Testimony : the Story of the Mental Health Services in Western Australia, 1830-1975</title>
<imprint>
<place>Nedlands, Western Australia</place>
<publisher>University of Western Australia Press</publisher>
<date>1984</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/wa/bib/WP0000850.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book Section: Once a Defective, always a Defective: Public Sector Residential Care 1900-1965</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Gillgren, Christina</name>
<title render="quoted">Once a Defective, always a Defective: Public Sector Residential Care 1900-1965</title>
<imprint>
<place>Perth</place>
<publisher>Centre for Disability Research and Development, Faculty of Health and Human Sciences, Edith Cowan University</publisher>
<date>1996</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Under blue skies : the social construction of intellectual disability in Western Australia</title>
<name type="author">Errol Cocks</name>
<num type="pages">53-91</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>