<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>NE00066</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCNS</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Organisation</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2011-03-03">2011-03-03</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Naomi Parry</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-06-28">2016-06-28</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00066b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Mittagong Farm Home for Boys</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Mittagong State Home</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Mittagong Children's Farm</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Industrial Farm Home for Boys, Mittagong</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Child Welfare Farm Home for Boys</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Farm Home for Boys</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Industrial Farm Home for Boys</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>State Home, Mittagong</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1906-01-01">1906</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1947-12-31">1947</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Juvenile Justice Centre</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Cottage Care</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Home</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Children's Home</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Government-run</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Farm School</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Mittagong Farm Home for Boys was established at Mittagong in 1906. It was a government-run Probationary Training Home for boys aged 8 to 17 who had been convicted in the Children's Courts. Mittagong Farm Home for Boys was part of Mittagong Cottage Homes. It became the Mittagong Training School For Boys in 1947.</abstract>
<p>The Mittagong Farm Home opened on 17 October 1906. It was situated on land already used as cottage-style accommodation for state children who were sick or invalid. Mittagong was organised on the cottage system, with an officer and his wife attached to each home. When Gosford Farm Home opened in 1912 Mittagong Farm Home was reserved for younger boys.</p>
<p>In November 1914 Charles Mackellar, the President of the State Children's Relief Board wrote to <span style="font-style:italic">The Sydney Morning Herald</span> to defend the Mittagong Farm Homes against criticisms made in the same paper by the Catholic Archbishop Dr Kelly. Mackellar's letter gives an overview of the approach of the State Children's Relief Board to the discipline, care and religious instruction of the children at the home:<br />
'The report says that at a meeting of the Westmead Catholic Homes for Boys "Dr Kelly said that the institution (i.e., the Westmead Home) was a home in the true sense of the word - not like the State Home at Mittagong with its prison conditions, where nearly every child had a policeman's hand on his shoulder, etc., etc." I shall refrain from stigmatising Dr Kelly's remarks in any harsher way than by saying that they give an absolutely incorrect idea of the management of the Mittagong Farm, and I would invite you to send one of your reporters to examine the Mittagong Homes and inquire into the methods used to control the children there, and report the result In your columns.<br />
'</p>
<p>Kelly's remarks were probably exaggerated. The goal of organisations like Westmead was to ensure Catholic children did not receive Protestant religious instruction and Kelly was undoubtedly urging donors to fund the homes, just as some Protestant clergymen encouraged donors to fund Protestant children's homes by condemning Catholics. But Mackellar was so angry he wrote to Cardinal Moran and copied his letter to the newspaper.</p>
<p>Mackellar told Cardinal Moran that Archbishop Kelly had in fact visited Mittagong four years previously and had praised it. He pointed out that the State Children's Relief Board tried to look after the spiritual welfare of Catholic children by employing Catholic staff, sending them to a Catholic service on Sundays and allowing visits from the neighbouring Marist Brothers community. Mackellar then described the discipline at Mittagong Farm Homes:<br />
'The discipline of the institution was referred to by the Archbishop as being in effect little different to that of a prison. Now, if there is one attribute making for successful reformation which the department has ever striven after in its treatment of children in these [state] institutions it is that the whole system shall be as unlike the old method in its attempts at reformation as it is possible to have it. Barrack like buildings have been superseded by cottages, bright with their own gardens and replete with every comfort suggesting "home." The officials approach the home idea altogether, in that a man and wife ("mother" and "father") are in charge of each cottage. No uniforms are worn by officials or children, no bolts bars, or locks are visible or allowed, and the children are given the greatest amount of liberty compatible with proper order and discipline. They go to the public school from their respective homes to their various avocations at the farm, workshops, etc … Where, then, is the semblance even of prison discipline?'</p>
<p>Later in November 1914 the <span style="font-style:italic">Herald</span> visited Mittagong and wrote a glowing article that called Mackellar 'The Children's Friend':<br />
'In the visitors' book in the largest of the homes [run by Mr and Mrs AE Boswell] someone has written: "Helping those who never had a chance." And that is the truth of it. The lads who are there have been taken from the evil surroundings of former days and placed in a home that is scrupulously neat and clear, and is bright with beautiful flowers. They have been taken from parents who have wilfully neglected them, or have confessed their inability to control them, and in those at the head of the home they find new and better parents, who spend their lives in trying to make good citizens of them. Some stay but a few months and are allowed to go back to their own homes, though they still remain under the protecting care of probation officers. Some stay for a considerable time, and after being taught a trade are apprenticed out and given a fair chance in the world. All who are under 14 years of age are sent to school, "and a bright and intelligent lot they are, too," said Mr Thresher, the headmaster of the school.'</p>
<p>According to this report there were two cottages in town, which held 50 girls who did most of the laundry, sewing and housework for the institution. On a 640 acre site three miles from town were eight boys' cottages, which held 300 boys.</p>
<p>The <span style="font-style:italic">Herald</span> correspondent was sympathetic to the boys' stories, describing one who was committed at 13 to Mittagong because he had run away from work. He told the journalist he had done so because he was working from dawn until 7pm every day skinning rabbits, but only got 2 shillings a week. Other boys were brought in because they had been sleeping out, or committed minor thefts. The journalist certainly felt most of them accepted their situation:<br />
'The first few days are the hardest-to bear. The child arrives among strangers in a strange part of the country, and his thoughts naturally go back to the home he has left no matter how bad a home it has been. But he very soon settles down to the new life, and begins to enjoy it. His pinched face fills out, and with a comfortable bed to sleep on and plenty of good food to eat, with happy companions and, above all, the kind mother heart of the matron beating for him as if he were her own child, he very soon forgets his troubles, and settles down as "one of the boys." '</p>
<p>According to this journalist, the discipline at the home taught self-reliance and independence.<br />
'In a word, they are put upon their honour. And there is nothing inherently bad in these boys and girls, taken as a whole-they have simply lacked a restraining influence in the past, and have been allowed, so to speak, to grow wild.'</p>
<p>Of religious matters, the journalist said the children were divided on sectarian lines: Catholics were cared for by Catholic house parents and Protestants were cared for by Protestant parents, and all children learned to say their prayers, to say grace and walked into Mittagong every Sunday to attend their own churches.</p>
<p>In 1947 this Institution became known as Mittagong Training School for Boys. The Mittagong Cottages were later renamed Renwick, and closed in the early 1990s. The site was sold by the New South Wales Government in the 1990s, to Landcom, and is being subdivided and developed, resulting in substantial loss of buildings and heritage.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1906-01-01">1906</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1947-12-31">1947</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Mittagong</placeEntry>
<event>Location - Mittagong Farm Home for Boys was situated at Mittagong</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00037b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
State Children's Relief Board (1881 - 1923)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1906-01-01">1906</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1923-12-31">1923</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00039b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Child Welfare Department, State Government of New South Wales (1923 - 1970)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1923-01-01">1923</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1947-12-31">1947</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01079b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
'Sobraon' Training Ship (1892 - 1911)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The 'Sobraon' Training Ship was used until 1911 when the remaining boys were sent to the Mittagong Farm Home for Boys and the Brush Farm Reformatory.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00930b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Records relating to State Wards, New South Wales (1881 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01149b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Gosford Training School (1923 - 1945)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Boys were sometimes transferred from Mittagong Farm Home to Gosford Training School if they offended at the Farm Home, or the Farm Home was overcrowded.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01086b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Registers Of Committals (1907 - 1921)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01576b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Place">
Mittagong Cottage Homes Area (1896 - 1994)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01152b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Renwick Association Inc (2011 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00993b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Feeble-Mindedness
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00992b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Mental Deficiency (c. 1905 - c. 1960)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00404b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Berry Training Farm (1934 - 1977)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Boys from Turner and Suttor Cottages at Mittagong Farm Home for Boys were sent to Berry Training Farm when they reached the age of 14.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00971b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Cottage Homes
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00136b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Marist Brothers (1872 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Marist Brothers had a community next door to the Mittagong Cottages and the Mittagong Farm Home, and brothers provided religious instruction to Catholic state wards.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01153b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Mittagong Cottage Homes (1885 - 1976)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1906-01-01">1906</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1947-12-31">1947</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Mittagong Farm Home for Boys was part of Mittagong Cottage Homes.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00403b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Anglewood (1943 - 1994)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1943-01-01">1943</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1945-12-31">1945</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Mittagong Farm Home for Boys administered Anglewood from 1943 to 1945, and boys from Turner and Suttor Cottages were transferred there in that period.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-later" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00496b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Mittagong Training School For Boys (1947 - 1976)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Mittagong Farm Home for Boys', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Mittagong Farm Home for Boys</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00066b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000717.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Mittagong Farm Homes: Renwick Mittagong NSW: Caring for disadvantaged and delinquent children 1885-1994</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Knapman, Leonie</name>
<title render="italic">Mittagong Farm Homes: Renwick Mittagong NSW: Caring for disadvantaged and delinquent children 1885-1994</title>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.talktome.bigpondhosting.com/renwick.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000013.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Farm Home For Boys, Mittagong (1906-1947) / Mittagong Training School For Boys (1947-1976) [State Records NSW Agency number 506]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Farm Home For Boys, Mittagong (1906-1947) / Mittagong Training School For Boys (1947-1976) [State Records NSW Agency number 506]</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>State Records Authority of New South Wales</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">SRNSW collection catalogue</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://search.records.nsw.gov.au/agencies/506"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000021.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Renwick (Mittagong Farm Home for Boys) web site</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Anson, Bill</name>
<title render="italic">Renwick (Mittagong Farm Home for Boys) web site</title>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://web.archive.org/web/20130410184643/http://www.renwick.com.au/smf/index.php"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000097.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Children In Need: An account of the administration and functions of the Child Welfare Department, New South Wales, Australia: with an examination of the principles involved in helping deprived and wayward children</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">McLean, Donald</name>
<title render="italic">Children In Need: An account of the administration and functions of the Child Welfare Department, New South Wales, Australia: with an examination of the principles involved in helping deprived and wayward children</title>
<imprint>
<place>Sydney</place>
<publisher>Government Printer</publisher>
<date>1955</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000100.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Article: Reap as you sow</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Matthews, Bernie</name>
<title render="quoted">Reap as you sow</title>
<imprint>
<date>2007</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Griffith Review, Edition 16: Unintended Consequences</title>
<num type="pages">10</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="https://griffithreview.com/articles/reap-as-you-sow/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000137.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Child Care and Protection Guide</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Child Care and Protection Guide</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>State Records Authority of New South Wales</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">State Records Authority of New South Wales website</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="https://www.records.nsw.gov.au/archives/collections-and-research/guides-and-indexes/child-care-and-protection-guide"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000187.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: They'll All Enjoy Christmas Parties</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">They'll All Enjoy Christmas Parties</title>
<imprint>
<date>1933</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Australian Women's Weekly</title>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000459.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Index to Child Care and Protection</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Index to Child Care and Protection</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>State Records NSW</publisher>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.records.nsw.gov.au/state-archives/indexes-online/indexes-to-education-and-child-welfare-records/index-to-child-care-and-protection"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000001.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Connecting Kin: Guide to Records</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Thinee, Kristy and Bradford, Tracy</name>
<title render="italic">Connecting Kin: Guide to Records</title>
<imprint>
<place>Sydney, New South Wales</place>
<publisher>New South Wales Department of Community Services</publisher>
<date>1998</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.community.nsw.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0008/319256/connectkin_guide.pdf"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000577.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: The Children's Friend: Sir Charles Mackellar: Mittagong Homes. A great work. Those who never had a chance.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">The Children's Friend: Sir Charles Mackellar: Mittagong Homes. A great work. Those who never had a chance.</title>
<imprint>
<date>1914</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Sydney Morning Herald</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://trove.nla.gov.au/ndp/del/article/15572189"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000850.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Challoner Cottage, Mittagong Farm Home [Other names: Cottage No.12, Old Dormitory Building, Renwick Child Welfare House, Mittagong Training School for Boys, Renwick Farm Home, Renwick State Ward Home]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Challoner Cottage, Mittagong Farm Home [Other names: Cottage No.12, Old Dormitory Building, Renwick Child Welfare House, Mittagong Training School for Boys, Renwick Farm Home, Renwick State Ward Home]</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>NSW Office of Environment and Heritage</publisher>
<date>1999-</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">State Heritage Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.environment.nsw.gov.au/heritageapp/ViewHeritageItemDetails.aspx?ID=5062002"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000842.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Challoner Cottage - Mittagong</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Downie, Leeallison</name>
<title render="quoted">Challoner Cottage - Mittagong</title>
<imprint>
<date>2013</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Heritage Watch NSW</title>
<name type="author">Greater Western Sydney Heritage Action Group and the NSW Heritage Network Inc - Linked To Protect</name>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.heritagewatchnsw.org.au/challoner-cottage-mittagong.php"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000844.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Hassall and Jefferis Cottages [Cutler's Inn, Government or Mittagong Farm Home, Kangaroo Inn]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Hassall and Jefferis Cottages [Cutler's Inn, Government or Mittagong Farm Home, Kangaroo Inn]</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>NSW Office of Environment and Heritage</publisher>
<date>1999-</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">State Heritage Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.environment.nsw.gov.au/heritageapp/ViewHeritageItemDetails.aspx?ID=5045486"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000845.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Rowe Cottage [Mittagong Training School Group]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Rowe Cottage [Mittagong Training School Group]</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>NSW Office of Environment and Heritage</publisher>
<date>1999-</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">State Heritage Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.environment.nsw.gov.au/heritageapp/ViewHeritageItemDetails.aspx?ID=2680276"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000846.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Goodlet Cottage: Mittagong Training Centre Group</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Goodlet Cottage: Mittagong Training Centre Group</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>NSW Office of Environment and Heritage</publisher>
<date>1999-</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">State Heritage Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.environment.nsw.gov.au/heritageapp/HeritageItemImage.aspx?ID=2680277#ad-image-0"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000847.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Renwick Child Welfare House</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Renwick Child Welfare House</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>NSW Office of Environment and Heritage</publisher>
<date>1999-</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">State Heritage Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.environment.nsw.gov.au/Heritage/listings/stateheritageregister.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000848.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Renwick Group</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Renwick Group</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>NSW Office of Environment and Heritage</publisher>
<date>1999-</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">State Heritage Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.environment.nsw.gov.au/heritageapp/ViewHeritageItemDetails.aspx?ID=2680275"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000849.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Suttor House: Mittagong Training Centre Group</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Suttor House: Mittagong Training Centre Group</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>NSW Office of Environment and Heritage</publisher>
<date>1999-</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">State Heritage Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.environment.nsw.gov.au/heritageapp/HeritageItemImage.aspx?ID=2680194#ad-image-0"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000576.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: The Mittagong Children's Farm</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">The Mittagong Children's Farm</title>
<imprint>
<date>1914</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Sydney Morning Herald</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article15541576"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000670.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Suttor House: Mittagong Training School Group</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Suttor House: Mittagong Training School Group</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1991</unitdate>
<note label="rights">JRC Planning</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000668.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Goodlet Cottage: Mittagong Training Centre Group</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Goodlet Cottage: Mittagong Training Centre Group</unittitle>
<unitdate>1991</unitdate>
<note label="rights">JRC Planning</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000669.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Challoner Cottage viewed from Bong Bong Road [Mittagong Farm Home, Cottage No.12, Old Dormitory Building, Renwick Child Welfare House, Mittagong Training School for Boys, Renwick Farm Home, Renwick State Ward Home]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Challoner Cottage viewed from Bong Bong Road [Mittagong Farm Home, Cottage No.12, Old Dormitory Building, Renwick Child Welfare House, Mittagong Training School for Boys, Renwick Farm Home, Renwick State Ward Home]</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 2012</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Louise Thom, NSW Office of Environment and Heritage</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000667.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Rowe Cottage [Mittagong Training School Group]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Rowe Cottage [Mittagong Training School Group]</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1991</unitdate>
<note label="rights">JRC Planning</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000663.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Extension of apple orchard, Mittagong Farm Home</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Extension of apple orchard, Mittagong Farm Home</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1908</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a copy of an image from the State Children's Relief Board Annual Report of 1908</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000662.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Mittagong the Farm Home for Boys</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Mittagong the Farm Home for Boys</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1907</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a copy of an image from the State Children's Relief Board Annual Report of 1907</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000661.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Mittagong Cottage Home Farm</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Mittagong Cottage Home Farm</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1907</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a copy of an image from the State Children's Relief Board Annual Report of 1907</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000224.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Heffernan [Mittagong Homes]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Leonie Knapman</repository>
<unittitle>Heffernan [Mittagong Homes]</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1948</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a digital copy of a photograph from an album collected by Child Welfare Department officers in the late 1940s. From the collection of Leonie Knapman.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Leonie Knapman, 59 Regent Street, Mittagong NSW 2575</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000004.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Child Welfare Farm Home for Boys, Mittagong - poultry farm</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Child Welfare Farm Home for Boys, Mittagong - poultry farm</unittitle>
<unitid>NSW Government Printing Office 1 - 32186</unitid>
<unitdate>1938</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the State Library of New South Wales</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>