<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>NE01494</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCNS</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Archival Series</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-11-01">2013-11-01</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Ann McCarthy</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-07-27">2016-07-27</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01494b.htm</entityId>
<entityId localType="ISMAPNG Archives Stanmore Repository Series Number">Series 003</entityId>
<entityType>concept</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Notices of Reception, Discharge, Death or Admission to Hospital of a Child</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1970-01-01">1970</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1977-12-31">1977</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Notices of Reception, Discharge, Death or Admission to Hospital of a Child is an archival series held by the Institute of Sisters of Mercy of Australia and Papua New Guinea Archives, Stanmore. The records relate to St Joseph's Orphanage, Goulburn, and to St John's Home, Auburn St, Goulburn. This Series is made up of one volume containing handwritten completion of forms to comply with the provisions of the Child Welfare Act 1939--Regulations 47A(w) and 47b(g), at the time of the closure of the Orphanage in 1975. Entries are for girls only.</abstract>
<h4>Access Conditions</h4>
<p> Application for access must be made, in writing, to the Archivist, providing personal identification documents to establish the right to access information. Physical access to the records is not permitted due to their fragility and the need to protect the confidentiality of information concerning other persons. Information will be forwarded by mail.</p>
<h4>Records</h4>
<p>The Notices of Reception, Discharge, Death or Admission to Hospital of a Child are managed by the Institute of the Sisters of Mercy of Australia and Papua New Guinea (ISMAPNG). ISMAPNG formed out of the consolidation of 14 of the 17 congregations of the Institute of the Sisters of Mercy in Australia, and from the region of Papua New Guinea. This included the Goulburn Congregation, which ran St Joseph's Orphanage, Goulburn and St John's Home, Auburn Street, Goulburn. St John's Home, Auburn St, Goulburn provided care for both girls and boys, and resulted from the amalgamation of St John's Boy's Home, Goulburn and St Joseph's Girls' Home, Goulburn in 1976.</p>
<p>The information in the register in this Series includes: Name and Address of Children's Home; Details of Child: Surname, Christian names, Date of birth, Sex; Details of Reception: Previous address, Date admitted; Details of Discharge/Transfer: Date of discharge/transfer, to whom discharged/transferred, Address of person to whom discharged/transferred, Relationship to child, Whether child was discharged/transferred with a view to adoption; Death: Date of death, Place of death, Cause of death, Duration of last illness, Attending medical practitioner, Officer-in-charge, Police Station location, Date of notification to Police Officer-in-charge; Admission to Hospital: Nature of illness, Name of hospital, Date of admission.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01489b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Institute of Sisters of Mercy of Australia and Papua New Guinea Archives, Stanmore (2012 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01490b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Contact Details">
Institute of Sisters of Mercy of Australia and Papua New Guinea Archives, Stanmore - Contact Details (2012 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00165b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Sisters of Mercy, Goulburn Congregation (1859 - 2011)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00169b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
St John's Home, Auburn Street Goulburn (1976 - 1987)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Notices of Reception, Discharge, Death or Admission to Hospital of a Child include records from St Johns' Home, Auburn Street, Goulburn.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00167b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
St Joseph's Orphanage, Goulburn (1864 - 1975)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Notices of Reception, Discharge, Death or Admission to Hospital of a Child include records from St Joseph's Orphanage, Goulburn.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Notices of Reception, Discharge, Death or Admission to Hospital of a Child', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Notices of Reception, Discharge, Death or Admission to Hospital of a Child</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01494b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>