<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>NE01277</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCNS</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Organisation</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-04-26">2013-04-26</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Naomi Parry and Liam Hogan</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2015-12-03">2015-12-03</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01277b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Ormond Training School</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Ormond</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Ormond Thornleigh</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Thornleigh Training School</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Thornleigh Girls' Home</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Ormond School, Thornleigh</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1962-01-01">1962</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1977-12-31">1977</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Reformatory</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Home</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Government-run</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Ormond Training School in Thornleigh, or Ormond School, was officially proclaimed and gazetted in October 1962. It had previously been called Ormond, Thornleigh, and had been an annexe to Parramatta Girls Training School. Ormond Training School was a facility for up to 104 girls, mostly school aged, and was a School for Specific Purposes. In 1976 it ceased to house girls, and boys from Mittagong Training School were sent there. Ormond Training School closed in 1977. Three years later Ormond School opened in the same buildings. The Duffy Avenue area later became known as Westleigh.</abstract>
<p>From 1946 to 1962, the site at Ormond had been a relatively small 'privilege' home for girls at Parramatta who were either ending their sentences, or who had behaved well. In 1961, however, reacting to a series of riots and disturbances at the Parramatta Girls Training School, the Child Welfare Department greatly expanded the Ormond/Thornleigh site from two cottages housing 28 girls, to a large complex housing 104 girls.</p>
<p>The Department wanted to divide up the girls at Parramatta into groups, with the better behaved housed at Thornleigh, away from those at Parramatta and the new institution at Hay. The 1961 Child Welfare Department Annual Report described the planned new system:</p>
<p>'When the main institution at <span style="font-style:italic">Thornleigh</span> is in use, there will be much greater opportunity to segregate those girls whose previous behaviour has indicated that they are likely to respond quickly to the educational, social and cultural programmes that are available, from the more sophisticated girls for whom a more rigidly disciplined training is essential for the development of stability and self-control.<br />
'</p>
<p>The new buildings were costly. The Child Welfare Department Annual Report of 1966 stated:</p>
<p>'Completed in 1962 at a cost of almost $1,000,000 to a unique design which combines security with a sense of space, freedom and graciousness, Ormond School accommodates delinquent girls, mainly in the 12 to 15 age group.'</p>
<p>The Ormond Training School was itself divided. Most of the girls were under the age of 15, and attended an internal school, while the older cottages were used as a 'Privilege Section' within Ormond. The Child Welfare Department report stated that girls selected to live in these privilege cottages and who were over school age went out 'to work in one or two local stores, and so prepare better for eventual discharge'.</p>
<p>The curriculum seems to have been deliberately designed to affect personality changes. There was an arrangement with the Hornsby and District Hospital for tattoo removal, and the school was described by the Child Welfare Department in a 1962 pamphlet as 'a practical expression of modern conception in re-education of delinquents'. It went on to describe the school's content:</p>
<p>'General education is continued with courses in dressmaking, cookery and other Home Science subjects. Under specialist teachers training is correlated with the many aspects of home life. … Through dress, deportment and cultural activities, opportunities are provided for personality adjustments.'</p>
<p>A former resident of the home in this time described the institution in a submission to the Senate Community Affairs Reference Committee Inquiry into Children in Institutional Care:</p>
<p>'At Ormond the punishment there for being disobedient, such as talking when you weren't supposed to consisted of scrubbing cement courtyards on your hands and knees with a tooth brush (I have always been curious, with the amount of girls scrubbing courtyards with toothbrushes, why the department never wondered why so many were needed).</p>
<p>Other forms of punishment were 24 hour periods of isolation, hours of bed drill, which consisted of stripping the bed and each sheet and each blanket would be inspected by an officer and if it wasn't correct with envelope corners and no wrinkles you would be instructed to remove it and put it on again until the bed was completed, then start the procedure over again and this could go on for a few hours at a time.</p>
<p>The shower cubical consisted of half doors where an officer would be continually watching you; again you were given no privacy. Every Saturday morning we would have to go into a cubical, undress, wrap ourselves in a towel and an officer would instruct us one at a time to come out of the cubical and she would look over our bodies, legs, arms then we would be instructed to drop the towel for further inspection.</p>
<p>We attended school on the grounds of Ormond two to three days a week the rest of the time we were washing, cooking, cleaning and mending.'</p>
<p>Louise Ellis, who spent time at Ormond in 1971 or 1972, contacted Find &amp; Connect looking for information about it, and agreed to share her memories of her time there. She paints a vivid picture of the buildings and the regime, including the distress girls suffered:</p>
<p>'Standing in front of Ormond on the outside was a building we called Privileged Cottage as that is where the girls on their last part of their stay lived and ate. Then there was the administration offices in middle at front, down the left hand side were a hall for movies and stuff, school rooms and then laundry.</p>
<p>Working their way down to the bottom of property, still on [the] left were isolation cells, horrible cement rooms with the air vents that you get in walls but down near the floor. You had a bed like a camp bed, one blanket and maybe there were three or four cells, not sure, but not very nice to be locked in there and forgotten about for 48 hours like [an officer] did to me for singing in line once. Yes I realise I can't sing but that really was an over reaction I think. Anyway the bottom fence was a tall wire fence, there was a swimming pool down that end but I only remember using that once.</p>
<p>On the other side were the three separate dormitories, I can't remember the names for them off hand. The dormitory was a building that consisted of kitchen and dining room, a hall down to the recreation room opposite that was the bathroom toilet area, then the dormitory was three sections of six beds or eight beds with lower wall petitioning each section, with a glass window from rec room where officers could check on you without entering. At the far end was a section the size of a normal doorway with those bessemer bricks, not the solid ones. That was the breezeway into the dormitory, it could be close[d] off in bad weather. Of course all doors to all rooms were always locked.</p>
<p>Then [there] was the entrance they brought new girls in. Just near the door was another room they locked you in before processing &amp; don't know why but that was dark. I was locked in with this girl I didn't know who arrived with me. We both sat there quietly not knowing what each other was like &amp; when they came to get us she had pulled all her eyelashes out reek. Anyway right near that room was the office they processed you in then next to that they had other rooms for dentists and doctors and hair cutting.</p>
<p>Then you're back up to the admin offices at front. I can't remember if we had a nickname for Ormond itself. I hope this helps with your description of Ormond, it was mostly red brick and wire or bessemer bricks all round.'</p>
<p>Louise Ellis also told Find &amp; Connect her recollections of the scrubbing she had to do:</p>
<p>'Yes we did have to scrub the cement outside, even in the rain but I remember using a normal wooden scrubbing brush and a rag to wipe the area, in 12 inch squares. The toothbrush was only when you were really bad LOL.'</p>
<p>Ormond continued to operate as a child welfare institution for girls until December 1976, when it received boys from the Training School for Boys, Mittagong, which had just closed. The school closed in 1977.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1962-01-01">1962</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1977-12-31">1977</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>Thornleigh</placeEntry>
<event>Address - Ormond Training School was situated at 72-78 Duffy Avenue, Thornleigh</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-earlier" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01062b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Ormond, Thornleigh (1946 - 1962)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00041b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Department of Youth, Ethnic and Community Affairs, State Government of New South Wales (1975 - 1976)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00040b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Department of Youth and Community Services, State Government of New South Wales (1976 - 1988)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00036b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Department of Youth and Community Services, State Government of New South Wales (1973 - 1975)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00035b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Department of Child Welfare and Social Welfare, State Government of New South Wales (1970 - 1973)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01377b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
School for Specific Purposes (1923 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01278b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Ormond School (1980 - 1984)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Ormond School occupied the buildings that had previously been used by Ormond Training School</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01183b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Marie Wood interviewed by Ann-Mari Jordens in the Forgotten Australians and Former Child Migrants oral history project [sound recording] (13 May 2010)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01185b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Effie Ray interviewed by Joanna Penglase in the Forgotten Australians and Former Child Migrants oral history project [sound recording]
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00930b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Records relating to State Wards, New South Wales (1881 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01318b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Parramatta Girls Training School (1946 - 1974)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1962-01-01">1962</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1977-12-31">1977</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Ormond Training School was an annexe of Parramatta Girls Training School</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00496b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Mittagong Training School For Boys (1947 - 1976)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1976-01-01">1976</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1976-12-31">1976</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>When Mittagong Training School was closed the boys were sent to Ormond.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-later" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01278b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Ormond School (1980 - 1984)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Ormond Training School', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Ormond Training School</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01277b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000412.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Annual Report: Child Welfare Department of New South Wales</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Child Welfare Department</name>
<title render="italic">Annual Report: Child Welfare Department of New South Wales</title>
<imprint>
<date>1955-1970</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000813.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Child Welfare in New South Wales</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Department of Child Welfare and Social Welfare</name>
<title render="italic">Child Welfare in New South Wales</title>
<imprint>
<place>Sydney</place>
<publisher>Child Welfare Department</publisher>
<date>c 1962</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000759.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Westleigh, New South Wales</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Westleigh, New South Wales</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Wikipedia</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westleigh,_New_South_Wales"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000405.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Submission 272</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Submission 272</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Commonwealth of Australia</publisher>
<date>2005</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Inquiry into Children in Institutional Care - Submissions received by the committee as at 17/3/05</title>
<name type="author">Senate Community Affairs Committee</name>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.aph.gov.au/Parliamentary_Business/Committees/Senate/Community_Affairs/Completed_inquiries/2004-07/inst_care/submissions/sublist"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000400.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Newcastle Public Industrial School for Girls (1867-1871) / Biloela Public Industrial School for Girls (1871-1887) / Parramatta Industrial School for Females (1887-1912) / Girl's Training Home, Parramatta (1912-1975) / Kamballa (1975-1983) [State Records NSW Agency number 460]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Newcastle Public Industrial School for Girls (1867-1871) / Biloela Public Industrial School for Girls (1871-1887) / Parramatta Industrial School for Females (1887-1912) / Girl's Training Home, Parramatta (1912-1975) / Kamballa (1975-1983) [State Records NSW Agency number 460]</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>State Records Authority of New South Wales</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">SRNSW collection catalogue</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://search.records.nsw.gov.au/agencies/460"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000118.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Abandon All Hope: a history of Parramatta Industrial School</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Djuric, Bonney</name>
<title render="italic">Abandon All Hope: a history of Parramatta Industrial School</title>
<imprint>
<place>Georges Terrace</place>
<publisher>Chargan</publisher>
<date>2008</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000100.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Article: Reap as you sow</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Matthews, Bernie</name>
<title render="quoted">Reap as you sow</title>
<imprint>
<date>2007</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Griffith Review, Edition 16: Unintended Consequences</title>
<num type="pages">10</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="https://griffithreview.com/articles/reap-as-you-sow/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/bib/NP0000106.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Wilma's Story</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Matthews, Bernie</name>
<title render="italic">Wilma's Story</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Online Opinion</publisher>
<date>2007</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.onlineopinion.com.au/view.asp?article=6236&amp;page=0"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000608.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Swimming is a favourite sport at Ormond School</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Swimming is a favourite sport at Ormond School</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1963</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a scan of an image that appeared in the Child Welfare Department Annual Report of 1963</abstract>
<note label="rights">Child Welfare Department [NSW Department of Community Services]</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000607.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Morning assembly at Ormond School. The new classrooms adjoin the Recreation Room (showing on extreme left)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Morning assembly at Ormond School. The new classrooms adjoin the Recreation Room (showing on extreme left)</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1968</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a scan of an image that appeared in the Child Welfare Department Annual Report of 1968</abstract>
<note label="rights">Child Welfare Department [NSW Department of Community Services]</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/objects/ND0000606.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">A dormitory at Ormond School, Thornleigh, with outlook on the School's swimming pool and tennis courts</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>A dormitory at Ormond School, Thornleigh, with outlook on the School's swimming pool and tennis courts</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1966</unitdate>
<abstract>This is a scan of an image that appeared in the Child Welfare Department Annual Report of 1966</abstract>
<note label="rights">Child Welfare Department [NSW Department of Community Services]</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>

<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>