<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>NE01109</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCNS</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Archival Series</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2012-03-28">2012-03-28</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Naomi Parry</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2018-02-01">2018-02-01</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01109b.htm</entityId>
<entityId localType="State Records Authority of New South Wales Series Number">11</entityId>
<entityType>concept</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Applications for Certificates of Exemption</part>
<part localType="parent">Board for the Protection of Aborigines</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1930-01-01">1930</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1964-12-31">1964</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Applications for Certificates of Exemption is a series of records created by the Board for the Protection of Aborigines, and the Aborigines Welfare Board. Certificates of Exemption could be granted to an applicant who, in the opinion of the Aborigines Welfare Board, ought to no longer be subject to the provisions of the Aborigines Protection Act and Regulations 1909-43, Section 18c (Regulation 56). Upon being issued with a Certificate of Exemption, a recipient was no longer eligible to receive any benefit, assistance or relief from the Board, and had to undertake to provide a proper home for himself/herself and his/her family.</abstract>
<h4>Access Conditions</h4>
<p>Due to the sensitive nature of these records access is restricted. Persons wishing to view these records must first contact the Department of Aboriginal Affairs.</p>
<h4>Records</h4>
<p>Most files in this series contain two official application forms for exemption (one form titled Application for Exemption from Provisions of Aborigines Protection Act and Regulations thereunder, and the other titled Personal Report on Applicant for Exemption from Provisions of Aborigines Protection Act and Regulations thereunder) and correspondence relating to the outcome of the application.</p>
<p>The Application for Exemption from Provisions of Aborigines Protection Act and Regulations thereunder records full name of applicant, caste [please note this is the language as it is used in the record], address, age, name; address and occupation of referees.</p>
<p>The Personal Report on Applicant for Exemption from Provisions of Aborigines Protection Act and Regulations thereunder is divided into sections. Section one gives full name, full address, age at last birthday, date of birth, caste [please note this is the language as it is used in the record], colour shade [please note this is the language as it is used in the record], and present state of health. Section two states particulars of family, including spouse and all children under the age of eighteen; providing: name, sex, relationship to the applicant, age, caste [please note this is the language as it is used in the record], colour shade [please note this is the language as it is used in the record], and remarks. Section three details employment particulars such as: nature of present employment, date of commencement, and whether permanent or temporary. This section also lists employment during the past two years, with space for three entries. Section four documents the general conduct of the applicant, including: drinking habits, gambling habits, thrift, morality, and any facts known about the spouse in relation to the above headings. Section four also specifies the nature of the present home, cleanliness and general condition of the home, improvements to the home, and care of the children. Section five reports on income and capital of the husband and wife, including: weekly wages, child endowment, pension, any other sources of income, cash in hand, bank deposits, bonds, other savings, and totals. The final section of the form records general remarks and recommendations, signature of the recording official, official designation, date, and address.</p>
<p>Other documents in these files can include the following: correspondence requesting application forms; personal references attesting to the character of the applicant; press clippings; police or welfare officers reports on applicants, photographs, certificates of exemption, expulsion orders and requests to have individuals removed from areas, correspondence from solicitors and Commonwealth agencies re pensions, requests for maternity allowance, reports on child endowment payments, requests for replacement certificates of exemption, and extracts from Aborigines Welfare Board Minutes.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01638b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
New South Wales State Archives Collection (1788 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01469b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Contact Details">
Department of Aboriginal Affairs - Contact Details
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01529b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Exemption Certificate (1943 - 1969)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01110b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Certificates of Exemption, Aborigines Welfare Board (1949 - 1954)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00016b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
Aborigines Protection (Amendment) Act 1943 (1943 - 1969)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00033b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Aborigines Welfare Board (1940 - 1969)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE00034b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Aborigines Protection Board (1883 - 1940)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Applications for Certificates of Exemption', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Applications for Certificates of Exemption</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - New South Wales</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/nsw/biogs/NE01109b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>