<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>TE00415</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCTS</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Tasmania</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Organisation</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2012-03-29">2012-03-29</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Caroline Evans</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2017-04-28">2017-04-28</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00415b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporatebody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="Also known as"><part>Tasmanian Institute for the Blind and Deaf</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="Also known as"><part>Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institute</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1898-01-01">1898</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1987-12-31">1987</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Disability Institution</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Hostel</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Home</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution, run by the Society for the Blind, Deaf and Dumb, opened in North Hobart in 1898. It provided an education and industrial training to adults and children with hearing and sight disabilities. There was accommodation for the country children who attended the school on the site. The Institution closed in 1997.</abstract>
<p>The Institution had a welfare section, a school which opened in 1901, and a small factory. The school had two sections, one for children who were blind and the other for those who were deaf. Their education reflected the Institution's belief in the dignity of manual work and the importance of developing the mind.</p>
<p>Children who were blind learned knitting, net making, simple fancy work, the piano, history, geography, scripture, Braille, and Moon Type, a system of raised curves, angles, and lines, which was supposed to be easier to learn than Braille. By the 1920s, the curriculum had expanded to include other handcrafts such as bead work or making papier maché. The children also learned to swim. A group known as the Braille Writers developed a Braille library that children and adults could use.</p>
<p>There were two approaches to teaching children who were deaf. One supported the children's deaf culture, which they expressed through sign language. The other sought to assimilate them into mainstream society by teaching them to lip read and speak. At first, influenced by the Quaker educationalist, Samuel Clemes, the first President of the Institution, the school taught both methods. In the beginning of 1912, with the appointment of a new teacher, the emphasis moved towards teaching speech and lip reading. That remained the trend.</p>
<p>Parents whose children had intellectual disabilities and speech problems often sent them to the school because there were no alternatives. However, the teachers sometimes found them difficult to manage and in 1918, the Committee called publicly for these children to have a school of their own. Five years later, the Committee changed direction when Edmund Morris Miller, an academic at the University of Tasmania, the Director of the State Psychological Clinic, and Chairman of the Mental Deficiency Board, became President. He accepted children with intellectual disabilities into the school because he believed they had a right to an education and that the school was the best place for them because they were often blind, deaf or unable to speak. Miller would have liked to base the State Psychological Clinic at the Institution but other Board members refused.</p>
<p>In 1923, the Institution's financial difficulties led to an inquiry. It recommended, without success, that the Education Department take over the school. Even so, this was, according to Joy Smith, the 'first step into what would eventually be a State monopoly of special education'.</p>
<p>In 1925, the headmaster was found guilty of stealing from the Institution's funds and sentenced to two months in prison. A former student, the Reverend Nat Sonners, remembered lining up on the front steps with the other students to see him driven away in disgrace for sentencing. The trial led to a Royal Commission into the Institution's affairs. It criticised the admission of children with intellectual disabilities, the purchase of a farm which did not make money, and the failure to collect fees from parents. It recommended a restructure of the Institution's management with five government nominees on the controlling body and a chairman also nominated by the government.</p>
<p>The Institution seems to have recovered both its finances and reputation by the 1930s. It was incorporated by an Act of Parliament in 1933.</p>
<p>In 1949, New Town Primary School introduced a special class for children who were partially deaf to prepare them to attend an ordinary school. They continued to board at the Institution. The same year, Professor Alexander Ewing and Dr Irene Ewing visited. They were Manchester University academics and advocates of teaching speech and lip reading. The Ewings were concerned that the children with partial deafness would be held back because, in the evenings when they went back to the Institution, they reverted to sign language with the children who were deaf. In 1952, this led to the opening of Wyadra, a hostel specifically for children with partial deafness.</p>
<p>The numbers of children at the Institution who were blind were always fewer than those who were deaf. As methods of preventing blindness improved, less children suffered from it. In 1933, this had led the school to accept children with partial sight. Teachers hoped that, with professional help, they would eventually be able to go to ordinary schools. The Sight Saving School, which evolved out of this idea, opened in March 1940 on the grounds of the Elizabeth Street Practicing School. The aim was to prevent further loss of sight and to teach the children Braille. This left only two children with blindness at the Institution. They too transferred to the Sight Saving School. Even so, the School for the Blind continued sporadically until it finally closed in 1972.</p>
<p>Many of the children at the school came from outside Hobart. From the beginning, the Institution provided accommodation for them. The premises were at Brickfields in North Hobart, originally a nursery and female convict hiring depot, then an immigrant depot, and finally an invalid depot, which closed in 1882. By 1897, when the Institution acquired it, the only remaining building was a 10 room house. This is where the children lived and attended school.</p>
<p>As the numbers of children in the school increased, they needed more accommodation. In 1907, a partial second storey was added to the previously single storied building. In 1916, the second storey was extended across the whole of the building. It included new dormitories, an open air sleeping area for 'delicate' children, a kitchen, staff rooms, bathrooms, and toilets. During the building operations, the children moved temporarily to Stowell, a house in Battery Point.</p>
<p>In 1945, with the numbers of children needing accommodation still rising, the government bought a large house opposite the Institution in Lewis Street and leased it back. Twenty-two children stayed there. In October 1946, a new extension provided accommodation for another 25. Girls lived at Lewis Street while boys remained in the old building.</p>
<p>In 1961, Lady Rowallen House, a purpose built school for children with deafness, opened at Campbell Street School. Those from outside Hobart boarded at the Institution. In 1972, after a pre-school class began, the Institution set up a pre-school dormitory for about 10 children in the Lewis Street house. Parents could stay there while young children settled in.</p>
<p>By the end of the 1970s, children with disabilities were increasingly attending their local schools. This meant that numbers at the hostels declined. There were only 16 children at Lewis Street when it closed in 1976. The hostel in the main building closed in 1982.</p>
<p>The Institution's functions were now completely different to its original purpose. It no longer offered an education or accommodation to children. From now on, until its closure in 1987, it would be mostly concerned with adults.</p>
<p>The Institution closed in 1987, following the recommendation of the Arthur Young Review of Services. The review also recommended that the Society for the Blind, Deaf and Dumb split into two separate organisations, the Royal Guide Dogs and the Tasmanian Deaf Society or Tasdeaf.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1898-01-01">1898</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1987-12-31">1987</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>North Hobart</placeEntry>
<event>Location - The Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution was in North Hobart</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00418b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Society for the Blind, Deaf and Dumb (1887 - 1987)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00651b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
Education Act (1932 - 1942)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Many of the children coming under the <span style="font-style:italic">Education Act</span> 1932 were sent to the Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00650b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
Education Act (1905 - 1932)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Many of the children coming under the <span style="font-style:italic">Education Act</span> 1905 were sent to the Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00200b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Mental Deficiency Board (1922 - 1964)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Edmund Morris Miller, the third President of the Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution, was also the Chairman of the Mental Deficiency Board.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00223b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
State Psychological Clinic (1922 - 1964)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Edmund Morris Miller, the third president of the Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution was also the Director of the State Psychological Clinic.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00569b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Sight Saving School (1940 - 1980)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Children from outside Hobart who attended the Sight Saving School boarded at the Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution. The Sight Saving School evolved out of the school run by the Institution for children who were blind.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00419b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Arthur Young Review of Services (1986)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>In 1986, the Arthur Young Review of Services recommended that the Society for the Blind, Deaf and Dumb, which ran the Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution, be split into two.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00417b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Admission Register, School for the Blind (1959 - 1972)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Admission Register contains historical information about the Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00416b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Admission Register, School for the Blind and Deaf (1924 - 1969)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Admission Register contains historical information concerning the Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00562b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Case Files, Tasmanian Institute for the Blind, Deaf and Dumb; Tasmanian Deaf Society (1914 - 2006)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Application and Case Files concern children placed in the Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00424b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Collection">
Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution Records held by Royal Guide Dogs Tasmania (1887 - 1987)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00545b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Wyadra Hostel (1952 - 1957)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution, which was also a Home, ran Wyadra Hostel.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-later" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00421b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Royal Guide Dogs Tasmania (1987 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-later" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00420b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Tasdeaf (1987 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Tasmania</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Tasmania</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00415b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000391.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Education of the blind</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Education of the blind</title>
<imprint>
<date>1931</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Mercury</title>
<num type="pages">9</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article29919643"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000390.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Education of the blind</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Education of the blind</title>
<imprint>
<date>1931</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Mercury</title>
<num type="pages">8</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article29919221"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000389.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Education of the deaf</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Education of the deaf</title>
<imprint>
<date>1931</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Mercury</title>
<num type="pages">3</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article29914741"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000388.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Educating the deaf</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Educating the deaf</title>
<imprint>
<date>1931</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Mercury</title>
<num type="pages">3</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article29914397"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000387.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Clemes, Samuel (1845-1922)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Oats, William N.</name>
<title render="quoted">Clemes, Samuel (1845-1922)</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Centre of Biography, Australian National University</publisher>
<date>1981</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Australian Dictionary of Biography</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://adb.anu.edu.au/biography/clemes-samuel-5683/text9603"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000348.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Those afflicted make appeal for aid</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Those afflicted make appeal for aid</title>
<imprint>
<date>1954</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Mercury</title>
<num type="pages">12</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-page1933131"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000265.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Time is the builder: a history of the Royal Tasmanian Society for the Blind and Deaf, 1887-1987</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Smith, Elizabeth Joy</name>
<title render="italic">Time is the builder: a history of the Royal Tasmanian Society for the Blind and Deaf, 1887-1987</title>
<imprint>
<place>Hobart</place>
<publisher>Elizabeth Joy Smith</publisher>
<date>1989</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000264.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: The Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Smith, Joy</name>
<title render="quoted">The Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Centre for Tasmanian Historical Studies</publisher>
<date>2006</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Companion to Tasmanian History</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.utas.edu.au/library/companion_to_tasmanian_history/B/Blind,%20Deaf%20and%20Dumb%20Institution.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000080.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, student at work, 1951 to 1973</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Tasmanian Images: Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</repository>
<unittitle>Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, student at work, 1951 to 1973</unittitle>
<unitid>TAHO Reference: AB713-1-8666</unitid>
<unitdate>1951 - 1973</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000079.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, student at work, 1951 to 1973</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Tasmanian Images: Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</repository>
<unittitle>Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, student at work, 1951 to 1973</unittitle>
<unitid>TAHO Reference: AB713-1-8667</unitid>
<unitdate>1951 - 1973</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000078.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired girl reading Braille text, possibly then transcribing to Braille typewriter, 1951 to 1976</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Tasmanian Images: Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</repository>
<unittitle>Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired girl reading Braille text, possibly then transcribing to Braille typewriter, 1951 to 1976</unittitle>
<unitid>TAHO Reference: AB713-1-8962</unitid>
<unitdate>1951 - 1976</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000077.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired girl reading Braille text, possibly then transcribing to Braille typewriter, 1951 to 1976</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Tasmanian Images: Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</repository>
<unittitle>Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired girl reading Braille text, possibly then transcribing to Braille typewriter, 1951 to 1976</unittitle>
<unitid>TAHO Reference: AB713-1-8963</unitid>
<unitdate>1951 - 1976</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000076.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired girl reading Braille text, possibly then transcribing to Braille typewriter, 1951 to 1973</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Tasmanian Images: Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</repository>
<unittitle>Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired girl reading Braille text, possibly then transcribing to Braille typewriter, 1951 to 1973</unittitle>
<unitid>TAHO Reference: AB713-1-8964</unitid>
<unitdate>1951 - 1973</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000075.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired girl reading Braille text, possibly then transcribing to Braille typewriter, 1951 to 1973</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Tasmanian Images: Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</repository>
<unittitle>Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired girl reading Braille text, possibly then transcribing to Braille typewriter, 1951 to 1973</unittitle>
<unitid>TAHO Reference: AB713-1-8965</unitid>
<unitdate>1951 - 1973</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the Tasmanian Archive and heritage Office</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000074.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired boy writing on a Braille typewriter, 1951 to 1973</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Tasmanian Images: Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</repository>
<unittitle>Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired boy writing on a Braille typewriter, 1951 to 1973</unittitle>
<unitid>TAHO Reference: AB713-1-8966</unitid>
<unitdate>1951 - 1973</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000073.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired boy reading a Braille map, 1951 to 1973</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Tasmanian Images: Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</repository>
<unittitle>Blind &amp; Deaf Institute, visually-impaired boy reading a Braille map, 1951 to 1973</unittitle>
<unitid>TAHO Reference: AB713-1-8967</unitid>
<unitdate>1951 - 1973</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by the Tasmanian Archive and Heritage Office</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000072.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Tasdeaf: Tasmanian Deaf Society</repository>
<unittitle>Blind, Deaf and Dumb Institution</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1905</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by Tasdeaf: Tasmanian Deaf Society</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>