<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>TE00093</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCTS</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Tasmania</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Place</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2011-02-03">2011-02-03</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Caroline Evans</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2017-08-14">2017-08-14</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00093b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>place</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Cape Barren Island Reserve</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="Also known as"><part>The Reserve</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1881-01-01">1881</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1951-12-31">1951</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Anglican</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Cape Barren Island Reserve was created in 1881 for the use of the descendants of Aboriginal women and European sealers living in the Furneaux Islands of Bass Strait. From the late 1920s, many Aboriginal children were removed from their parents on Cape Barren Island. It ceased to be a reserve in 1951.</abstract>
<p>Following the death of Trucanini in 1876, most white Tasmanians believed that there were no more Aborigines left alive. Yet the descendants of Aboriginal women and white sealers continued to live on the Furneaux Islands. In 1871, the Islanders petitioned the Governor for a reserve and the exclusive use of the mutton bird rookeries. Instead they received two ten hectare blocks on Cape Barren Island for homesteads and agricultural pursuits. In addition, the rookeries on Chapell and Big Dog Islands were gazetted under the <span style="font-style:italic">Game Preservation Act</span>. According to Lyndall Ryan, by its actions, the government accepted that the Islanders were a separate community but did not acknowledge that they had exclusive rights because of their Aboriginality. Following a series of missions by the Anglican Church, pressure from Canon Marcus Brownrigg, who sought to increase Anglican influence on the Island, and a campaign by the Islanders, the government set aside 2500 hectares for the Islanders. It became known as 'the reserve'.</p>
<p>For the first 20 years 'the reserve' was jointly run and funded by the government and the Anglican Church. However, it did not have a residential mission and the missionary/school teacher had few powers because in Tasmania there was no Aboriginal protection legislation. From the beginning of the twentieth century, the Church's role declined significantly.</p>
<p>The <span style="font-style:italic">Cape Barren Island Reserve Act</span> of 1912 provided for the subdivision of the Cape Barren Island Reserve into homesteads and agricultural blocks specifically for the use of the descendents of Aboriginal women and white sealers living in the Furneaux Group of islands. Persons named in the schedule and their descendants and widows could apply to occupy the land rent free. Licenses could be bequeathed to widows or descendants but if a widow married a white man she lost the licence. The residents had to live continuously in their houses for six months of the year. Anyone over twenty-one years of age who was not a licenced occupier or lessee could be removed from the Reserve. The state government wanted to encourage Islanders to move to the mainland so they made it possible for them to obtain a license to lease Crown land elsewhere in Tasmania. The Act provided for regulations to be made to control the residents. The purpose of the Act was to force the Cape Barren Islanders to become self sufficient agriculturalists.</p>
<p>In the 1920s, the mutton bird industry, and therefore the Islander economy, began to decline. In 1928, AW Burbury of the Fauna Board visited Cape Barren Island. He recommended that the children should be removed as soon as they left school and put to work as domestic servants or in trades on mainland Tasmania. The government did not act. However, from 1928 to 1980, the head teacher at the school was appointed special constable. This enabled him to use the existing child welfare legislation to arrest children for neglect so that they could become wards of state. He sometimes used a shed at the back of the school to lock them up. No specific legislation was ever passed in Tasmania to remove Aboriginal children.</p>
<p>According to the <span style="font-style:italic">Bringing them home</span> report, poverty, alcoholism, and the refusal to become the agriculturalists envisaged in the <span style="font-style:italic">Cape Barren Island Act</span>, meant that the Islanders risked losing their children. Another issue was that the Islanders relied on each other to help out with their children. Authorities saw this, not as a strength, but an indication of neglect. Poverty and fear of losing their children led the Islanders to move to Invermay in Launceston or to mainland Australia. By 1944, there were only 106 left on the island.</p>
<p>That year, a new <span style="font-style:italic">Cape Barren Island Reserve Act</span> made it even more difficult for the Islanders to obtain a land grant. The idea was to force them to become self-sufficient agriculturalists or to leave the island. These policies appear to have specifically targeted the Islanders as Aborigines. In addition, socially and culturally, white Tasmanians recognised them as such. Yet the government did not. It continued to deny their Aboriginality claiming that as 'octoroons', they did not qualify.</p>
<p>By 1951, only one lessee was eligible for the land grant. The reserve closed. The government refused to help the Islanders, telling them that instead they must move to the mainland. Officials continued their efforts to remove Islander children from their families using the <span style="font-style:italic">Infant Welfare Act</span> of 1935 and later, the <span style="font-style:italic">Child Welfare Act</span> of 1960. In theory, parents could go to court to argue against a charge of neglect against their child but in practice it was difficult for them to get to Launceston where the cases were heard. Parents could also be imprisoned for the neglect of one child which meant that the rest of the children would then be made wards of state as well.</p>
<p>The <span style="font-style:italic">Bringing them home inquiry</span> heard the following account of a boy's removal from Cape Barren island:</p>
<p>'The circumstances of my being taken, as I recollect, were that I went off to school in the morning and I was sitting in the classroom and there was only one room where all the children assembled and there was a knock at the door, which the schoolmaster answered. After a conversation he had with somebody at the door, he came to get me. He took me by the hand and took me to the door. I was physically grabbed by a male person at the door. I was taken to a motor bike and held by the officer and driven to the airstrip and flown off the island. I was taken from Cape Barren Island in October 1959 [aged twelve].</p>
<p>I had no knowledge [I was going to be taken], I was not even able to see my grandmother [and I had] just the clothes I had on my back, such as they were. I never saw Mum again.'</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE01001b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
John Morris interviewed by Lyn McLeavy in the Bringing them home oral history project [sound recording] (2000)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00999b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Dennis Daniels interviewed by Lyn McLeavy in the Bringing them home oral history project [sound recording] (2000)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00998b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Item">
Charles Saville interviewed by Lyn McLeavy in the Bringing them home oral history project [sound recording] (2000)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00034b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Northern Tasmanian Home for Boys (1921 - 1973)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Northern Tasmanian Home for Boys probably received children from Cape Barren Island Reserve.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00018b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Social Services Department, State of Tasmania (1934 - 1961)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Some children from Cape Barren Island Reserve became wards of the Social Services Department.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00016b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Children of the State Department, State of Tasmania (1918 - 1935)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Some children from Cape Barren Island Reserve became wards of the Children of the State Department.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00085b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Launceston Girls' Home (1921 - 1989)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Launceston Girls' Home probably received children from Cape Barren Island Reserve.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00056b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Roland Boys' Home (1951 - c. 1993)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Roland Boys' Home probably received children from Cape Barren Island Reserve.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00004b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
Child Welfare Act 1960 (1960 - 2003)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Children from Cape Barren Island were committed to the 'care' of the state as neglected under the <span style="font-style:italic">Child Welfare Act.</span></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00003b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
Infants' Welfare Act 1935 (1935 - 1961)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Children from Cape Barren Island were committed to the 'care' of the state as neglected under the <span style="font-style:italic">Infant Welfare Act</span>.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00017b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
The Children of the State Act 1918 (1918 - 1936)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Children from Cape Barren Island were committed to the 'care' of the state as neglected under the <span style="font-style:italic">Children of the State Act</span>.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00543b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
The Church of England in Australia and Tasmania (1788 - 1981)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>In conjunction with the state government, The Church of England In Australia and Tasmania ran the Cape Barren Island Reserve.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00688b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Reserve (1881 - 1951)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00225b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Stolen Generations
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Cape Barren Island Reserve', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Tasmania</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Cape Barren Island Reserve</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Tasmania</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00093b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000634.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Bringing them home: Report of the National Inquiry into the separation of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander children from their families</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Bringing them home: Report of the National Inquiry into the separation of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander children from their families</title>
<imprint>
<date>1997</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="https://www.humanrights.gov.au/publications/bringing-them-home-report-1997"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000354.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: God's own country?: the Anglican Church and Tasmanian Aborigines</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Boyce, James</name>
<title render="italic">God's own country?: the Anglican Church and Tasmanian Aborigines</title>
<imprint>
<place>Hobart</place>
<publisher>Social Action and Research Centre, Anglicare Tasmania</publisher>
<date>2001</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000011.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: For the record: background information on the work of the Anglican Church with Aboriginal children and directory of Anglican agencies providing residential care to children from 1830 to 1980</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Boyce, James</name>
<title render="italic">For the record: background information on the work of the Anglican Church with Aboriginal children and directory of Anglican agencies providing residential care to children from 1830 to 1980</title>
<imprint>
<place>Melbourne</place>
<publisher>Anglicare Australia</publisher>
<date>2003</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000156.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: The Aboriginal Tasmanians</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Ryan, Lyndall</name>
<title render="italic">The Aboriginal Tasmanians</title>
<edition>2nd</edition>
<imprint>
<place>St Leonards NSW</place>
<publisher>Allen and Unwin</publisher>
<date>1996</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000027.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Tasmania: legislation</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Tasmania: legislation</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Institute of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Studies</publisher>
<date>2008</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">To remove and protect: laws that changed Aboriginal lives</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://aiatsis.gov.au/collections/collections-online/digitised-collections/remove-and-protect/tasmania"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000065.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Homes and Orphanages</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Homes and Orphanages</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Care Leavers Australia Network</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Care Leavers Australia Network (CLAN)</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.clan.org.au/homes/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>