<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>TE00241</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:FCTS</agencyCode>
<agencyName>Find &amp; Connect - Tasmania</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Organisation</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2011-10-27">2011-10-27</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Caroline Evans</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2017-04-28">2017-04-28</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00241b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporatebody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Royal Derwent Hospital</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="Also known as"><part>Willow Court</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1968-01-01">1968</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="2000-12-31">2000</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Government-run</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Home</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Hospital</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Royal Derwent Hospital, formerly known as Lachlan Park, was renamed in 1968. It was in New Norfolk. That year, Millbrook Rise Psychopathic Hospital, also in New Norfolk, became a part of it and, in addition to the Lachlan Park site, a new complex opened on the eastern side of the Lachlan River. Lachlan Park and Millbrook Rise both housed children. The Royal Derwent Hospital closed in 2000.</abstract>
<p>In a 1944 report, Dr Catarinich, Victoria's Director of Mental Hygiene, condemned the buildings of Lachlan Park as too crowded, old-fashioned, unhygienic, and structurally unsound to carry out modern therapies. He recommended a new mental hospital and abandonment of the site. In 1949, a Parliamentary Standing Committee, appointed to comment on Dr Catarinich's findings, recommended that a new hospital be built on the eastern side of the Lachlan River using land bought in the nineteenth century to extend the hospital's pastoral and agricultural activities. Construction began in the 1950s. The new hospital opened in 1968.</p>
<p>The former Lachlan Park site on the western side of the Lachlan River did not close. Instead residents with mental illnesses were transferred across the river to the new site on the eastern side while those diagnosed with intellectual disabilities remained at the former Lachlan Park. In combination with the former Millbrook Rise Psychopathic Hospital, the two sites became the Royal Derwent Hospital. Lachlan Park was also known as Willow Court. The name came from a willow tree planted in the front court yard which was supposed to be a cutting from the one on Napoleon's grave in St Helena.</p>
<p>This roughly followed the recommendation of a 1964 Parliamentary Standing Committee on Public Works that the old Lachlan Park complex be used as a 'Mental Defectives Colony'. According to Dr JRV Foxton, Director of Psychiatric Services its purpose was:</p>
<p>'to care for mentally deficient patients, ranging from infancy to old age on one hand and from total idiocy to high-grade feeble mindedness on the other. Therefore provision [had] to be made for those who [were] totally dependent... For children adolescent [sic] and adults, and for patients who require secure detention to protect the public.'</p>
<p>These categories reflect those of the <span style="font-style:italic">Mental Deficiency Act</span> 1920.</p>
<p>The old Lachlan Park site housed about 400 people with intellectual disabilities, with just under a quarter of them children. The parents of many of those children had committed them on the advice of doctors but others were wards of state placed at the Hospital from various institutions because they had been classified as 'mentally deficient'. The Tasmanian Ombudsman's inquiry, which reported in 2004, received submissions from wards of state who had been in the Hospital.</p>
<p>A new development on the Lachlan Park site was the Female Maximum Security Ward known as Alonnah or Ward A, for girls classified under the <span style="font-style:italic">Mental Deficency Act</span>. This often meant, not an intellectual disability, but refusing to conform to social attitudes about sexual behaviour. Even though the <span style="font-style:italic">Mental Health Act</span> 1963, which superseded the <span style="font-style:italic">Mental Deficiency Act</span>, specifically stated that 'promiscuity' did not imply an intellectual disability, policy more suited to the old act appears to have persisted for a while. Miranda Morris ascribes this to a 'moral panic' about teenage girls and young women in the 1960s that led to the establishment of Weeroona Girls' Training Centre and a new women's prison at Risdon, as well as Alonnah Ward.</p>
<p>The walls of Alonnah were made of thick concrete and the windows were covered with metal grilles. There was one eight bed dormitory and 12 isolation cells for punishment. These had huge doors with one way peepholes, known as Judas windows, and asylum locks. The day rooms could be constantly surveyed from a glassed-in office on a dais. There was no privacy in the bathrooms. The only outside space was a small yard enclosed by 15 foot high concrete walls. With the help of a staff member, the girls made a little garden against the walls.</p>
<p>Some of the girls had employment in the occupational therapy centre, also on the site, packing pegs for the Pioneer Peg Factory in New Norfolk or collating for the Government Printer. They earned enough to buy cigarettes. Other activities included pottery, physical exercises, and playing a modified form of netball in the yard. There was a gramophone and TV. Bed time was at eight pm, except on the rare occasions the girls attended a social at the occupational therapy centre.</p>
<p>Although Alonnah was meant to be high security, by 1969, it was apparently more like an open ward. Only 10 girls lived there and they made a trip with staff to Maria Island that year. Morris suggests that Alonnah was 'obsolete even whilst it was being built'. The last girls left in 1985 and boys lived there temporarily. By 1990 it was closed and the building was used as a plant nursery in a sheltered work program for people with intellectual disabilities.</p>
<p>An oral history project conducted by Margaret Reynolds and Monica Hols led to the publication in 2011 of: <span style="font-style:italic">Remember the children: stories about the lives of young people in Tasmania's last mental institution, 1950-2000</span>. It contains stories from former residents of Millbrook Rise Psychopathic and Royal Derwent Hospitals, many of whom had traumatic experiences. Contributors to the book spoke of distressing treatments and children being unwashed, tied to their beds, and beaten as well as deprived of food, meaningful activity, and their own clothes. Similarly, <span style="font-style:italic">Through the window</span>, the autobiography of Rachel Greene, a former resident of the children's ward, briefly describes the very difficult childhood that she had there.</p>
<p>In the later years of the Royal Derwent Hospital, conditions improved. Contributors to <span style="font-style:italic">Remember the Children</span>, remember the staff as 'co-operative, courteous and helpful'. There was a special facility outside the ward where about 10 children could do activities supervised by two nurses.</p>
<p>When the Royal Derwent Hospital closed in 2000, residents, many of whom had been there since childhood, were sent back to their place of origin, sometimes to families who did not know that they existed. A number of lifelong friends were split up in the process. In 2013, former residents of the Hospital live in group homes and supported accommodation run by not-for-profit organisations. The former Lachlan Park site is registered by the Tasmanian Heritage Council.</p>
<p>The Ombudsman's <span style="font-style:italic">Review of claims of abuse from adults in state care as children: Final Report - Phase 2</span> of 2006 mentions the Royal Derwent Hospital.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1968-01-01">1968</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="2000-12-31">2000</toDate>
</dateRange>
<placeEntry>New Norfolk</placeEntry>
<event>Location - The Royal Derwent Hospital was in New Norfolk</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-earlier" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00502b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Millbrook Rise Psychopathic Hospital (1934 - 1968)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Royal Derwent Hospital took Millbrook Rise over in 1968.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="temporal-earlier" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00240b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Lachlan Park Hospital (1937 - 1968)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Royal Derwent Hospital was previously known as Lachlan Park.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00021b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Department of Community Services, State of Tasmania (1989 - 1993)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00579b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
The Mental Health Services Commission (1968 - 1989)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00342b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Rosebank Cottage for Disabled Children (1979 - c. 1994)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Rosebank Cottage was established in part so that children with disabilities were not sent to the Royal Derwent Hospital.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00562b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Case Files, Tasmanian Institute for the Blind, Deaf and Dumb; Tasmanian Deaf Society (1914 - 2006)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Application and Case Files include Royal Derwent Hospital diagnostic evaluations.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00333b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Veranto Lifestyle Assistance (2011 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Veranto Lifestyle Assistance manages some of the homes of former residents of the Royal Derwent Hospital.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00251b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
Mental Deficiency Act (1920 - 1963)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The terms of the Mental Deficiency Act underlay the establishment of Alonnah Ward at the Royal Derwent Hospital.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00010b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
Mental Health Act 1963 (1963 - 1999)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The Mental Health Act superceded the Mental Deficiency Act. Its statement that 'promiscuity' did not indicate intellectual disability did not immediately affect policy in Alonnah Ward at the Royal Derwent Hospital.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00199b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Mentally Deficient (c. 1920 - c. 1963)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00189b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Intellectual Disability (c. 1980 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00038b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Weeroona Girls' Training Centre (1959 - 1979)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Like Alonnah Ward at the Royal Derwent Hospital, Weeroona Girls' Training Centre was built during a period of concern about the behaviour of girls and young women.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00573b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Investigation of the care and treatment of 'socially maladjusted teenage girls', Sub-Committee of the Tasmanian Branch of the Australian Institute of Welfare Officers (c. 1975)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The report mentions the Royal Derwent Hospital.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00956b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Legislation">
Disability Services Act (2011 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>The <span style="font-style:italic">Disability Services Act</span> followed the closure of the Royal Derwent Hospital. It was intended to prevent the future use of institutions such as the Royal Derwent Hospital for the care of people with disabilities.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00608b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Hospital (c. 1820 - c. 1990)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00609b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Glossary Term">
Mental Hospital (c. 1960 - c. 1990)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00799b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Patient Records-Alphabetical Register of Patients, Royal Derwent Hospital (1888 - 1974)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00800b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Patient Records Removed from Case Books, Millbrook Rise Psychopathic and Royal Derwent Hospitals (1894 - 1979)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00745b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Archival Series">
Patient Files, Lunatic Asylum, Hospital for the Insane, Mental Diseases Hospital, Lachlan Park Hospital, and the Royal Derwent Hospital (1857 - 1993)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00639b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Division of Psychiatric Services (1963 - 1968)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00955b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Motion for Tri Party Support on Disability and Willow Court (2008)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00399b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Risdon Prison (1960 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Like Alonnah Ward at the Royal Derwent Hospital, the women's section at Risdon Prison was built during a period of concern about the behaviour of girls and young women.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Royal Derwent Hospital', in <span style="font-style:italic">Find &amp; Connect - Tasmania</span>, </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Royal Derwent Hospital</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Find &amp; Connect - Tasmania</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/biogs/TE00241b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000696.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Article: Tasmanian government declares never again to institution days</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Tasmanian government declares never again to institution days</title>
<imprint>
<place>Canada</place>
<date>2008</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Institution watch: international edition</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.institutionwatch.ca/cms-filesystem-action?file=newsletters/fall_2008_2.pdf"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000695.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Willow Court History Group</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Willow Court History Group</title>
<imprint>
<date>2014</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.willowcourttasmania.org/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000694.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Treatment of Mental Illness</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Tooth, John</name>
<title render="quoted">Treatment of Mental Illness</title>
<imprint>
<place>Hobart</place>
<publisher>Centre for Tasmanian Historical Studies</publisher>
<date>2005</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The companion to Tasmanian history</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.utas.edu.au/library/companion_to_tasmanian_history/M/Mental%20Illness.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000693.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Royal Derwent Hospital</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Tooth, John</name>
<title render="quoted">Royal Derwent Hospital</title>
<imprint>
<place>Hobart</place>
<publisher>Centre for Tasmanian Historical Studies</publisher>
<date>2005</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The companion to Tasmanian history</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.utas.edu.au/library/companion_to_tasmanian_history/R/Royal%20Derwent%20Hosp.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000082.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Review of claims of abuse from adults in state care as children - Final Report - Phase 2</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Ombudsman Tasmania</name>
<title render="italic">Review of claims of abuse from adults in state care as children - Final Report - Phase 2</title>
<imprint>
<date>2006</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000056.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Article: More calls for abused ward compensation clemency</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">More calls for abused ward compensation clemency</title>
<imprint>
<date>2007</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">ABC news</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2007/12/11/2115555.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000417.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Postcards from the asylum</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Knight, Karen</name>
<title render="italic">Postcards from the asylum</title>
<imprint>
<place>Lauderdale, Tasmania</place>
<publisher>Pardalote</publisher>
<date>2008</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000398.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Through the window</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Greene, Rachel</name>
<title render="italic">Through the window</title>
<imprint>
<place>Glenorchy, Tasmania</place>
<publisher>Rachel Greene</publisher>
<date>2007</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000394.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Report and recommendations of the care and treatment of 'Socially maladjusted teenage girls' in Tasmania</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Sub-Committee of the Tasmanian Branch of the Australian Institute of Welfare Officers</name>
<title render="italic">Report and recommendations of the care and treatment of 'Socially maladjusted teenage girls' in Tasmania</title>
<imprint>
<place>Hobart</place>
<publisher>Tasmanian Branch of the Australian Institute of Welfare Officers</publisher>
<date>1975 circa</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000001.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Listen to the children: Review of claims of abuse from adults in state care as children</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Ombudsman Tasmania</name>
<title render="italic">Listen to the children: Review of claims of abuse from adults in state care as children</title>
<imprint>
<place>Hobart</place>
<publisher>Office of the Ombudsman, Tasmania</publisher>
<date>2004</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000277.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Troubled asylum: the history of the Invalid Barracks, New Norfolk Colonial Hospital, New Norfolk Madhouse, New Norfolk Her Majesty's Lunatic Asylum, New Norfolk Mental Diseases Hospital, New Norfolk Lachlan Park, New Norfolk Royal Derwent Hospital</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Gowlland, RW</name>
<title render="italic">Troubled asylum: the history of the Invalid Barracks, New Norfolk Colonial Hospital, New Norfolk Madhouse, New Norfolk Her Majesty's Lunatic Asylum, New Norfolk Mental Diseases Hospital, New Norfolk Lachlan Park, New Norfolk Royal Derwent Hospital</title>
<imprint>
<place>New Norfolk</place>
<publisher>Self publication</publisher>
<date>1996</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000276.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Willow Court Asylum Complex: Tasmanian Heritage Entry</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Willow Court Asylum Complex: Tasmanian Heritage Entry</title>
<imprint>
<place>Hobart</place>
<publisher>Heritage Tasmania</publisher>
<date>2008</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000274.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Willow Court, Conservation Management Plan, Stage D, Alonnah/A Ward and Industrial Therapy</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Johnston, Paul, Strating, R, Morris, Miranda, and Small, T</name>
<title render="italic">Willow Court, Conservation Management Plan, Stage D, Alonnah/A Ward and Industrial Therapy</title>
<imprint>
<date>2006</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000267.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Remember the children: stories about the lives of young people in Tasmania's last mental institution, 1950-2000</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Reynolds, Margaret and Hols, Monica</name>
<title render="italic">Remember the children: stories about the lives of young people in Tasmania's last mental institution, 1950-2000</title>
<imprint>
<place>Hobart</place>
<publisher>National Disability Services</publisher>
<date>2011</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/bib/TP0000210.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: From tiny acorns mighty oaks grow: the history of Oaks Tasmania</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Alexander, Alison</name>
<title render="italic">From tiny acorns mighty oaks grow: the history of Oaks Tasmania</title>
<imprint>
<place>Glenorchy, Tasmania</place>
<publisher>Oak Tasmania</publisher>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000147.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">The outside of Alonnah as it looked in October 2012</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>The outside of Alonnah as it looked in October 2012</unittitle>
<unitdate>2012</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Courtesy of the photographer.</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000146.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">The dayroom at Alonnah as it looked in October 2012</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>The dayroom at Alonnah as it looked in October 2012</unittitle>
<unitdate>2012</unitdate>
<abstract>The nurses' station was higher than the dayroom so that nursing staff could look down on it. This established their authority.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Courtesy of the photographer.</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000145.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">The corridor in Alonnah as it looked in October 2012</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>The corridor in Alonnah as it looked in October 2012</unittitle>
<unitdate>2012</unitdate>
<abstract>The isolation cells are on either side of the corridor. The nurses' station was to the left at the end of the corridor. It overlooked the dayroom.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Courtesy of the photographer.</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000144.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">An isolation cell in Alonnah, Royal Derwent Hospital, as it looked in October 2012</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>An isolation cell in Alonnah, Royal Derwent Hospital, as it looked in October 2012</unittitle>
<unitdate>2012</unitdate>
<abstract>The heavy door which is lying on its side against the wall originally belonged to the cell. The windows had a shutter that could be closed at night. Many of the cells at Lachlan Park had the light switch outside the room so that residents had no control over it.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Courtesy of the photographer</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.findandconnect.gov.au/ref/tas/objects/TD0000106.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">The Royal Derwent Hospital after it closed</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>The Royal Derwent Hospital after it closed</unittitle>
<unitdate>2010</unitdate>
<abstract>Photographed by Korske Ana</abstract>
<note label="rights">Reproduction rights owned by Korske Ana.</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>